<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-03-13T17:02:46-06:00</updated><id>/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Sarah Constantin</title><subtitle>Math/machine learning person currently trying to solve aging and make sense of our world. Founder, www.daphnia-labs.com and www.thelri.org.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Intro Post</title><link href="/2020/03/13/intro-post.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Intro Post" /><published>2020-03-13T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2020-03-13T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>/2020/03/13/intro-post</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2020/03/13/intro-post.html">&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;layout: post
title: New Blog and Mainenance
categories: [blog meta]
___&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been blogging in various places for nearly a decade, but I’ve never actually hosted my own site, or consolidated all my writing in one place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But now it’s past time for me to start taking my writing/blogging more seriously.  I want it to be searchable and all in one place, and I want to own my own data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thankfully, Github now makes hosting easy, and supports the blogging framework Jekyll.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I always find it nice when people are transparent about their process, so I’ll share  mine: it’s taken me most of the last two days to learn Jekyll and get the site working, as well as saving all my writing from different blogs in .rtf files, one post at a time.
I still have another day of “grunt work” to add my backlog of posts into the new site, while editing to add links and formatting and images and tags. Could this be automated? Maybe, but I’m not sure how, or if it comes with more risk of messing it up, so I’m doing it by hand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On this site I’ll be aggregating my old posts from &lt;a href=&quot;https://srconstantin.wordpress.com&quot;&gt;Otium&lt;/a&gt;, my &lt;a href=&quot;https://srconstantin.posthaven.com&quot;&gt;Posthaven site&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://parentingwithevidence.wordpress.com&quot;&gt;Parenting with Evidence&lt;/a&gt;, and the now defunct Hourglass Bio, as well as potentially other stuff from my archive.  I’ll also be putting all my new posts here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll cross-promote posts on &lt;a href=&quot;//https://twitter.com/s_r_constantin&quot;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt; (where my handle is @s_r_constantin) and, of course, you can subscribe using RSS.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">layout: post title: New Blog and Mainenance categories: [blog meta] ___</summary></entry></feed>