<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://srconstantin.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://srconstantin.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-03-09T23:34:40-05:00</updated><id>https://srconstantin.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Sarah Constantin</title><subtitle>Trained in math and machine learning, currently trying to solve technological problems and make sense of our world.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Does It Pay To Do More Research?</title><link href="https://srconstantin.github.io/2021/03/08/does-it-pay-to-do-more-research.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Does It Pay To Do More Research?" /><published>2021-03-08T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-03-08T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://srconstantin.github.io/2021/03/08/does-it-pay-to-do-more-research</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://srconstantin.github.io/2021/03/08/does-it-pay-to-do-more-research.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Hypothesis&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do investors profit from spending more time and effort researching and analyzing their decisions?  Does it pay to be an “infovore” who seeks out an unusual amount of information?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s pretty obvious, and well-confirmed by the literature, that the &lt;em&gt;least&lt;/em&gt; info-seeking investors do poorly.  In stock markets, for instance, individual investors (e.g. day traders) get worse returns than institutional investors. Institutional investors have full-time professionals on staff and access to expensive information sources; individual investors typically know far less.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The interesting question is whether being unusually info-seeking correlates with having &lt;em&gt;higher&lt;/em&gt; than median returns, not whether being unusually ignorant correlates with having lower than median returns.  Do the most information-seeking investors earn the highest returns?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Motivation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This Venkat Rao &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/vgr/status/1277262959828283392&quot;&gt;thread &lt;/a&gt;claims that a major problem with society is that too many “rich people” are “lazy” when they make resource allocation decisions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;The word “invest” has 2 distinct meanings in relation to capital:


Invest (1): Spend money to build a capability. Example: a bridge, a factory, a mansion.


Invest (2): Spend money to acquire a formal stake in an existing capability. Example: stock, bond, lien.


2 now dominates 1.


The two are coupled. For example, you invest (2) in my company so I can invest (1) in a new factory. Instead of shareholder value or a dividend, you might claim a share of the output at a good price for example (offtakes, kinda like futures).


…


It’s a moral hazard to purely invest (2) in money-in-money-out (MIMO) ways. You have no interest in how black box works. All knowledge risk lies with investee. If your MIMO deal is not honored you can’t tell fraud apart from real problems. You can’t judge whether to grant relief.


This is the definition of dumb money. Of course most real investment (2) does informally include some appreciation of the underlying investment (1), but not in any way that is operationally specific. Few investors who play for even controlling stakes actually desire control.


Control in finance has come to mean “control of the board and ability to hire/fire top executives”, which is increasingly just too shallow to address the complexity of modern principal-agent relations. Money _wants _to be stupid because the rich don’t want to do invest (1) work.


Financialization, “shareholder value” as a disease, etc, all have their tools in a single psychological problem: the rich are really lazy. They don’t want to put in the work to make their money smart. They want to either swarm opportunities via imitation, or rely on “analysts.”


There is a lot of bullshit conservative sermonizing about how the poor deserve their fates because they don’t work hard and that’s why the economy suffers etc. This is not only not the problem, it’s not even true. Most economic problems arise from the rich not working hard enough.


If you have 10s of millions of dollars, it _matters_ how hard you, PERSONALLY, think about where to put it.  Even a single degree of delegation causes huge principal-agent distortions. To the extent that some wealth creation opportunities need concentrated capital, the rich must think.


Some rich do think and work hard but they think wide and shallow for “highest ROIC” (where the I is investment (2), not investment (1)) opportunities. They rarely think deep about how a particular investment (2) will drive the invest (1). They don’t care about the meaning of the money.


There is something deeply nihilistic, stupid, fearful, and acting-dead about this. If the only difference between 2 investments for you is return rates, and you are not curious about the futures implied by investing in either, you’re kinda dumb and boring.


…


This whole point is why I’m not a socialist. I don’t think it matters much who “owns” the capital. Whether it is a workers’ co-op or a fat-cat single rich person, the question is how hard they think.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a lot in this thread, a lot of it resonates with me, and I think it’s worth taking seriously enough to actually unpack the claims and investigate whether they’re literally &lt;em&gt;true.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I see it, Venkat is making two separate claims.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One is about the relationship between “investment (1)” and “investment (2)”, between constructing physical objects that produce value, and the abstracted process of spending money to turn it into more money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He seems to believe, and I share the same intuition, that the world would be a better place if more people who had the means to invest in big projects did so because they wanted those projects to exist, not just because they wanted the revenue stream.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Elon Musk &lt;em&gt;wants to go to Mars&lt;/em&gt;; he’s also trying to structure his companies to be profitable, but I’m pretty sure he would count it a failure if he made a bunch of money but humanity never became a multiplanetary species.  That’s the kind of thing Venkat is talking about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s natural, for kids at least, or for people imagining what they’d do with wealth vastly greater than their own, to think “If I ever have money, I’ll use it to do something &lt;em&gt;awesome&lt;/em&gt;.” You could make the world a better place, make your mark on history, or even just have a spectacularly good time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Venkat seems to be claiming that a.) the people who actually &lt;em&gt;have&lt;/em&gt; that much money rarely want to spend it on things they personally find awesome, and b.) it would be better for the world if they did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I share this intuition, but I don’t really know how I’d go about testing it.  Since there’s almost no public data about the psychology of rich investors, we have to rely on anecdote; and while a consultant like Venkat has met many rich investors, he’s seen a very selective picture of how they think and spend their time.  My own experience with rich investors is even more limited.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for how the world would be different if investors put money into projects that they valued for reasons other than revenue, I’m not sure how to seriously answer the question without an incredibly broad theory of economics and ethics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But Venkat is also making a narrower, more tractable claim: “the rich are really lazy.”  That is, investors do not “think hard” about where to put their money. In more neutral terms, investors underinvest in information-gathering and analysis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a testable hypothesis, at least if you only think about the financial self-interest of investors.  If the investors who are &lt;em&gt;most&lt;/em&gt; inclined to investigate/research/seek information are also earning the highest returns, then most investors are irrationally &lt;em&gt;neglecting&lt;/em&gt; research by comparison.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If investors tend to “underthink” relative to what would be economically rational, then they are &lt;em&gt;certainly&lt;/em&gt; underthinking relative to Venkat’s socially beneficial ideal, which includes not only considering the effect of an investment on your bank account, but also its effect on the rest of the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusions From The Literature&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of the evidence I could find comes from investments on public markets, since of course there’s far more data on the stock performance of publicly traded companies. I am less confident about what this means about private equity or venture capital investment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, engaging in more research into company fundamentals, and being in some sense “better at formal analysis”, &lt;em&gt;does&lt;/em&gt; correlate reliably with higher returns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hedge funds that make more in-person site visits to portfolio companies have higher returns. Site-visitors have annual returns 6.1 percentage points higher than non-visitors.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Investment firms that download more SEC filings have higher returns.  Downloaders (of any files) have annual returns 1.5 percentage points higher than non-downloaders.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Financial analysts who download SEC filings make more accurate forecasts than non-downloaders, and the longer they spend reading SEC filings, the more accurate their forecasts.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“Buy-side analysis” refers to the research and forecasting performed in-house by employees of investment firms. Mutual funds whose investment decisions more closely track the recommendations of their analysts have higher returns.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mutual fund managers who score higher on the Cognitive Reflection Test (a measure of how good people are at avoiding intuitive-but-wrong answers; strongly correlated with IQ) have funds with higher Sharpe ratios (the same returns, but less risk) than their low-scoring peers.  That is, roughly, being less prone to “jump to conclusions” is associated with better investment performance.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Angel investors who do more due diligence have a significantly higher proportion of their investments become “home runs”, defined as investments where the investor receives returns of at least 100% upon exit of the company.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Strikingly, the biggest downloader of public financial documents is Renaissance Capital, whose &lt;a href=&quot;https://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=3504766&quot;&gt;66% annual returns over the past 30 years&lt;/a&gt; dwarf anything else in the financial markets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seems to be the case that spending more time and effort on fact-finding that relates to fundamentals (reading financial documents, visiting factory sites, engaging in due diligence) and listening more closely to the employees who specialize in such research, is profitable – and thus that most firms underinvest in it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By contrast, “imitative information-seeking”, all things equal, seems to anticorrelate with investment returns and forecasting accuracy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Investment analysts who change their forecasts the most in response to changes in other analysts’ published forecasts have worse performance.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Investment firms tend to perform worse if their portfolios closely track changes in published financial analyst recommendations.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Investment firms that tend to buy stocks that have been in the news recently, have worse performance than investment firms that are less correlated with the news cycle.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basically, the evidence available to me suggests that Venkat is right. Institutional investors &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; perform better when they do more investigation into company fundamentals, and worse when they focus more on how other people perceive a company.  The median institutional investor would make more money if they were more investigative and less imitative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Information Seeking by Investment Analysts&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Investment analysts who download more publicly available data about firms tend to make more accurate price forecasts. Financial analysts whose recommendations correlate closely with the average of other financial analysts’ recommendations tend to perform worse than the contrarians.  This suggests that analysts who are good at research and do more of it make better predictions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Strangely, financial analysis firm &lt;em&gt;rankings&lt;/em&gt; were found to anticorrelate with the use of internal library resources at the firm (in a study published in 1997, when written information resources were mostly in hard copy.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Financial analysts who download more publicly available data about firms from EDGAR, the SEC database, perform better. Only 24% of analysts made an EDGAR download within a day before issuing a new recommendation update.  Those that did, had a 3.7% reduction in forecast error.  Spending more time reading reports also corresponds to better accuracy – each 1% increase in time spent reading files corresponded to an 0.8% increase in forecast accuracy.[1]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, analysts that base their recommendations more on public consensus tend to perform worse.  A measure of Reliance on Public Information (RPI) can be calculated for financial analysts based on the sensitivity of their recommendations to public variables like price momentum, earnings surprise, average turnover, change in consensus recommendation, and change in consensus earnings forecast.  A portfolio that follows stock recommendations of analysts in quintile 1 of RPI (the least reliant on public information) produces an average monthly return of 1.83%, or 22% a year.  Data was collected on 3480 analysts over the period 1993-2006; returns were calculated over the 31 days following a new recommendation.  Low-RPI analysts tend to recommend buying larger firms (factor loading -0.19, p&amp;lt;0.05), while high-RPI analysts tend to recommend shorting larger firms (factor loading (-0.21, p&amp;lt;0.05), and more high-priced firms (-0.29, p&amp;lt;0.05).[2]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A 1997 survey of 100 securities analysts from the largest UK and US investment firms found that firm ranking &lt;em&gt;negatively&lt;/em&gt; correlated (p&amp;lt;0.001) with the frequency that respondents answered that their staff checks the internal library.[3]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Information Seeking by Investment Funds and Fund Performance&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Use of Public Information&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Firms that download more publicly available files about their investments generally perform better than firms that do not.  Also, “short sellers” who make leveraged bets against firms earn more profit when they trade immediately after public news about a firm, suggesting that they are profiting from making better use of publicly available information than most investors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, firms whose investment choices are more closely correlated with the public advice of analysts generally perform worse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hedge funds that access more SEC filings online perform better. The most frequent downloader of all is Renaissance Technologies. Firms that download files have on average 1.5% higher annualized returns than firms that don’t.[4]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Users who download files from EDGAR, the official website where SEC filings are stored, can be traced to IP addresses corresponding either to institutional investors (e.g. Goldman Sachs, Morgan Stanley) or to individual “retail” investors.  There is no correlation between a firm’s future stock performance and how much its filings were downloaded by “retail” investors, but there is a positive correlation (p&amp;lt;0.01) between a firm’s future performance and how much its files were downloaded by institutional investors, and also a positive correlation (p&amp;lt;0.01) between a firm’s institutional-investor downloads and its subsequent change in holdings among those investors, particularly when the 10K filings have a positive overall “tone”, suggesting that institutional investors do in fact invest more in firms when the firms’ publicly available data is favorable.[4]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Short selling does not increase immediately before news about a stock is published, but does increase after, suggesting that short sellers are making their decisions on the basis of public news rather than anticipating that news.  Moreover, the returns on short sales are more than twice as high on days when there is news about a stock, which also suggests that short sellers are making better use of public information than other investors.[5]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Short-selling in the COVID-19 pandemic was more profitable for investors who had previously held a short position in any healthcare stock before, suggesting that investors with more familiarity with healthcare were more able to understand what was going on with COVID-19 and how it would affect stock prices.[6]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reliance on Public Information (RPI) is a measure of how sensitive an investor’s holdings are to changes in public information, in this case changes in analysts’ recommendations.  RPI is negatively correlated (r = -0.17) with Carhart 4-factor alpha, in a sample of 1696 mutual funds.[7]  Better funds use more private as opposed to public information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, if you construct a measure “RPI_σ” to represent the coefficients from regressing the change in a mutual fund’s % holdings on the change in the standard deviation of analysts’ recommendations, and compare the  RPI_σ of 1220 mutual funds to their fund performance, the correlation is significantly negative (p&amp;lt;0.05).  [8]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A measure (PTMC, Propensity to Trade with Media Coverage) of a mutual fund’s tendency to trade stocks more when they’re in the news, negatively correlates with fund performance. Over the period 1993-2002, stocks purchased by top-quintile PTMC funds lost 0.17% monthly in CAPM-adjusted alpha, while stocks purchased by bottom-quintile PTMC funds gained 0.46% monthly. The difference is still significant for Fama-French three-factor adjusted alpha and Carhart 4-factor adjusted alpha.[9]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Use of Private Information&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Private research by an investment firm – site visits to portfolio companies, interviews with portfolio CEOs, and in-house analysts estimating stock values – _does _correspond to higher returns. Investment firms that engage in more in-house research activities, or weight in-house research more heavily in investment decisions, tend to perform better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;About ⅙ of hedge funds make site visits to the companies they invest in.  Among 2469 Chinese hedge funds over the period 2012-2017, and CSMAR data on corporate site visits in China, 15.43% of hedge fund managers visited at least one company site.  Funds that made site visits had significantly (p&amp;lt;0.01) higher returns, CAPM alpha, Sharpe ratio, and volatility than funds that didn’t. Mean annual returns were 21.4% for funds that did site visits, vs. 15.3% for funds that did not.[10]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Female fund managers and managers with a graduate degree are more likely to make site visits.  11% of male managers made site visits, while 33% of female managers did.  12% of managers with graduate degrees made site visits, vs. 9% of managers without graduate degrees.[10]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chinese mutual funds between 2006-2016  were more likely to make trades on stocks if they had recently made a site visit, indicating that site visits did indeed provide them with decision-relevant information.  A portfolio of stocks that were bought by a mutual fund after a site visit had above-market returns after adjusting for Fama-French factors, indicating that mutual funds are successfully using site visits to identify good investments.[11]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fund managers who report (in a questionnaire) rating conversations with company executives as “very important” to their investment decisions perform significantly better (p &amp;lt;0.05) than fund managers who rate conversations with executives as “not important.”[12]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The added value of buy-side research – that is, the work of investment analysts doing proprietary research for investment firms – can be evaluated by measuring the “buy-side alpha” logged in a private database for an investment firm.   All investment analysts at this firm use the same baseline algorithm for valuing stocks; then, their individual research prices some stocks higher or lower than the algorithm would predict. This difference is called the “buy-side alpha.”  In the month following portfolio formation, it turns out, the “buy-side alpha” does correlate with actual stock performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stocks with top-quintile buy-side alphas are rated significantly &lt;em&gt;lower&lt;/em&gt; by sell-side analysts than stocks with bottom-quintile buy-side alphas (p&amp;lt;0.01), and have higher book-to-market ratios (p &amp;lt;0.01).  A portfolio based on buying stocks each month that had seen upgrades in buy-side alpha would earn 1.19% monthly, or an expected 15% per year, while a portfolio based on buying stocks whose buy-side alphas had been downgraded would earn 0.61% monthly, or an expected 7.6% yearly.  This is a significant difference, and continues to be significant after adjusting for risk, while the advantage of buying stocks recommended by sell-side analysts is no longer significant after risk adjustment.[13]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover, the mutual funds included in this database did buy stocks more when their buy-side analysts rated them higher, and sell stocks more when their buy-side analysts rated them lower.  The regression coefficient of firm investment on buy-side analyst ratings is significantly positive, p&amp;lt;0.01, even when controlling for sell-side analysts’ ratings.[13]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, the risk-adjusted quarterly returns of mutual funds correlate positively (p&amp;lt;0.01) with the sensitivity of their investment decisions to buy-side analyst recommendations, but returns do _not _correlate with the sensitivity to sell-side analyst recommendations.  In other words, it pays to rely on (private) buy-side research, but not to rely on (public) sell-side analysis.[13]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fund Manager Cognitive Characteristics and Fund Performance&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;84 fund managers from 267 mutual funds were given a battery of online cognitive tests, and their test results were compared to their publicly available fund performance.  The abnormal returns of funds (over their benchmark) did &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; correlate with fund managers’ performance on the Cognitive Reflection Test,  their score on a Theory of Mind test, or their self-reported competitiveness.  Ambiguity tolerance was positively (p&amp;lt;0.005) associated with abnormal returns.[14]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unsurprisingly, higher risk tolerance among fund managers in an experimental setting correlated positively with higher volatility in their funds (p&amp;lt;0.005), while a perfect score of 5 on the Cognitive Reflection Test (which 30% of the fund managers got) was negatively correlated with volatility (p&amp;lt;0.05).[14]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Together, these two facts imply that risk-adjusted performance (i.e. Sharpe ratio) is higher for fund managers who get perfect scores on the CRT.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Performance on the CRT by fund managers also has a strong positive correlation (0.51, p&amp;lt;0.005) with performance on the Advanced Progressive Matrices test, a measure of fluid intelligence. [14]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Information Seeking by Venture Capital and Investment Performance&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a survey of 128 angel investors investing in 1038 new ventures, firms that exited were classified as losing money (Failures), producing an internal rate of return of 0-99%, and exiting at 100% gains or greater (Home Runs).  ⅔ of investments were failures, and 20% were home runs. The number of home run exits of an investor correlated positively (0.24, p&amp;lt;0.05) with the investor’s propensity to engage in due diligence.[15]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Limitations and Conclusions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The data we have about the benefits of site visits comes entirely from the Chinese markets, which may not be representative of other investment markets.  For instance, checking on a factory to make sure its production is as good as it reports may be more important in a lower-trust environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also are short of data on investment performance in private equity in general, and particularly in the individual characteristics and decision processes of private equity investors that are predictive of fund performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite these limitations, we do seem to see consistent results pointing towards positive correlations between higher information-seeking activities by investors and higher investment returns, across investment categories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[1]Gibbons, Brian, Peter Iliev, and Jonathan Kalodimos. “Analyst information acquisition via EDGAR.” &lt;em&gt;Management Science&lt;/em&gt; (2020).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[2]Ali, Usman, et al. &lt;em&gt;Analysts’ use of public information and the profitability of their recommendation revisions&lt;/em&gt;. Working Paper, Yale University, 2008.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[3]Baldwin, Nancy Sadler, and Ronald E. Rice. “Information‐seeking behavior of securities analysts: Individual and institutional influences, information sources and channels, and outcomes.” &lt;em&gt;Journal of the American Society for Information Science&lt;/em&gt; 48.8 (1997): 674-693.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[4]Crane, Alan, Kevin Crotty, and Tarik Umar. “Do hedge funds profit from public information.” &lt;em&gt;Rice University&lt;/em&gt; (2018).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[5]Engelberg, Joseph E., Adam V. Reed, and Matthew C. Ringgenberg. “How are shorts informed?: Short sellers, news, and information processing.” &lt;em&gt;Journal of Financial Economics&lt;/em&gt; 105.2 (2012): 260-278.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[6]Schattmann, Levy, Jan-Oliver Strych, and P. Joakim Westerholm. “Information Processing Skills of Short Sellers: Empirical Evidence from the COVID-19 Pandemic.” &lt;em&gt;Available at SSRN 3763198&lt;/em&gt; (2021).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[7]Kacperczyk, Marcin, and Amit Seru. “Fund manager use of public information: New evidence on managerial skills.” &lt;em&gt;The Journal of Finance&lt;/em&gt; 62.2 (2007): 485-528.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[8]Abdesaken, Gerald. “On the precision of public information and mutual fund performance.” &lt;em&gt;Journal of Asset Management&lt;/em&gt; 16.2 (2015): 85-100.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[9]Fang, Lily H., Joel Peress, and Lu Zheng. “Does your fund manager trade on the news? media coverage, mutual fund trading and performance.” Media Coverage, Mutual Fund Trading and Performance (March 18, 2009)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[10]Drake, Michael S., et al. “Is there information content in information acquisition?.” &lt;em&gt;The Accounting Review&lt;/em&gt; 95.2 (2020): 113-139.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[11]Chen, Honghui, et al. “The Geography of Information Acquisition.” &lt;em&gt;Available at SSRN 3371978&lt;/em&gt; (2019).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[12]Drachter, Kerstin, Alexander Kempf, and Michael Wagner. “Decision processes in German mutual fund companies: evidence from a telephone survey.” &lt;em&gt;International Journal of Managerial Finance&lt;/em&gt; (2007).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[13]Rebello, Michael, and Kelsey Wei. “A glimpse behind a closed door: The investment value of buy-side research and its effect on fund trades and performance.” (2011).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[14] Farago, Adam, et al. &lt;em&gt;Cognitive skills and economic preferences in the fund industry&lt;/em&gt;. No. 2019-16. Working Papers in Economics and Statistics, 2019.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[15] Wiltbank, Robert. “Investment practices and outcomes of informal venture investors.” &lt;em&gt;Venture Capital&lt;/em&gt; 7.4 (2005): 343-357.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="lit-review" /><summary type="html">The Hypothesis</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Mammalian Aggression</title><link href="https://srconstantin.github.io/2021/01/17/Mammalian-Aggression.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Mammalian Aggression" /><published>2021-01-17T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-01-17T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://srconstantin.github.io/2021/01/17/Mammalian-Aggression</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://srconstantin.github.io/2021/01/17/Mammalian-Aggression.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Introduction&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In trying to understand how aggression works, as well as aggressive emotions like anger, I decided to go to the animal literature.  Human psychology research is all too prone to being determined by researchers’ preconceptions, and we all have a lot of firsthand experience and personal agendas when it comes to theorizing about human behavior. It’s easier to get some distance when thinking about animals; we have less stake in any particular theory of how animal emotions work.  It’s also easier to set up experimental conditions with animals that would be hard to do ethically with humans, like keeping them in confinement and exposing them to stressors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What the mammal literature says about aggression is that it splits neatly into discrete types.  Researchers disagree on exactly how many clusters there are, since there are inevitable judgment calls in defining taxonomies. And the pattern is somewhat different depending on species.  But one very consistent finding is that there &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; qualitatively different types of aggression.  They are governed by different hormones, activated in different situations, and seem to involve different subjective experiences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Defensive&lt;/strong&gt;
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Social&lt;/strong&gt;
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Maternal&lt;/strong&gt;
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Predatory&lt;/strong&gt;
   &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Target&lt;/strong&gt;
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Conspecifics, other species, inanimate objects
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Conspecifics only
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Conspecifics and other species
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Other species only
   &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Situation&lt;/strong&gt;
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Acute pain, imminent danger without possibility of escape
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Competition (over e.g. food, territory, mates)
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Threats to nursing young
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Hunting edible prey
   &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Attack lethality&lt;/strong&gt;
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Low
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Varies
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;High
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;High
   &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Arousal&lt;/strong&gt;
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;High
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;High
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Low
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Low
   &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Affect&lt;/strong&gt;
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Distressed, angry, fearful
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;alert
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;fearless
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Calm, alert, happy, curious, fearless
   &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Piloerection&lt;/strong&gt;
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Depends on species
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Yes
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Yes
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;No
   &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Vocalizing and threats&lt;/strong&gt;
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Yes
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Yes
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;No
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;No
   &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Association with sex hormones&lt;/strong&gt;
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;?
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Yes (increased by testosterone; blocked by ovarian hormones)
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Yes (increased by progesterone, testosterone)
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Depends on species
   &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cortisol levels during attack&lt;/strong&gt;
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;High
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;High
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Low
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Low
   &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Other positively associated hormones&lt;/strong&gt;
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;cholecystokinin, dopamine,histamine, substance P 
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;ACTH, CRH,histamine, norepinephrine,substance P,vasopressin
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;NO, vasopressin, oxytocin
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;acetylcholine
   &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Other negatively associated hormones&lt;/strong&gt;
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;norepinephrine
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;serotonin
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;CRH, neuropeptide Y, neurotensin
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;serotonin
   &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Brain region promoting the behavior &lt;/strong&gt;
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;amygdala, hippocampus, PAG
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Amygdala,lateral hypothalamus, lateral septum, olfactory bulb
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;dorsal raphe, lateral septum
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;amygdala, lateral hypothalamus, olfactory bulb
   &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Brain region inhibiting the behavior&lt;/strong&gt;
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;lateral septum, medial hypothalamus
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;?
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;PAG
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;PAG
   &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Drugs that increase the behavior&lt;/strong&gt;
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;amitriptyline, delta-9-THC, desmethylimipramine, ethanol,imipramine,iproniazid, naloxone, nialamide, pargyline
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;amphetamine, anabolic steroids, chlordiazepoxide,cyproheptadine,ethanol,fenfluramine, PCPA
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;alprazolam,chlordiazepoxide, diazepam,fluoxetine,oxazepam 
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;arecoline
   &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Drugs that decrease the behavior&lt;/strong&gt;
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;lithium,opioids,PCP
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;5-HT,cannabis,citalopram,fluoxetine, fluprazine, naloxone, quipazine, tryptophan
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;5-HT, amitriptyline, amfonelic acid, desipramine,fluprazine, GnRH antagonists, imipramine, morphine, NOS inhibitors, PCPA
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;5-HT, amphetamine, atropine,  delta-9-cannabidiol, ethanol, scopolamine
   &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Effect of domestication&lt;/strong&gt;
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;reduces
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;no change
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;no change
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;no change
   &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“Defensive Aggression”/”Defensive Rage” – Cortisol, Substance P&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A certain cluster of behaviors in mammals can be called “defensive aggression”, “affective defense,” or “defensive rage”. These behaviors are reactions to pain or immediate threat, whether that threat comes from a member of the same species, a member of a different species, or an inanimate object.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Defensive aggression is associated with negative emotions like fear and anger. It is aversive; a rat will learn not to push a lever that stimulates its brain in the same region that stimulates defensive aggression.  It is also associated with cortisol (the “stress hormone”), substance P (involved in pain perception), cholecystokinin (associated with panic), all suggesting that it is a reaction to frightening and painful situations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Defensive aggression in some species seems to involve qualitatively different and “milder” types of attack (less likely to cause injury) than other types of aggression.  It is also prompted by the same types of situations and same regions of brain stimulation associated with fleeing, hiding, and submission signals (like baring the belly to get an opponent to stop attacking.)  And animals engage in defensive aggression reflexively when hurt even when there is no visible attacker; they’ll “attack” inanimate objects or the air, as though “letting off steam”.  Speculatively, these details suggest that defensive aggression is something of a reflexive “lashing out” when an animal is hurt or scared, not very well optimized to injure or intimidate an opponent, and have more in common with other self-preservation behaviors (like fleeing, hiding, or submitting) than with other types of aggression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Affective Defense”/“Defensive Rage” in Cats&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Affective defense” in mammals typically involves flattening of the ears, lowering of the body, drawing in the head, pupillary dilation, piloerection, hissing, and stiffening of the tail. It is triggered by either a conspecific or a member of another species who is perceived to be a threat.[18]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In cats, “defensive rage” behavior includes ear retraction, piloerection, back arching, pupillary dilatation, vocalization, unsheathing of the claws, and paw strike.  It occurs when a cat is threatened by either a member of the same or different species. Stimulating the midbrain periaqueductal gray (PAG), which is generally a pain center, elicits defensive rage behaviors in cats.[21]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Various compounds associated with pain and stress, as well as acute ethanol intoxication, can affect the “defensive rage” response.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blocking substance P, a substance involved in pain response, in cats reduces the defensive rage response to stimulation in the medial amygdala and medial hypothalamus.[22]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ethanol enhances defensive rage responses in cats, while it reduces predatory attacks.[23]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cholecystokinin, a neuropeptide and digestive hormone which causes nausea and induces panic when administered to humans, potentiates the defensive rage response in cats.[24]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Naloxone reduces the threshold for inducing defensive rage in the cat by brain stimulation; opioid receptor agonists block defensive rage.[57]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Defensive rage in cats appears to be inhibited by the medial hypothalamus.  Medial hypothalamus lesions make cats extremely defensive – they spit and claw in the presence of humans, they’ll run from a dog and fight if attacked.[48]  However, olfactory bulbectomy doesn’t affect defensive aggression in cats.[48]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Defensive Aggression in Dogs&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The septal region in the brain is involved in inhibiting defensive aggression in dogs.  Septal lesions make dogs more “overexcitable, baring their teeth, and attempting to bite when handled.”[48]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Cortisol-Related Aggression in Hamsters&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Syrian and Siberian hamsters are more aggressive in the winter (short-day condition) than the summer, despite their testes being smaller in the winter.  The increased aggression appears to be mediated by elevated cortisol, downstream of melatonin signaling.  In primates as well, seasonal rises in testosterone don’t always correlate to increased aggression, and exogenous T doesn’t always increase aggression. Just as in male humans, there is no correlation between testosterone levels and aggressive behavior.[33]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, amygdala lesions suppress shock-induced fighting in hamsters.[48]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Defensive Aggression in Marmosets&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As with cats and opossums, stimulating the marmoset ventromedial hypothalamus elicits aggressive responses, chiefly short attacks and vocal threats, as well as flight responses.[27]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Female marmosets attack intruders; the magnitude of the aggressive response correlates positively with testosterone level immediately after the attack.[92]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Defensive Aggression in Mice&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Defensive aggression in mice seems to be inhibited by the septal region of the brain and enhanced by the olfactory bulb, unlike hamsters and gerbils who do not have an olfactory bulb-dependent aggression response.[48]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mice who have had their olfactory bulb removed do not fight back when attacked or exhibit fighting behavior after electric shocks. Peripheral anosmia does not cause this response, indicating that its effect on aggression is not due exclusively to the fact that it is necessary for smell.[48]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Septal lesions in mice enhance defensiveness; struggling, biting, and escaping.[48]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Defensive Aggression in Rabbits&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Septal lesions increase defensive responses (like foot thumping) to human experimenters in rabbits.[48]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Defensive Aggression in Rats&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Defensive biting in rats is different from attack biting; it is usually targeted at the snout, while attacking rats bite their opponent’s back; and defensive biting is seen &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; often against human hands or tools than against rats.  Defensive biting only occurs during or immediately after the defending animal has been hurt, and only when escape is impossible. Defensive biting also does not involve piloerection, while offensive biting always does.[4]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Defensive aggression is specifically selected against when rats are domesticated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;233 wild-caught rats were selected for “tameness”, that is, lower rates of aggressive behaviors towards human handlers, or “aggression”, that is, higher rates of aggressive behaviors towards human handlers, over 8-10 generations.  [1]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was no difference in testosterone levels between tame and wild rats of both sexes; however, aggressive rats had significantly higher serum cortisone levels than wild rats, in both sexes.  Aggressive rats had significantly larger startle responses to stimuli than tame rats, in both sexes.[1]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tame rats show fewer displays of defensive aggression towards other rats than aggressive rats, but no fewer displays of offensive aggression.[1]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As with other animals, the septal and medial hypothalamus regions of the brain appear to inhibit defensive aggression in rats, while the amygdala and hippocampus stimulate it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Septal lesions in rats enhance defensiveness – heightened fighting in response to foot shock and handling.  Medial hypothalamus lesions also dramatically increase defensiveness.  Amygdala and hippocampus lesions, by contrast, decrease defensiveness.[48][79]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Certain drugs affect defensive aggression in rats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Irritable aggression” in both male and female rats – an increased tendency to fight each other when deprived of food or sleep or administered electric shocks – is increased by administering cannabis or delta-9-THC.[78]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lithium reduces aggression in rats in response to pain from hot plates or electric shocks.[80]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tricyclic antidepressant drugs imipramine, amitryptiline, and desmethylimipramine, and the MAOIs nialamide, iproniazid, and pargyline, all increased shock-induced aggression in rats.[81]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Acute administration of dopamine intravenously increases shock-induced aggression in rats, while acute intravenous norepinephrine reduces it.[82]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Phencyclidine (PCP) dose-dependently reduces defensive aggression in rats both against other rats after foot shock, and against an inanimate target after immobilization and tail shock.[83]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Histamine increases rat aggression in response to foot shocks; this effect is further potentiated by an H1-receptor-blocking antihistamine and suppressed by an H2-receptor-blocking antihistamine, suggesting that H2 histamine receptors are involved in defensive aggression.[84]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cholecystokinin type 2 receptors in the PAG are necessary for two defensive behaviors in rats, freezing and escape.[116]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pain-Induced Aggression in Spider Monkeys&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spider monkeys will bite other monkeys, rats, mice, dolls, and balls immediately after being administered painful electric shocks.  If two monkeys are both shocked, initially both will attack; after repeated shocks, a pattern emerges where one always attacks and one always flees.[29]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Aggressive Vocalization and Pain-Induced Aggression in Squirrel Monkeys&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The “kecker” call, associated with aggression, can be stimulated in squirrel monkeys by electrodes in the amygdala, hypothalamus, and periventricular gray.[36]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Phencyclidine at high doses blocks pain-induced aggression in squirrel monkeys.[94]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Social Aggression (“Offensive Aggression”, “Intermale Aggression”) – Testosterone, Vasopressin, Low Serotonin&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Social aggression, unlike defensive aggression, is directed only at members of one’s own species.  It is sometimes called “intermale aggression” or “hormone-dependent aggression” even though it is not exclusive to males, because it is generally more common in males and correlates well to testosterone levels.  It also inversely correlates to serotonin levels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Social aggression revolves around competition for scarce resources – mates, territory, or in some species food and water. It generally involves threat displays intended to make an opponent back down without a fight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Social aggression is the least well-categorized of the types of aggression I describe here; in some species (such as marmosets) there doesn’t seem to be a clear distinction between social and defensive aggression.  In rats, social aggression is always accompanied by piloerection (hair standing on end) while defensive aggression never is.  But not all species seem to have this sharp distinction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are major differences between the ways “social aggression” is studied in rodents vs. primates which make the situation more confusing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In rodents, “offensive aggression” is defined as the propensity for an individual to attack an unknown intruder into his space.  Since the “resident” invariably defeats the “intruder”, dominance and “offensive aggression” are identical.  Dominant rodents are higher in testosterone than average and have more access to mates.  In rodents, the relationship between social aggression and the hormones serotonin and testosterone is straightforward: testosterone raises social aggression and serotonin lowers it.   Stress and anxiety anticorrelate with offensive aggression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In primates and social carnivores such as wolves and mongooses, however, studies are typically done within a group of individuals who live together (in the wild or the lab).  Conflicts are primarily with community members, and only occasionally with strangers.  And intragroup conflicts often resolve with little or no physical violence, just threat behaviors and mild scuffling.  So “dominance” is a more complex phenomenon; a dominant individual in a group is the one who wins most conflicts and receives the most submission behavior, and has the most access to resources (like mates, food, and water), but the dominant individual is _not _necessarily the most aggressive individual.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The relationship between dominance, aggression, and the hormones testosterone, serotonin, and cortisol, is likewise complicated in primates and in social carnivores. Dominance rank does not necessarily correlate positively with aggression.  Completely nonviolent individuals are, by definition, at the bottom of the dominance hierarchy (they lose all fights they’re in), but otherwise, in primates and carnivores, “fighting more” is not necessarily “winning more.”  The most dominant individuals in a stable hierarchy are rarely threatened, and can easily cause others to back down with a harmless threat display.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aggression does not always correlate with cortisol in primates and social carnivores. Dominance usually correlates positively with baseline cortisol levels.  On the other hand, losing fights causes an &lt;em&gt;acute&lt;/em&gt; spike in cortisol in the loser. Because of the negative feedback in cortisol levels, these two observations are consistent; frequent experiences of losing fights can be expected to &lt;em&gt;depress&lt;/em&gt; long-term baseline cortisol levels, even as each losing battle causes a spike in cortisol in the short term.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Serotonin in primates correlates &lt;em&gt;positively _with dominance rank and with _non-severe&lt;/em&gt; aggression (initiating threat displays or harmless physical scuffles) but &lt;em&gt;negatively&lt;/em&gt; with severe aggression (wounding another primate).  As in rodents, low serotonin correlates with serious violence in primates, but primates also have a more complex repertoire of dominant/threatening social behavior which are associated with &lt;em&gt;high&lt;/em&gt; serotonin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Testosterone, though, in primates and carnivores just as in rodents, has a straightforward positive correlation with both dominance and aggression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Social Aggression in Baboons&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Among female baboons, testosterone correlates with dominance rank and within-individual aggression but not across-individual aggression – i.e. higher-T baboons are not more aggressive overall, but particular baboons are more aggressive at times when their T is higher.[90]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dominant baboons have more copulatory success, are more likely to dominate in conflicts (receive submissive gestures or avoidance from other baboons), and are more likely to win conflicts over food. But they do not engage in more aggressive encounters.  High dominance rank among baboons is associated with low baseline cortisol and high cortisol response to stress.[98]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Social Aggression in Chimpanzees&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Behavioral style in chimpanzees was broken down into 6 principal components:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“Smart” (uses coalitions when initiating aggression; is usually the groom-ee in grooming interactions; has most play offers accepted)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“Affiliative” (participates in a lot of grooming; frequent hugging and touching)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“Playful” (plays often and with many other chimps)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“Aggressive” (most social interactions are aggressive; has many coalition partners in aggression)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“Friendly” (has many friends; spreads affiliative behavior around many individuals)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“Mellow” (frequently does not react to aggression or social approach)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Friendly” and “Affiliative” personality was not associated with dominance rank.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Playful” and “Smart” personalities were more likely to be subordinate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Aggressive” and “Mellow” personalities were more likely to be dominant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cortisol did not correlate with rank, aggression given, or aggression received.  There was a nonsignificant positive association between cortisol and the “Smart” and “Aggressive” styles.[61]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In adolescent male chimpanzees, testosterone (after correcting for age) was positively associated with dominance and aggression given, negatively associated with aggression received, and positively associated with the “mellow” behavioral style.  Testosterone was not associated with the “Aggressiveness” behavioral style.  Note that “Aggressiveness” indicates that a high percent of one’s total social interactions are aggressive, so an individual who is both aggressive and friendly might have a &lt;em&gt;low&lt;/em&gt; “Aggressiveness” score.[100]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dominance rank, aggression, and testosterone are correlated in adult male chimpanzees.[98]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Citalopram, an SSRI, reduced aggressive behavior in a zoo chimpanzee.[102]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Aggression and Social Dominance in Cynomolgus Monkeys&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dominant cynomolgus monkeys (those who win most conflicts) tend to also engage in more aggression overall.  Serotonin tends to inhibit aggression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other hormones have relationships with aggression and dominance as well: testosterone is positively correlated with dominance rank; cortisol is positively correlated with rank in males but not females; and ovariectomy increases both aggression and submission in females, suggesting that some ovarian hormone is responsible for blocking aggression and submission.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In female cynomolgus monkeys, the lower the social rank of a monkey, the more aggression she received and the more submissive behaviors she practiced.  But aggressive behaviors follow an inverted U-shaped relationship with rank; the most dominant individuals actually engage in less aggression than the middle ranks, though the most subordinate individuals do the least aggression of all.  If monkeys are split into two groups, “dominant” and “subordinate”, the difference in aggression is not significant, but it’s clear how with this pattern, different choices of split point would result in different conclusions.[107]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dominant monkeys were larger and had higher levels of LH, cortisol response, oxytocin, and dopamine metabolites than subordinates.[107]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was no association between cortisol levels and social rank in female cynomolgus monkeys.  Higher-ranked monkeys engaged in more aggression while lower-ranked monkeys engaged in more submission.[59]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When given sertraline, an SSRI, adult female cynomolgus monkeys showed changes in social behavior. Before treatment, dominant monkeys were more aggressive than subordinates; with sertraline, dominant monkeys engaged in less aggression until they matched the low subordinate level.  Before treatment, subordinate monkeys engaged in more submission than dominants; with sertraline, the subordinates’ submissive behavior dropped to match the low dominant level.[103]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Homovanillic acid levels (a metabolite of dopamine) were higher in both male and female dominant cynomolgus monkeys than in subordinates.  No association with norepinephrine metabolites. In males but not females, lower HIAA (a metabolite of serotonin) was associated with dominance.[105]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dominant male monkeys have higher basal cortisol and testosterone levels; subordinate monkeys have stronger cortisol response to ACTH challenge.[58]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ovariectomy causes a 2-3x increase in aggression and submission in female cynomolgus monkeys.[106]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As with other animals, ethanol can stimulate aggression in cynomolgus monkeys.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Acute and chronic alcohol drinking both increase rates of contact aggression in cynomolgus monkeys.[104]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Social Aggression in Dogs&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Domestic dogs who engaged in “leash aggression” (attempting to attack other dogs while on leash) were matched to a dog of the same age, sex, and breed who did not engage in “leash aggression.”  Aggressive dogs were more likely to bark, lunge, and growl at model dogs than non-aggressive dogs.  Aggressive dogs had higher levels of free vasopressin than nonaggressive dogs, but no difference in oxytocin.[89]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Among assistance dogs bred for affectionate dispositions and low aggressiveness, oxytocin was higher than in pet dogs.[89]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Social Aggression in Gerbils&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like mice and rats, male gerbils who cohabit with a female will attack unfamiliar intruders in their home territory.[109]  Castration abolishes territorial aggression; castration + supplemental testosterone restores it.[110]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Olfactory bulbectomy reduces social aggression in gerbils; high dose testosterone propionate reverses this effect. [48]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gerbils will typically attack unfamiliar gerbils and also rats and mice that venture into their territory.  Gerbils dosed with delta-9-THC will still sniff, approach, and chase a mouse, but will not bite it.[111]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Social Aggression in Hamsters&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As with other animals, testosterone and other androgens increase aggression in hamsters; so do the hormones vasopressin and corticotropin releasing hormone (CRH), a stimulator of the HPA-axis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In hamsters, vasopressin administration increases rates of flank marking (a dominance behavior), and vasopressin antagonists reduce flank marking by dominant hamsters, which in turn increases flank marking by submissive hamsters.[33]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blocking vasopressin dose-dependently reduces male hamsters’ rate of attacking intruders.[91]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A CRF1 antagonist blocks attacks against intruding male hamsters – higher latency to bite, lower chase duration, lower attack frequency.[63]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anabolic steroids (testosterone cypionate, nandrolone deconate, and boldenone undecylinate) increase offensive aggression in male hamsters.[74]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Social Aggression in Marmosets&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Common marmosets exhibit “vocal threats” along with limited piloerection in the tail and relatively harmless “short attacks”, when competing over food.  Short attacks are generally made against lower-ranking or younger monkeys, are terminated by flight or submissive squeals, and are never followed by chasing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Genital display and flicking of the ear-tufts are behaviors that alpha marmosets usually make towards subordinate marmosets, or any marmosets towards strange marmosets and humans.  If the strangers counter-threaten, serious biting attacks ensue.  Violent attacks and fighting are accompanied by substantial piloerection.[26]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the common marmoset and black tufted-ear marmoset, as well as in lemurs and tamarins, dominant individuals have higher cortisol than subordinates.[88]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Social Aggression in Mice&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Olfactory bulbectomy reduces social aggression in mice; peripherally induced anosmia does not.[48]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Naloxone suppresses intermale aggression in isolated mice.[75]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cannabis reduces the tendency of mice to fight an intruder, even at doses too low to suppress locomotor activity.[78]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a subpopulation of rats and mice, roughly a quarter of subjects, ethanol administration increases aggression against intruders. In particular, ethanol lengthens the duration of bursts of aggressive activity, but does not affect the latency to attack.[96]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mice lacking the HNMT gene have higher levels of brain histamine, and are more aggressive against intruders.  They also have an altered sleep/wake cycle (they are more active during the light period when mice usually sleep, and less active during the dark period when mice are usually awake.)[117]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mice lacking substance P receptors are far less likely to attack an intruder.[118]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Social Aggression in Rabbits&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The male rabbit who is most likely to follow, attack, and chase is considered the dominant rabbit in a group; he has higher peripheral testosterone levels than the others.[93]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Offensive” or “Hormone-dependent” Aggression in Rats&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Offensive aggression in rats is clearly delineated from defensive aggression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a colony of rats, if an intruder enters, one male rat will typically attack the intruder; this male is also the dominant rat in “agonistic encounters” within the colony.  These attacks are preceded by approach, sniffing, and (if the rat is not a colony member) piloerection, followed by biting, boxing, and climbing on top of the other rat.  The intruder rat rarely bites back after being attacked.[4]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Only hormone-dependent aggression in rats is accompanied by piloerection; defensive and predatory aggression are not. Hormone-dependent aggression is not territorial – a male rat will attack an unfamiliar male rat even if he is in an unfamiliar area.[6]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When a cat smell is added to a rat cage, offensive attacks disappear; defensive biting is unchanged or increased, however.[3]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Offensive aggression in rats is associated with testosterone, copulation, and winning fights; it is reduced when a rat experiences “disappointment”, failing to get an expected reward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Castration reduces social aggression in male rats, and testosterone supplementation increases it.  The amount of aggression in intact male rats correlates with the baseline level of serum testosterone. Rat testosterone spikes after exposure to a receptive female and after successful aggression.[6]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Male rats will exhibit much more social aggression if they cohabit with females.  Both male and female rats will exhibit more hormone-dependent aggression if they are competing for scarce food.[6]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Offensive aggression in male rats increases after copulation with females.[7]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Male intruder rats display offensive aggression against female residents, but never males.  Female intruder rats rarely are attacked, and when they are it is usually only after they rebuff multiple attempts to mate.[8]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When access to food or water is restricted, the “alpha” male or female rats in a colony (those who attack intruders the most) are &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; the same rats who get the most access to the food or water.  But alpha male rats &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; the ones who have the most access to copulating with females.[8]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rats surprised by a lack of reward in a situation that normally provides rewards show a reduction in social aggression and a greater propensity to be attacked.[9]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Social aggression in rats also anti-correlates with serotonin and is increased by serotonin-depleting drugs and decreased by serotonergic drugs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Male Wistar rats treated with PCPA, a drug which depletes cerebral serotonin, or a saline control, before being placed in another weight-matched rat’s cage.  The PCPA-treated intruder rats frequently attacked the residents; the control rats never did. PCPA-treated rats were also more likely to socially approach the resident rats.  Defensive and submissive behaviors were unchanged.[2]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When it was the resident rats who were treated with PCPA or control, treated rats attacked more; there was no change in defensive or submissive behaviors.[2]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hypothalamic stimulation prompts rats to attack other rats (male and female), anaesthetized or dead rats, and mice, but not toy rats.  Castration increases latency of hypothalamic aggression; testosterone reverses the effect.  Serotonin-receptor-binding drugs such as fluprazine, quipazine, and TFMPP, increase the threshold for hypothalamic aggression.[5]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps surprisingly, though, social aggression in rats anticorrelates with anxiety.  Rats bred for low rates of anxious behavior were more aggressive than rats bred for high rates of anxious behavior or rats without selective breeding.[76]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Social Aggression in Mongooses&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the dwarf mongoose, dominant females have higher cortisol levels than subordinate females.[88]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unusually among social mammals, mongooses don’t show elevated testosterone in situations of conflict. Testosterone levels in male mongooses don’t correlate with rates of aggression, dominance rank, or mating rates. [112]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mongooses are unusual in that they are cooperative breeders; only a few individuals in a group reproduce, and the rest are “helpers” who look after the children.  However the “helper” males have just as much testosterone as the dominant males.  Mongooses also continue to play even as adults, which many species don’t.[112]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Social Aggression in Oryx&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oryx engage in postural threats (erect posture, threatening with horns) and head-butting conflicts with the horns of other males. They submit by bowing their heads or leaving after challenged.  Melengestrol acetate, a progestin, reduces aggression when given in the feed of a herd of male oryx.  Melengestrol reduces testosterone levels, as well as levels of posturing, contact, chasing, and submission.[108]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Social Aggression in Rhesus Monkeys&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In rhesus monkeys, serotonin is negatively associated with intra-species aggression in rhesus monkeys, but positively associated with dominance.  When aggression is split into the two categories of competitive aggression (threatening, chasing, and displacing, without causing serious injury) vs. severe aggression (causing wounds), we find that serotonin, and dominance rank, are &lt;em&gt;positively&lt;/em&gt; associated with competitive aggression and &lt;em&gt;negatively&lt;/em&gt; associated with severe aggression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Testosterone is positively associated with aggression.  Cortisol is negatively associated with threat displays.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In free-living young male rhesus monkeys, ACTH and norepinephrine levels were positively associated with aggressiveness ratings, while 5-HIAA (a serotonin metabolite) levels were negatively associated.[27]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;28 young male monkeys taken from 3500 free-living macaques on an island in South Carolina were rated for “aggressiveness” by researchers based on direct observation, examination of scars and wounds, and photographs.  ACTH was significantly positively associated with aggressiveness, as was norepinephrine; serotonin was negatively associated.[37]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dominance among females in a free-living macaque colony is associated with the frequency of threatening, displacing, and chasing behavior, but not with severe aggression or spontaneous wounding.  High dominance rank correlated positively with 5-HIAA (a serotonin metabolite.)  Severe aggression or wounding correlated negatively with 5-HIAA.[41]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The C77G polymorphism in the mu-opioid receptor gene in macaques is associated with an abnormally low cortisol response to stress and pain.  Threat displays, such as teeth-baring, staring, and ear-flapping, correlated &lt;em&gt;negatively&lt;/em&gt; with cortisol levels.  The mutant macaques had significantly higher rates of threat display, but not more cage-shaking or attacks on self or inanimate objects.[35]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Testosterone in male rhesus monkeys correlates positively with rates of aggression, dominance rank, rate of receiving submission, and “tension” (yawning, teeth grinding, and banging objects; also symptomatic of inhibited aggressive behavior due to the presence of dominant animals.)  High testosterone correlates negatively with submissive behaviors. On the other hand, the reverse correlation does not apply; the monkeys most likely to submit do not have the lowest testosterone.[40]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dominance in rhesus monkeys seems to involve activity in the amygdala and lateral hypothalamus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you remove the amygdala from a dominant rhesus monkey, he becomes submissive, never aggresses or retaliates, and moves to the bottom of the dominance hierarchy. He also becomes more aggressive/fearless in individual-cage settings.[41]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stimulation of male rhesus monkeys in the lateral hypothalamus prompts them to aggressively attack the dominant monkey.  The stimulated monkeys did not attack females or inanimate objects.  The stimulated subordinate monkey usually lost fights with the dominant; the dominant monkey mounted the female more and actively threatened the stimulated subordinate male.  Eventually the formerly subordinate monkeys became dominant; their hair stood on end, they strutted, they &lt;em&gt;looked&lt;/em&gt; dominant, while the formerly dominant monkeys crouched and had matted hair.[39]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When amphetamine is administered to stumptail macacques, affiliative behavior decreases and aggressive behavior increases.[97]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Social Aggression in Squirrel Monkeys&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Squirrel monkeys make threat displays and aggressive vocalizations when faced with a strange intruder; the rate of these aggressive responses increases when they are given ethanol or the benzodiazepine chlordiazepoxide.[95]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Dominance in Vervet Monkeys&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dominance is measured by how often a male monkey succeeds in agonistic encounters (i.e. the other monkey submits or avoids).  36 adult male vervet monkeys were separated into 12 groups of 4. In each, a dominant male (winning over 85% of encounters) emerged.  Tryptophan and fluoxetine (both serotonergic) significantly increased the frequency of approaching, proximity, and grooming but decreased the rate of aggressive behaviors.  By contrast, fenfluramine and cyproheptadine (which deplete serotonin), decreased approaching, proximity, and grooming and increased aggression.[38]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The animals treated with serotonergic drugs became dominant and remained so; the animals treated with anti-serotonin drugs became subordinate and remained so.  This suggests that low serotonin may be a signal of &lt;em&gt;low&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;threatened&lt;/em&gt; dominance, which prompts aggression.[38]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cortisol levels do not correlate with social dominance in stable groups of vervet monkeys. Cortisol levels rise during competition for dominance among familiar males, particularly among the winners of such competitions.[60]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Social Aggression in Wolves&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cortisol is higher in dominant wolves than subordinate wolves, consistent across 3 packs and 2 years.  There is no overall correlation between cortisol and levels of agonistic and aggressive behavior.  However, cortisol is higher during the mating period, and so is aggressive behavior.  Dominant wolves do not fight more than subordinate wolves; they just win a higher percentage of their fights.[85]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Male wolves are more likely than female wolves to fight against other packs; male wolves also have higher cortisol than female wolves.[86]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dominant male wolves have higher testosterone and cortisol than subordinate wolves.[87]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Maternal Aggression: Oxytocin, Vasopressin&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maternal aggression is the propensity of mammalian mothers to become more aggressive in defense of their offspring during pregnancy and while nursing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Maternal Aggression in Mice&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mouse maternal aggression is promoted by nursing and caring for infant offspring, not necessarily pregnancy or even female sex.  The male sex hormone testosterone, in addition to pregnancy-related female hormones, increases maternal aggression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a species of mice where fathers as well as mothers have significant parental investment into raising children, there is a “paternal aggression” phenomenon in which male parents are more aggressive towards intruders than male virgins are.[66]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prenatal testosterone exposure increases maternal aggression in mice.[67]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mouse maternal aggression is blocked by stress, as well as stress and anxiety-related hormones, such as CRH, neuropeptide Y, and neurotensin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Corticotropin-releasing hormone, as well as the presence of stressors, inhibits maternal aggression in mice.  Nursing mice also show reduced fear and anxiety.[50]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mice selected for high maternal aggression have reduced neuropeptide Y expression, which also correlates with decreased fear and anxiety.  They also have increased CRF binding protein expression (which reduces the effect of CRF), and increased NO synthase. [51]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neurotensin injected into a lactating mouse’s brain significantly and dose-dependently reduces maternal aggression.  Neurotensin antagonists significantly increase maternal aggression.  Neurotensin has many functions, including stimulating ACTH production.[53]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Serotonin-related drugs also affect maternal aggression in mice, though the pattern of effect is not obvious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PCPA, a serotonin depletion agent, as well as 5-HTP, a serotonin precursor, inhibit maternal aggression in postpartum mice.  Antagonists of serotonin receptors such as mianserin, methiothepin, and methysergide, also reduce maternal aggression.[70]  5-HTP and PCPA have opposite effects on serotonin but they both increase dopamine levels, and also increase levels of 5HIAA, the metabolite of serotonin.[70]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imipramine, a tricyclic antidepressant with strong effects on many neurotransmitter receptors, reduces maternal aggression in mice.[69]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Morphine reduces maternal care for pups and maternal aggression in mice.[68]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Maternal Aggression in Rats&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maternal aggression in rodents, like predatory aggression and unlike social aggression, is _not _accompanied by a cortisol response, elevated arousal, or social signaling (threats).  Maternal aggression tends to attack more vulnerable body parts (the belly) as opposed to social aggression (which attacks the back) or defensive aggression (which attacks the face).[33]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Female rats become more aggressive against unfamiliar rats during pregnancy, after birth, and during lactation. To a lesser extent, cohabiting with even a sterile male induces increased aggression in female rats.[6]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Female social aggression in rats is confined to the living area, unlike social aggression in male rats; a female rat outside her home will not attack a stranger.[6]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Female rats need to be stimulated by suckling pups in order to have maternal aggression. Removing nipples doesn’t remove the aggression, but anaesthesia to the ventral skin does, suggesting that the trigger is sensory rather than lactation-related.[10]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lactating female rats, but not alpha male rats, will bury an intruder after attacking it.  Like social aggression and unlike defensive aggression, piloerection is present in both maternal and alpha male attacks on intruders.[55]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maternal aggression in rats is enhanced by oxytocin and vasopressin, as well as GnRH (which increases the release of sex hormones).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blocking oxytocin chemically reduces maternal aggression in high-aggression lactating rats, and adding IV oxytocin increases maternal aggression in low-aggression lactating rats.  Likewise, blocking vasopressin in high-aggression lactating rats reduces maternal aggression, while IV vasopressin in low-aggression lactating rats increases maternal aggression.[11]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GnRH antagonists reduce maternal aggression in rats, but not maternal care.[71]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Serotonin has a complicated relationship with maternal aggression in rats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lesions to the serotonin-producing cells in the dorsal raphe reduce both maternal aggression and maternal care in rats, indicating that serotonin is necessary for maternal aggression.[54]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, fluoxetine (an SSRI) increases maternal aggression in rats relative to controls.[64]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, serotonergic drugs often decrease maternal aggression, such as  fluprazine [64], amitriptyline[73], and desipramine.[73]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In keeping with the finding that stress anticorrelates with maternal aggression, all benzodiazepines (which have anxiolytic effects) increase maternal aggression in rats.[67]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lateral septum is necessary for maternal aggression in rats, and the periaqueductal gray (PAG) inhibits it, as one would expect for a behavior that is negatively associated with anxiety.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lesions to the lateral septum in rats abolish maternal aggression, as well as maternal behavior such as retrieving, licking, and nursing pups.[52]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rats lesioned in the periaqueductal gray (PAG) attack intruders 2x as often as controls.[56]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Domestication does not inhibit maternal aggression; wild and domesticated Norway rat strains show no difference in maternal aggression.[77]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Maternal Aggression in Voles&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A nitric oxide synthesis inhibitor reduces maternal aggression in prairie voles.[72]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prairie voles are monogamous, and after pair-bonding, &lt;em&gt;male&lt;/em&gt; prairie voles become much more aggressive against intruders.  Vasopressin receptor antagonists prevent this increase in aggression, while supplemental vasopressin increases it.[113]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s possible that male aggression in voles actually is a closer hormonal match to maternal aggression given the pair-bonding aspect.  Consistent with this hypothesis, supplemental testosterone does not increase aggression in male voles[114] and castration does not inhibit aggression.[115]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Predatory Aggression&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Predatory aggression is violence against edible prey. It is almost always directed against members of a different species, though some mutations make animals attack conspecifics in ways that resemble predatory aggression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Predation is distinct from social and defensive aggression in that it is &lt;em&gt;stealthy&lt;/em&gt; (there is no vocalization or threat display, to avoid scaring off the prey) and it is &lt;em&gt;pleasurable rather than stressful&lt;/em&gt; to the predator.  Predatory behavior is not associated with cortisol response, and it is stimulated by the centers of the brain associated with reward and alertness, rather than the ones associated with fear and pain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Predatory Aggression in Baboons&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Olive baboons hunt occasionally, mostly hares, gazelles, birds, and other ungulates.  Male olive baboons do most of the killing and eating of prey.[101]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Predatory Aggression in Cats&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cats can attack other animals in two obviously distinct ways; “affective attack”, which involves hissing, growling, back arching, and piloerection; and “predatory attack”, in which the cat quietly stalks its prey and does not make aggressive noises or arch its back, and its hair does not stand on end.[12]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cats who are quicker to attack rats are also quicker to approach novel stimuli and slower to avoid threatening stimuli; the reverse is true of cats who are slow to attack rats.  Predatory behavior in cats seems to be related to curiosity and fearlessness.[21]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Predatory aggression in cats is stimulated by activity in the lateral hypothalamus and amygdala and inhibited by activity in the periaqueductal gray.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Electrical stimulation of the lateral hypothalamus in the cat (the same area that promotes feeding and wakefulness behavior) elicits predatory aggression.[21]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cats lesioned in the amygdala stop killing mice.[48]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lesions in the periaqueductal gray (PAG) lowered the threshold to cats attacking rats when stimulated in the hypothalamus.[43]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gonadectomy in female cats makes them quicker to attack a rat; gonadectomy in male cats makes them slower to attack a rat.  This suggests a positive association between testosterone and predation in cats.[25]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The muscarinic agonist arecoline can induce biting attack in the cat; muscarinic antagonists such as scopolamine and atropine block this effect.[62]  Arecoline is the psychoactive ingredient in betel nuts, and in humans causes an effect similar to nicotine – alertness, energy, euphoria, and relaxation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Predatory Aggression in Chimpanzees&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is significant overlap between intraspecific aggression and predation in chimpanzees. They sometimes stalk each other before attacking, and they have been known to eat infant chimpanzees after a fight.[49]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Predatory Aggression in Foxes&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Administration of 5-HT (serotonin) significantly reduced a fox’s likelihood of attacking a rat placed in its cage.[42]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Predatory Aggression in Mice&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mice kill and eat crickets.  A strain of mice bred for large amounts of voluntary wheel-running had no significant difference from controls in their rates of intermale aggression or maternal aggression, but the wheel-running mice were quicker to attack crickets.  Since wheel-running is a pleasurable activity that mice seek out, this suggests that propensity to kill crickets is associated with reward from active behaviors.  The wheel-running mice were smaller and had more pups than the control mice; serum testosterone levels were the same.[17]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reproductive and hormone status of female mice does not correlate with their propensity to attack crickets, suggesting that predatory and maternal aggression have different physiological bases.  Ovariectomy reduces maternal aggression in mice but does not reduce cricket-killing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A mouse’s sense of smell seems related to its ability to distinguish its own species from others. Abolishing it doesn’t reduce predation, but does cause cannibalism (a mouse “preying” on its own kind.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Experimentally induced anosmia reduces both maternal aggression and intermale aggression, but not cricket-killing.[19]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Olfactory bulbectomy in mice causes cannibalism – one adult mouse will kill and eat the other, and mothers will eat their young.[48]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, the hormone vasopressin in mice seems to be essential for aggression against other mice, but not for predation against other species.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mice with a disrupted vasopressin receptor, Avpr1b-/-, have lower intermale aggression, maternal aggression, and defensive biting responses, but the same number of “defensive avoidance” behaviors (fleeing, boxing).  Predatory aggression against crickets is intact in Avpr1b-/- mice.  This gene seems to be required for all types of attack responses towards conspecifics, but not to other species.[20]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some neuroactive drugs block mouse predation, including drugs that increase serotonin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Amphetamine, imipramine, and tripelennamine (an antihistamine) block mice from killing frogs.[14]  Serotonergic drugs (imipramine, fluoxetine, 5-HT) inhibit locust-killing in CBA mice[42].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Predatory Aggression in Minks&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you put a rat in a mink’s cage, it will attack 100% of the time. When given 5-HT (serotonin), only half the minks attacked the rat.[42]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Predatory Aggression in Primates&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many species of primates engage in some predation, against frogs, lizards, snakes, birds, or monkeys. Almost all use the craniocervical bite, a killing bite to the head or neck of the prey.  The exception is the baboon, which often starts to eat before its prey is dead, perhaps because the baboon’s size and strength allow it to immobilize prey even without immediately killing it.[30]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;_Predatory Aggression in Rats _&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rats often kill and eat frogs and turtles. Attacks on these animals are probably a better measure of rat predatory aggression than mouse-killing, even though rats do often eat mice as well; mouse-killing seems stimulated by some of the same mechanisms as social aggression and is a less “pure” instance of the class.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Testosterone doesn’t affect predatory aggression in rats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When male Wistar rats were tested for whether they would kill a frog (&lt;em&gt;Rana pipens&lt;/em&gt;) placed in their cage, those who didn’t kill the frog immediately never attacked a frog on subsequent trials. Testosterone injection didn’t induce frog killing.  The rats who did kill frogs learned to kill them faster upon repeated trials, but again testosterone injection had no effect on latency.[13]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Testosterone supplementation doesn’t increase frog-killing in female rats either.[15]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some drugs also reduce predatory aggression in rats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Amphetamine blocks rats from killing mice, and not just because it reduces appetite; at low doses, rats are still willing to kill mice even though they don’t want to eat them.  The same is true for frog-killing.[16]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Delta-9-cannabinol (the main psychoactive ingredient in cannabis) reduces rats’ frequency of attacking turtles.[45]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some rats attack other rats in ways more akin to predation than social aggression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In strains of rats with abnormally low glucocorticoid function, the lateral hypothalamus is activated during conflicts with other rats. These low-cortisol rats attack other rats on the head, throat, and belly, without any of the usual preliminaries of signaling aggression. In other words, their aggression against conspecifics looks more like predation.  Humans diagnosed with antisocial personality disorder also have lower cortisol levels than average.[33]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rats subjected to post-weaning social isolation also are abnormally aggressive and prone to attack vulnerable regions without intention signaling, again more like predatory or maternal aggression than typical social aggression.[47]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As with social aggression and maternal aggression, domestication of rats does not reduce predatory aggression.  Norway rats bred for low aggression towards humans did not show any decline in predatory behavior.[42]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Predatory Aggression in Voles&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After 13 generations of selecting bank voles for higher rates of predatory behavior, raising the rate of predatory behavior 5x relative to controls, the two highest SNPs found in the predatory lines were in the gene PDE4D, found expressed in the brain. PDE4D is responsible for degrading cAMP.  PDE4D inhibitors have antidepressant effects.[46]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mobbing&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mobbing refers to behaviors by groups of prey animals to approach, intently observe, harass, and attack a predator or other large member of another species.  Mobbing is common in primates, particularly New World monkeys.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Baboons, geladas, and chimpanzees launch aggressive counterattacks that can seriously wound predators; e.g. baboons often kill leopards.  Arboreal New World monkeys like tamarins and capuchins, by contrast, tend to lunge, jump, and make stereotyped threat behaviors when a predator (such as a snake) has captured one of them.  Where mobbing does not pose a lethal threat to the predator, it may be an attempt to get the predator to move on, as well as monitoring the threat. But capuchins also mob non-threatening, non-prey animals, and the reason why is unknown.[31]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Parallels to Human Aggression&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The criminology literature tends to make a single distinction in types of aggression – “reactive” aggression, a spontaneous, “hair-trigger” loss of self-control in response to frustration or provocation, or “predatory” aggression, a deliberate behavior engaged in to achieve a desired goal. Acts of “reactive” aggression are done under stress; acts of “predatory” aggression are done calmly and strategically, and may even be enjoyable.  The analogy between “predatory” aggression in humans and literal predation in animals is loose, and based primarily on the fact that both involve low cortisol and are not associated with strong negative emotions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Reactive” aggression in this criminology paradigm would seem to correspond either with “defensive” or “social” aggression – they’re not clearly delineated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Children with a history of aggressive behavior have been observed to cluster into two types. One type of child engages only in “impulsive” or “reactive” aggression. A second type of child engages both in this “impulsive” aggression and in “premeditated”/ “pro-active” aggression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Children in the “impulsive” group were more likely to have low IQs and schizophrenia diagnoses; children in the “mixed” group were more likely to have a history of drug abuse.  [12]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In studies of juvenile offenders, “premeditated”/”instrumental” aggression was reported to be a better predictor of future criminality than “reactive” aggression.[12]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In studies of men who battered their wives, some men’s heart rate rises during marital conflict, and some men’s heart rate lowers.  The low-heart-rate group was more likely to have a history of violence outside the marriage, more likely to have a drug dependence, and more likely to have antisocial and aggressive-sadistic characteristics.[12]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Human hunter-gatherers rarely engage in spontaneous “reactive” aggression, while chimpanzees and bonobos engage in conflict three orders of magnitude more often. An unusually high-violence group of Australian aborigines, plagued by poverty and alcoholism, was observed by ethnographers to engage in violence 0.005 times per 100 hours per individual, compared to 1-3 times per 100 hours per individual for chimpanzees and bonobos.  In other words, human hunter-gatherers spend at least 1000x less time than apes in violent squabbles with members of their community.[32]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, human hunter-gatherers engage in hostile raids and ambushes that are deadlier than anything other primates do.  Compared to our nearest primate neighbors, we have extremely low rates of reactive aggression and extremely high rates of proactive (premeditated) aggression.[32]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When animals such as dogs are bred for tameness, it is chiefly defensive aggression that is selected against (since we are selecting primarily for lack of violence against humans, who are neither prey nor conspecifics).  Hominid facial morphology has changed in the same way as dog facial morphology, and we have developed a longer developmental period, prolonged play, and cooperative communication, similar to the “domestication syndrome” in other animals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some hypothesize that have “bred ourselves” for tameness starting about 200,000 years ago, perhaps through capital punishment of reactively-aggressive, antisocial individuals.  Capital punishment appears to be a human universal, and in hunter-gatherer societies it is typically antisocial males with a history of selfish violence who are executed.  Capital punishment itself, of course, is an example of &lt;em&gt;proactive&lt;/em&gt; aggression – carefully planned and calmly premeditated.[32]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chimpanzees have a lower death rate from intergroup aggression than human subsistence farmers, but comparable to human subsistence hunter-gatherers, based on 33 human groups from around the world.[99]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Generalizations &amp;amp; Speculations&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Defensive aggression is pretty clearly a response to fear and pain, which belongs in the same category with other behaviors like fleeing, hiding, freezing, cowering (protecting vulnerable body parts), and fawning (submission signals.)  It is an &lt;em&gt;agitated, reactive, and non-strategic&lt;/em&gt; form of aggression, as you can see from the fact that it is relatively ineffective at harming the opponent, and that often an animal in pain will “take its frustration out on” any nearby animals or inanimate objects, regardless of whether they caused the pain. Human experiences like frustration, irritability, or “defensiveness” are probably manifestations of defensive aggression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Translating social aggression into the human realm is more complicated. It seems clearly related to testosterone, competition, and status conflict, as well as protecting valuable resources (like territory, food, or mates), all of which of course humans do.  But it’s unclear to me what the &lt;em&gt;subjective feeling&lt;/em&gt; is that corresponds with social aggression.  Even valence is unclear – is engaging in social aggression pleasant or unpleasant for animals?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lateral hypothalamus is generally considered a pleasure center (or at least a “reward-seeking” center), and stimulating it makes rhesus monkeys much more socially aggressive, suggesting that they are in a “seeking”, eager mood when they start fights; the amygdala is associated with fear, and amygdalectomized monkeys are passive and placid and never fight back.  So, at least, social aggression is associated with energetic, urgent feelings, but it seems to be a mix or an ambiguous relationship between fear and pleasure-seeking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maternal aggression is very clearly associated with &lt;em&gt;fearlessness&lt;/em&gt; and the &lt;em&gt;absence of stress&lt;/em&gt;.  It is a calm, non-agitated, deadly type of aggression.  It’s not otherwise clear to me what it “feels like from the inside”, though, or what situations (if any) apart from defending young children it would arise in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Predatory aggression has a very consistent psychological profile – it’s alert, calm, focused, and eager.  It is a strategic and goal-directed kind of aggression, very effective at killing.  In humans, it probably shows up during literal hunting (we are a predatory species after all), as well as in strategic types of conflict such as warfare.  It seems to have a lot in common with the “flow state” of enjoyable, focused, trance-like absorption in a stimulating activity, which humans also engage in through nonviolent activities such as games and skilled work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Animal domestication selectively breeds animals for reduced defensive aggression, while preserving other types of aggression (social, maternal, and predatory.)  Tame animals are less fearful and skittish around new objects and surprising encounters, less likely to either flee or fight out of fear or irritation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Human evolution, our own “domestication”, probably did the same thing; we have drastically fewer impulsive, irritable violent reactions to our neighbors than other primates, but probably equal motivation for defending our children and competing for social status, and &lt;em&gt;greater&lt;/em&gt; skill than any of our primate relatives in forms of organized violence such as hunting and warfare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Among contemporary humans, showing frustration is viewed as a sign of weakness, but being calmly dangerous can earn respect. We admire predatory (and social) aggression, but disdain defensive aggression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As far as hormones go, serotonin seems to clearly correlate with what might be termed “contentment” or “satiety.” It reduces motivation to hunt and to engage in social aggression, reliably across animals.  High serotonin levels correlate with and even cause dominant social rank; the very most dominant individuals in a hierarchy are typically _less_violent, or less severely violent, than the mid-rank individuals, presumably because they’re so high status they don’t have to fight much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Testosterone seems to increase motivation to engage in &lt;em&gt;both&lt;/em&gt; social aggression and social submission, while progesterone inhibits both aggression and submission.  This is contrary to the stereotype of submission as “unmanly”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps testosterone increases motivation to engage in &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; social-status-related activities, both fighting and submission, while serotonin has a somewhat independent effect, such that low serotonin increases aggression but not submission.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[1]Albert, Frank W., et al. “Phenotypic differences in behavior, physiology and neurochemistry between rats selected for tameness and for defensive aggression towards humans.” Hormones and behavior 53.3 (2008): 413-421.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[2]Vergnes, Marguerite, Antoine Depaulis, and Any Boehrer. “Parachlorophenylalanine-induced serotonin depletion increases offensive but not defensive aggression in male rats.” &lt;em&gt;Physiology &amp;amp; behavior&lt;/em&gt; 36.4 (1986): 653-658.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[3]Blanchard, Robert J., et al. “Fear and aggression in the rat.” &lt;em&gt;Aggressive Behavior&lt;/em&gt; 10.4 (1984): 309-315.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[4]Blanchard, Robert J., and D. Caroline Blanchard. “Aggressive behavior in the rat.” &lt;em&gt;Behavioral biology&lt;/em&gt; 21.2 (1977): 197-224.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[5]Kruk, Menno R. “Ethology and pharmacology of hypothalamic aggression in the rat.” &lt;em&gt;Neuroscience &amp;amp; Biobehavioral Reviews&lt;/em&gt; 15.4 (1991): 527-538.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[6]Albert, D. J., R. H. Jonik, and M. L. Walsh. “Hormone-dependent aggression in male and female rats: experiential, hormonal, and neural foundations.” &lt;em&gt;Neuroscience &amp;amp; Biobehavioral Reviews&lt;/em&gt; 16.2 (1992): 177-192.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[7]Flannelly, Kevin J., et al. “Copulation increases offensive attack in male rats.” &lt;em&gt;Physiology &amp;amp; behavior&lt;/em&gt; 29.2 (1982): 381-385.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[8]Blanchard, Robert J., Kevin J. Flannelly, and D. Caroline Blanchard. “Life-span studies of dominance and aggression in established colonies of laboratory rats.” &lt;em&gt;Physiology &amp;amp; behavior&lt;/em&gt; 43.1 (1988): 1-7.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[9]Mustaca, Alba E., Cristina Martínez, and Mauricio R. Papini. “Surprising nonreward reduces aggressive behavior in rats.” &lt;em&gt;International Journal of Comparative Psychology&lt;/em&gt; 13.1 (2000).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[10]Bosch, Oliver J., and Inga D. Neumann. “Both oxytocin and vasopressin are mediators of maternal care and aggression in rodents: from central release to sites of action.” &lt;em&gt;Hormones and behavior&lt;/em&gt; 61.3 (2012): 293-303.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[11]Bosch, Oliver J. “Maternal aggression in rodents: brain oxytocin and vasopressin mediate pup defence.” &lt;em&gt;Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society B: Biological Sciences&lt;/em&gt; 368.1631 (2013): 20130085.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[12]McEllistrem, Joseph E. “Affective and predatory violence: A bimodal classification system of human aggression and violence.” &lt;em&gt;Aggression and violent behavior&lt;/em&gt; 10.1 (2004): 1-30.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[13]Bernard, Bruce K. “Frog killing (ranacide) in the male rat: lack of effect of hormonal manipulations.” &lt;em&gt;Physiology &amp;amp; behavior&lt;/em&gt; 12.3 (1974): 405-408.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[14]Barr, Gordon A., K. E. Moyer, and Judith L. Gibbons. “Effects of imipramine, d-amphetamine, and tripelennamine on mouse and frog killing by the rat.” &lt;em&gt;Physiology &amp;amp; Behavior&lt;/em&gt; 16.3 (1976): 267-269.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[15]Bernard, Bruce K. “Testosterone manipulations: effects on ranacide aggression and brain monoamines in the adult female rat.” &lt;em&gt;Pharmacology Biochemistry and Behavior&lt;/em&gt; 4.1 (1976): 59-65.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[16]Gay, Patricia E., et al. “The effects of d-amphetamine on prey killing and prey eating in the rat and mouse.” &lt;em&gt;Bulletin of the Psychonomic Society&lt;/em&gt; 10.5 (1977): 385-388.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[17]Gammie, Stephen C., et al. “Predatory aggression, but not maternal or intermale aggression, is associated with high voluntary wheel-running behavior in mice.” &lt;em&gt;Hormones and behavior&lt;/em&gt; 44.3 (2003): 209-221.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[18]Weinshenker, Naomi J., and Allan Siegel. “Bimodal classification of aggression: affective defense and predatory attack.” &lt;em&gt;Aggression and Violent Behavior&lt;/em&gt; 7.3 (2002): 237-250.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[19]Al-Maliki, Sami, and Paul F. Brain. “A comparison of effects of simple experimental manipulations on fighting generated by breeding activity and predatory aggression in’TO’strain mice.” &lt;em&gt;Behaviour&lt;/em&gt; 69.3-4 (1979): 183-199.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[20]Wersinger, Scott R., et al. “Disruption of the vasopressin 1b receptor gene impairs the attack component of aggressive behavior in mice.” &lt;em&gt;Genes, Brain and Behavior&lt;/em&gt; 6.7 (2007): 653-660.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[21]Siegel, Allan, and Majid B. Shaikh. “The neural bases of aggression and rage in the cat.” &lt;em&gt;Aggression and Violent Behavior&lt;/em&gt; 2.3 (1997): 241-271.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[22]Shaikh, Majid B., Anda Steinberg, and Allan Siegel. “Evidence that substance P is utilized in medial amygdaloid facilitation of defensive rage behavior in the cat.” &lt;em&gt;Brain research&lt;/em&gt; 625.2 (1993): 283-294.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[23]Schubert, Kristie, et al. “Differential effects of ethanol on feline rage and predatory attack behavior: an underlying neural mechanism.” &lt;em&gt;Alcoholism: Clinical and Experimental Research&lt;/em&gt; 20.5 (1996): 882-889.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[24]Panksepp, Jaak, and Margaret R. Zellner. “Towards a neurobiologically based unified theory of aggression.” &lt;em&gt;REVUE INTERNATIONALE DE PSYCHOLOGIE SOCIALE.&lt;/em&gt; 17 (2004): 37-62.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[25]Inselman-Temkin, Barbara R., and John P. Flynn. “Sex-dependent effects of gonadal and gonadotropic hormones on centrally-elicited attack in cats.” &lt;em&gt;Brain Research&lt;/em&gt; 60.2 (1973): 393-410.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[26]Lipp, Hanspeter P. “Aggression and flight behaviour of the marmoset monkey Callithrix jacchus: an ethogram for brain stimulation studies.” &lt;em&gt;Brain, Behavior and Evolution&lt;/em&gt; 15.4 (1978): 241-259.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[27]Lipp, Hanspeter P., and R. W. Hunsperger. “Threat, Attack and Flight Elicited by Electrical Stimulation of the Ventromedial Hypothalamus of the Marmoset Monkey Callithrix jacchus; pp. 276–293.” &lt;em&gt;Brain, behavior and evolution&lt;/em&gt; 15.4 (1978): 276-293.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[28]Higley, J. Dee, et al. “Cerebrospinal fluid monoamine and adrenal correlates of aggression in free-ranging rhesus monkeys.” &lt;em&gt;Archives of General Psychiatry&lt;/em&gt; 49.6 (1992): 436-441.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[29]Azrin, Nathan H., R. Rv Hutchinson, and R. D. Sallery. “PAIN‐AGGRESSION TOWARD INANIMATE OBJECTS 1.” &lt;em&gt;Journal of the Experimental Analysis of Behavior&lt;/em&gt; 7.3 (1964): 223-228.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[30]Steklis, Horst D., and Glenn E. King. “The craniocervical killing bite: Toward an ethology of primate predatory behavior.” &lt;em&gt;Journal of Human Evolution&lt;/em&gt; 7.7 (1978): 567-581.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[31]Crofoot, Margaret C. “Why mob? Reassessing the costs and benefits of primate predator harassment.” &lt;em&gt;Folia primatologica&lt;/em&gt; 83.3-6 (2012): 252-273.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[32]Wrangham, Richard W. “Two types of aggression in human evolution.” &lt;em&gt;Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences&lt;/em&gt; 115.2 (2018): 245-253.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[33]Haller, József. “The role of the lateral hypothalamus in violent intraspecific aggression—The glucocorticoid deficit hypothesis.” &lt;em&gt;Frontiers in systems neuroscience&lt;/em&gt; 12 (2018): 26.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[34]Albers, GE Demas MA Cooper HE, and K. K. Soma. “8 Novel Mechanisms Underlying Neuroendocrine Regulation of Aggression: A Synthesis of Rodent, Avian, and Primate Studies.” (2007).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[35]Miller, G. M., et al. “A mu-opioid receptor single nucleotide polymorphism in rhesus monkey: association with stress response and aggression.” Molecular psychiatry 9.1 (2004): 99-108.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[36]Jürgens, Uwe, et al. “Vocalization in the squirrel monkey (Saimiri sciureus) elicited by brain stimulation.” &lt;em&gt;Experimental brain research&lt;/em&gt; 4.2 (1967): 114-117.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[37]Higley, J. Dee, et al. “Cerebrospinal fluid monoamine and adrenal correlates of aggression in free-ranging rhesus monkeys.” &lt;em&gt;Archives of General Psychiatry&lt;/em&gt; 49.6 (1992): 436-441.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[38]Raleigh, Michael J., et al. “Serotonergic mechanisms promote dominance acquisition in adult male vervet monkeys.” &lt;em&gt;Brain research&lt;/em&gt; 559.2 (1991): 181-190.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[39]Robinson, Bryan W., Margery Alexander, and Glenda Bowne. “Dominance reversal resulting from aggressive responses evoked by brain telestimulation.” &lt;em&gt;Physiology &amp;amp; Behavior&lt;/em&gt; 4.5 (1969): 749-752.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[40]Rose, Robert M., John W. Holaday, and Irwin S. Bernstein. “Plasma testosterone, dominance rank and aggressive behaviour in male rhesus monkeys.” &lt;em&gt;Nature&lt;/em&gt; 231.5302 (1971): 366-368.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[41]Rosvold, H. Enger, Allan F. Mirsky, and Karl H. Pribram. “Influence of amygdalectomy on social behavior in monkeys.” &lt;em&gt;Journal of comparative and physiological psychology&lt;/em&gt; 47.3 (1954): 173.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[42]Nikulina, Ella M. “Neural control of predatory aggression in wild and domesticated animals.” &lt;em&gt;Neuroscience &amp;amp; Biobehavioral Reviews&lt;/em&gt; 15.4 (1991): 545-547.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[43]Manchanda, S. K., et al. “Predatory aggression induced by hypothalamic stimulation: modulation by midbrain periaqueductal gray (PAG).” &lt;em&gt;Neurobiology (Budapest, Hungary)&lt;/em&gt; 3.3-4 (1995): 405.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[44]McDonough Jr, J. H., F. J. Manning, and To F. Elsmore. “Reduction of predatory aggression of rats following administration of delta-9-tetrahydrocannabinol.” &lt;em&gt;Life Sciences&lt;/em&gt; 11.3 (1972): 103-111.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[45]McDonough Jr, J. H., F. J. Manning, and To F. Elsmore. “Reduction of predatory aggression of rats following administration of delta-9-tetrahydrocannabinol.” &lt;em&gt;Life Sciences&lt;/em&gt; 11.3 (1972): 103-111.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[46]Konczal, Mateusz, et al. “Genomic response to selection for predatory behavior in a mammalian model of adaptive radiation.” &lt;em&gt;Molecular Biology and Evolution&lt;/em&gt; 33.9 (2016): 2429-2440.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[47]de Boer, Sietse F. “Animal models of excessive aggression: implications for human aggression and violence.” &lt;em&gt;Current opinion in psychology&lt;/em&gt; 19 (2018): 81-87.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[48]Albert, D. J., and M. L. Walsh. “Neural systems and the inhibitory modulation of agonistic behavior: a comparison of mammalian species.” &lt;em&gt;Neuroscience &amp;amp; Biobehavioral Reviews&lt;/em&gt; 8.1 (1984): 5-24.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[49]Bygott, J. David. “Cannibalism among wild chimpanzees.” &lt;em&gt;Nature&lt;/em&gt; 238.5364 (1972): 410-411.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[50]Gammie, Stephen C., et al. “Corticotropin-releasing factor inhibits maternal aggression in mice.” &lt;em&gt;Behavioral neuroscience&lt;/em&gt; 118.4 (2004): 805.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[51]Gammie, Stephen C., et al. “Altered gene expression in mice selected for high maternal aggression.” &lt;em&gt;Genes, Brain and Behavior&lt;/em&gt; 6.5 (2007): 432-443.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[52]Flannelly, Kevin J., et al. “Effects of septal-forebrain lesions on maternal aggression and maternal care.” &lt;em&gt;Behavioral and neural biology&lt;/em&gt; 45.1 (1986): 17-30.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[53]Gammie, Stephen C., et al. “Neurotensin inversely modulates maternal aggression.” &lt;em&gt;Neuroscience&lt;/em&gt; 158.4 (2009): 1215-1223.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[54]Holschbach, M. Allie, Erika M. Vitale, and Joseph S. Lonstein. “Serotonin-specific lesions of the dorsal raphe disrupt maternal aggression and caregiving in postpartum rats.” &lt;em&gt;Behavioural brain research&lt;/em&gt; 348 (2018): 53-64.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[55]Albert, D. J., et al. “Maternal aggression and intermale social aggression: A behavioral comparison.” &lt;em&gt;Behavioural processes&lt;/em&gt; 14.3 (1987): 267-276.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[56]Lonstein, Joseph S., and Judith M. Stern. “Role of the midbrain periaqueductal gray in maternal nurturance and aggression: c-fos and electrolytic lesion studies in lactating rats.” &lt;em&gt;Journal of Neuroscience&lt;/em&gt; 17.9 (1997): 3364-3378.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[57]Siegel, Allan, and Kristie Schubert. “Neurotransmitters regulating feline aggressive behavior.” &lt;em&gt;Reviews in the Neurosciences&lt;/em&gt; 6.1 (1995): 47-62.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[58]Czoty, Paul W., Robert W. Gould, and Michael A. Nader. “Relationship between social rank and cortisol and testosterone concentrations in male cynomolgus monkeys (Macaca fascicularis).” &lt;em&gt;Journal of neuroendocrinology&lt;/em&gt; 21.1 (2009): 68-76.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[59]Stavisky, R. C., et al. “Dominance, cortisol, and behavior in small groups of female cynomolgus monkeys (Macaca fascicularis).” &lt;em&gt;Hormones and Behavior&lt;/em&gt; 39.3 (2001): 232-238.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[60]McGuire, Michael T., Gary L. Brammer, and Michael J. Raleigh. “Resting cortisol levels and the emergence of dominant status among male vervet monkeys.” &lt;em&gt;Hormones and behavior&lt;/em&gt; 20.1 (1986): 106-117.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[61]Anestis, Stephanie F. “Behavioral style, dominance rank, and urinary cortisol in young chimpanzees (Pan troglodytes).” &lt;em&gt;Behaviour&lt;/em&gt; 142.9-10 (2005): 1245-1268.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[62]Siegel, Allan, et al. “Neuropharmacology of brain-stimulation-evoked aggression.” &lt;em&gt;Neuroscience &amp;amp; Biobehavioral Reviews&lt;/em&gt; 23.3 (1999): 359-389.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[63]Farrokhi, Catherine, et al. “Effects of the CRF1 antagonist SSR125543A on aggressive behaviors in hamsters.” &lt;em&gt;Pharmacology Biochemistry and Behavior&lt;/em&gt; 77.3 (2004): 465-469.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[64]Johns, Josephine M., et al. “The effects of dopaminergic/serotonergic reuptake inhibition on maternal behavior, maternal aggression, and oxytocin in the rat.” &lt;em&gt;Pharmacology Biochemistry and Behavior&lt;/em&gt; 81.4 (2005): 769-785.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[65]Olivier, Berend, Jan Mos, and Ruud Van Oorschot. “Maternal aggression in rats: effects of chlordiazepoxide and fluprazine.” &lt;em&gt;Psychopharmacology&lt;/em&gt; 86.1-2 (1985): 68-76.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[66]Trainor, Brian C., M. Sima Finy, and Randy J. Nelson. “Paternal aggression in a biparental mouse: Parallels with maternal aggression.” &lt;em&gt;Hormones and behavior&lt;/em&gt; 53.1 (2008): 200-207.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[67]Mos, Jan, and Berend Olivier. “Quantitative and comparative analyses of pro-aggressive actions of benzodiazepines in maternal aggression of rats.” &lt;em&gt;Psychopharmacology&lt;/em&gt; 97.2 (1989): 152-153.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[67]Mann, Martha A., and Bruce Svare. “Prenatal testosterone exposure elevates maternal aggression in mice.” &lt;em&gt;Physiology &amp;amp; Behavior&lt;/em&gt; 30.4 (1983): 503-507.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[68]Mann, Martha A., and Bruce Svare. “Prenatal testosterone exposure elevates maternal aggression in mice.” &lt;em&gt;Physiology &amp;amp; Behavior&lt;/em&gt; 30.4 (1983): 503-507.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[69]Yoshimura, Hiroyuki, and Nobuya Ogawa. “Acute and chronic effects of psychotropic drugs on maternal aggression in mice.” &lt;em&gt;Psychopharmacology&lt;/em&gt; 97.3 (1989): 339-342.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[70]Ieni, John R., and John B. Thurmond. “Maternal aggression in mice: effects of treatments with PCPA, 5-HTP and 5-HT receptor antagonists.” &lt;em&gt;European journal of pharmacology&lt;/em&gt; 111.2 (1985): 211-220.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[71]Bayerl, Doris S., Stefanie M. Klampfl, and Oliver J. Bosch. “More than reproduction: Central gonadotropin‐releasing hormone antagonism decreases maternal aggression in lactating rats.” &lt;em&gt;Journal of neuroendocrinology&lt;/em&gt; 31.9 (2019): e12709.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[72]Gammie, Stephen C., Uade B. Olaghere-da Silva, and Randy J. Nelson. “3-Bromo-7-nitroindazole, a neuronal nitric oxide synthase inhibitor, impairs maternal aggression and citrulline immunoreactivity in prairie voles.” &lt;em&gt;Brain Research&lt;/em&gt; 870.1-2 (2000): 80-86.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[73]Cox, Elizabeth Thomas, et al. “Combined norepinephrine/serotonergic reuptake inhibition: effects on maternal behavior, aggression, and oxytocin in the rat.” &lt;em&gt;Frontiers in psychiatry&lt;/em&gt; 2 (2011): 34.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[74]Harrison, Robert J., et al. “Chronic anabolic-androgenic steroid treatment during adolescence increases anterior hypothalamic vasopressin and aggression in intact hamsters.” &lt;em&gt;Psychoneuroendocrinology&lt;/em&gt; 25.4 (2000): 317-338.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[75]Lynch, W. C., L. Libby, and H. F. Johnson. “Naloxone inhibits intermale aggression in isolated mice.” &lt;em&gt;Psychopharmacology&lt;/em&gt; 79.4 (1983): 370-371.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[76]Veenema, Alexa H., et al. “Low inborn anxiety correlates with high intermale aggression: link to ACTH response and neuronal activation of the hypothalamic paraventricular nucleus.” &lt;em&gt;Hormones and behavior&lt;/em&gt; 51.1 (2007): 11-19.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[77]Price, Edward O., and Paul L. Belanger. “Maternal behavior of wild and domestic stocks of Norway rats.” &lt;em&gt;Behavioral Biology&lt;/em&gt; 20.1 (1977): 60-69.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[78]Abel, Ernest L. “Cannabis and aggression in animals.” &lt;em&gt;Behavioral biology&lt;/em&gt; 14.1 (1975): 1-20.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[79]Eichelman, Burr S. “Effect of subcortical lesions on shock-induced aggression in the rat.” &lt;em&gt;Journal of Comparative and Physiological Psychology&lt;/em&gt; 74.3 (1971): 331.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[80]Kovacsics, Colleen E., and Todd D. Gould. “Shock-induced aggression in mice is modified by lithium.” &lt;em&gt;Pharmacology Biochemistry and Behavior&lt;/em&gt; 94.3 (2010): 380-386.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[81]Eichelman, Burr, and Jack Barchas. “Facilitated shock-induced aggression following antidepressive medication in the rat.” &lt;em&gt;Pharmacology Biochemistry and Behavior&lt;/em&gt; 3.4 (1975): 601-604.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[82]Geyer, Mark A., and David S. Segal. “Shock-induced aggression: opposite effects of intraventricularly infused dopamine and norepinephrine.” &lt;em&gt;Behavioral Biology&lt;/em&gt; 10.1 (1974): 99-104.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[83]Cleary, James, Juan Herakovic, and Alan Poling. “Effects of phencyclidine on shock-induced aggression in rats.” &lt;em&gt;Pharmacology Biochemistry and Behavior&lt;/em&gt; 15.5 (1981): 813-818.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[84]Creer, Thomas L., and D. A. Powell. “Effect of repeated shock presentations and different stimulus intensities on shock-induced aggression.” &lt;em&gt;Psychonomic Science&lt;/em&gt; 24.3 (1971): 133-134.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[85]Sands, Jennifer, and Scott Creel. “Social dominance, aggression and faecal glucocorticoid levels in a wild population of wolves, Canis lupus.” &lt;em&gt;Animal behaviour&lt;/em&gt; 67.3 (2004): 387-396.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[86]Cassidy, Kira A., et al. “Sexually dimorphic aggression indicates male gray wolves specialize in pack defense against conspecific groups.” &lt;em&gt;Behavioural processes&lt;/em&gt; 136 (2017): 64-72.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[87]van Kesteren, Freya, et al. “Sex, stress and social status: patterns in fecal testosterone and glucocorticoid metabolites in male Ethiopian wolves.” &lt;em&gt;General and comparative endocrinology&lt;/em&gt; 179.1 (2012): 30-37.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[88]Creel, Scott. “Dominance, aggression, and glucocorticoid levels in social carnivores.” &lt;em&gt;Journal of Mammalogy&lt;/em&gt; 86.2 (2005): 255-264.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[89]MacLean, Evan L., et al. “Endogenous oxytocin, vasopressin, and aggression in domestic dogs.” &lt;em&gt;Frontiers in psychology&lt;/em&gt; 8 (2017): 1613.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[90]Beehner, Jacinta C., Jane E. Phillips‐Conroy, and Patricia L. Whitten. “Female testosterone, dominance rank, and aggression in an Ethiopian population of hybrid baboons.” &lt;em&gt;American Journal of Primatology: Official Journal of the American Society of Primatologists&lt;/em&gt; 67.1 (2005): 101-119.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[91]Ferris, Craig F., and Michael Potegal. “Vasopressin receptor blockade in the anterior hypothalamus suppresses aggression in hamsters.” &lt;em&gt;Physiology &amp;amp; behavior&lt;/em&gt; 44.2 (1988): 235-239.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[92]Ross, Corinna N., and Jeffrey A. French. “Female marmosets’ behavioral and hormonal responses to unfamiliar intruders.” &lt;em&gt;American Journal of Primatology&lt;/em&gt; 73.10 (2011): 1072-1081.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[93]Girolami, L., et al. “Agonistic behavior, plasma testosterone, and hypothalamic estradiol binding in male rabbits.” &lt;em&gt;Aggressive Behavior: Official Journal of the International Society for Research on Aggression&lt;/em&gt; 23.1 (1997): 33-40.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[94]Emley, Grace S., and Ronald R. Hutchinson. “Effects of phencyclidine on aggressive behavior in squirrel monkeys.” &lt;em&gt;Pharmacology Biochemistry and Behavior&lt;/em&gt; 18.2 (1983): 163-166.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[95]Weerts, Elise M., and Klaus A. Miczek. “Primate vocalizations during social separation and aggression: effects of alcohol and benzodiazepines.” &lt;em&gt;Psychopharmacology&lt;/em&gt; 127.1-2 (1996): 255-264.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[96]Miczek, Klaus A., et al. “Alcohol, GABA A-benzodiazepine receptor complex, and aggression.” &lt;em&gt;Recent developments in alcoholism&lt;/em&gt;. Springer, Boston, MA, 2002. 139-171.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[97]Sapolsky, Robert M. “The endocrine stress-response and social status in the wild baboon.” &lt;em&gt;Hormones and behavior&lt;/em&gt; 16.3 (1982): 279-292.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[98]Muller, Martin N., and Richard W. Wrangham. “Dominance, aggression and testosterone in wild chimpanzees: a test of the ‘challenge hypothesis’.” &lt;em&gt;Animal Behaviour&lt;/em&gt; 67.1 (2004): 113-123.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[99]Wrangham, Richard W., Michael L. Wilson, and Martin N. Muller. “Comparative rates of violence in chimpanzees and humans.” &lt;em&gt;Primates&lt;/em&gt; 47.1 (2006): 14-26.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[100]Anestis, Stephanie F. “Testosterone in juvenile and adolescent male chimpanzees (Pan troglodytes): Effects of dominance rank, aggression, and behavioral style.” &lt;em&gt;American Journal of Physical Anthropology: The Official Publication of the American Association of Physical Anthropologists&lt;/em&gt; 130.4 (2006): 536-545.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[101]Strum, Shirley C. “Primate predation: Interim report on the development of a tradition in a troop of olive baboons.” Science 187.4178 (1975): 755-757.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[102]Richard, Rebecca, Brandon Boren, and Jeffrey Becker. “The use of citalopram hydrobromide to manage aggression in a male chimpanzee (pan troglodytes).” &lt;em&gt;Journal of Zoo and Wildlife Medicine&lt;/em&gt; 50.4 (2020): 1005-1007.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[103]Shively, Carol A., et al. “Sertraline effects on cerebrospinal fluid monoamines and species-typical socioemotional behavior of female cynomolgus monkeys.” &lt;em&gt;Psychopharmacology&lt;/em&gt; 231.7 (2014): 1409-1416.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[104]Shively, Carol A., Kathleen A. Grant, and Thomas C. Register. “Effects of long-term moderate alcohol consumption on agonistic and affiliative behavior of socially housed female cynomolgus monkeys (Macaca fascicularis).” &lt;em&gt;Psychopharmacology&lt;/em&gt; 165.1 (2002): 1-8&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[105]Shively, Carol A., Kathleen A. Grant, and Thomas C. Register. “Effects of long-term moderate alcohol consumption on agonistic and affiliative behavior of socially housed female cynomolgus monkeys (Macaca fascicularis).” &lt;em&gt;Psychopharmacology&lt;/em&gt; 165.1 (2002): 1-8..&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[106]Gadeleta, S. J., et al. “A physical, chemical, and mechanical study of lumbar vertebrae from normal, ovariectomized, and nandrolone decanoate-treated cynomolgus monkeys (Macaca fascicularis).” &lt;em&gt;Bone&lt;/em&gt; 27.4 (2000): 541-550.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[107]Michopoulos, Vasiliki, et al. “Social subordination produces distinct stress-related phenotypes in female rhesus monkeys.” &lt;em&gt;Psychoneuroendocrinology&lt;/em&gt; 37.7 (2012): 1071-1085.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[108]Patton, M. L., et al. “Aggression control in a bachelor herd of fringe‐eared oryx (Oryx gazella callotis), with melengestrol acetate: Behavioral and endocrine observations.” &lt;em&gt;Zoo Biology: Published in affiliation with the American Zoo and Aquarium Association&lt;/em&gt; 20.5 (2001): 375-388.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[109]Kromrey, Sarah A., et al. “Preclinical laboratory assessments of predictors of social rank in female cynomolgus monkeys.” &lt;em&gt;American journal of primatology&lt;/em&gt; 78.4 (2016): 402-417.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[110]Rearden, John J. “Dominance and aggression in the Mongolian gerbil (Meriones unguiculatus).” &lt;em&gt;Psychological reports&lt;/em&gt; (1974).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[111]Piña-Andrade, Sonia, et al. “Testosterone dependent territorial aggression is modulated by cohabitation with a female in male Mongolian gerbils (Meriones unguiculatus).” &lt;em&gt;Hormones and Behavior&lt;/em&gt; 117 (2020): 104611.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[111]Ginsburg, Harvey J., Steve A. Norris, and Gail Hudson. “Delta-9-tetrahydrocannabinol affects consummatory but not appetitive sequence of interspecific aggression in the Mongolian gerbil (Meriones unguiculatus).” &lt;em&gt;Bulletin of the Psychonomic Society&lt;/em&gt; 10.5 (1977): 361-363.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[112]Creel, Scott, David E. Wildt, and Steven L. Monfort. “Aggression, reproduction, and androgens in wild dwarf mongooses: a test of the challenge hypothesis.” &lt;em&gt;The American Naturalist&lt;/em&gt; 141.5 (1993): 816-825.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[113]Winslow, James T., et al. “A role for central vasopressin in pair bonding in monogamous prairie voles.” &lt;em&gt;Nature&lt;/em&gt; 365.6446 (1993): 545-548.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[114]Winslow, James T., et al. “A role for central vasopressin in pair bonding in monogamous prairie voles.” &lt;em&gt;Nature&lt;/em&gt; 365.6446 (1993): 545-548.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[115]Demas, Gregory E., et al. “Castration does not inhibit aggressive behavior in adult male prairie voles (Microtus ochrogaster).” &lt;em&gt;Physiology &amp;amp; Behavior&lt;/em&gt; 66.1 (1999): 59-62.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[116]Bertoglio, Leandro José, Valquiria Camin de Bortoli, and Hélio Zangrossi Jr. “Cholecystokinin-2 receptors modulate freezing and escape behaviors evoked by the electrical stimulation of the rat dorsolateral periaqueductal gray.” &lt;em&gt;Brain research&lt;/em&gt; 1156 (2007): 133-138.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[117]Naganuma, Fumito, et al. “Histamine N-methyltransferase regulates aggression and the sleep-wake cycle.” &lt;em&gt;Scientific reports&lt;/em&gt; 7.1 (2017): 1-9.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[118]De Felipe, Carmen, et al. “Altered nociception, analgesia and aggression in mice lacking the receptor for substance P.” &lt;em&gt;Nature&lt;/em&gt; 392.6674 (1998): 394-397.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="lit-review" /><summary type="html">Introduction</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Chronic Mania and Persistent Euphoric States</title><link href="https://srconstantin.github.io/2020/07/29/chronic-mania.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Chronic Mania and Persistent Euphoric States" /><published>2020-07-29T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-07-29T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://srconstantin.github.io/2020/07/29/chronic-mania</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://srconstantin.github.io/2020/07/29/chronic-mania.html">&lt;p&gt;Can a human be happy all the time?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me clarify; I don’t mean “happiness” in any kind of complex sense. I don’t mean wellbeing or eudaimonia or life satisfaction or anything like that.  I mean &lt;em&gt;being in a good mood&lt;/em&gt; – better than good, “high”, bubbly, enthusiastic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the psychiatry literature they call this state “euphoria” or “elation.”  It can be produced by recreational drugs, or by placing electrodes in some locations in the brain, or by some brain injuries, or by neurological or psychiatric disorders.  It is common in manic and hypomanic episodes.  And, of course, it is a normal mood that healthy sober people can enter as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But most euphoric states are transient, and most ways to deliberately induce euphoria don’t work. Morphine, for instance, can produce euphoria, but not continuously for months at a time; you develop tolerance for the drug until the euphoria-producing dose and the fatal dose intersect.  And people who have a stroke of good fortune like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hedonic_treadmill#Happiness_set_point&quot;&gt;winning the lottery&lt;/a&gt; don’t stay euphoric forever – they initially feel great but then &lt;em&gt;adapt&lt;/em&gt; to their changed circumstances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, you might ask, is there some kind of negative feedback loop in the brain such that euphoria is &lt;em&gt;always&lt;/em&gt; temporary?  Is it literally impossible to feel awesome all the time, for months or years at a stretch?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Turns out the answer is no.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is something called chronic mania, which is just what it sounds like: a manic state, including euphoria/elation, which lasts for over 6 months, sometimes forever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The nineteenth-century psychiatrist Emil Kraepelin was the first to give a clinical description of chronic mania, though some modern neurologists think that today those patients would be diagnosed with frontotemporal dementia[1], and in his day, chronic mania was the second most common reason for a patient to be committed to a mental hospital.[2]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apart from the length of their episodes, chronic mania patients differ from bipolar patients in a few systematic ways.  Chronic mania generally doesn’t alternate with depression, and is more likely than bipolar mania to come with an “elated mood.”  Chronic mania, compared to bipolar mania, is more likely to come with delusions, especially delusions of grandeur, while bipolar mania is more likely to come with symptoms of psychomotor agitation like tension, pressured speech, loss of sleep, and elevated sex drive.[2] Chronic mania is more likely to begin after age 40.[3]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The typical pattern, from case studies, seems to be of a person who may have had transient manic episodes in the past, “settling into” a chronic manic state where they are generally euphoric but out of touch with reality, engaging in reckless, inappropriate, or obnoxious behavior, until they come to the attention of psychiatrists when neighbors or relatives bring them to the hospital.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Case Studies&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kraepelin commented on the behavioral disinhibition and poor impulse control of chronic mania patients:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Only the coarser enjoyments, eating, drinking, smoking, snuffing, still arouse in them vivid feelings, further the satisfaction of their personal wishes and wants…[they] talk more than their share, swagger, try to gain for themselves all possible little advantage.”[1]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He also notes that they engage in hoarding behavior:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“They collect all possible rubbish in their pockets, make a mess with it all round about, rub and wipe things, adorn themselves with rags and scraps of ribbon.”[1]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Frederic Wertham, a psychiatrist writing in 1929, described cases of chronic mania that fit the overall pattern.[4]  In all seven cases, the chronic mania began after age 30 (later than the typical onset of bipolar disorder), and in all cases it lasted several years.  In several cases, the patients had previously had briefer manic episodes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wertham describes traits such as “pressure of activity, great sociability, lack of fatigue, good humor”, “noisiness and talkativeness”, “buoyant” and “elated” moods, “wild schemes” and delusions (of unrealistic business deals, religious revelations, million-dollar inheritances),  “joviality and playfulness with jokes and laughing”, “vulgar and profane” language and sexual advances towards nurses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like Kraepelin’s patients, one of Wertham’s patients collects useless items and decorates herself – she “wore flowers in her hair and bits of colored wool tied to her buttons…continued decorating herself with little objects.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wertham notes some patterns: chronic mania patients tend to be middle-aged at onset, tend to have highly sociable and active personalities even before their illness, have no sign of cognitive decline (as you’d expect in dementia), and tend to be heavyset.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similar features show up in more recent case studies of chronic mania: older age, hoarding, delusions, disinhibited behavior.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One 68-year-old woman[5] had been in an “elevated mood” state for 30 years, during which she increasingly hoarded objects and lived in increasing squalor, refusing all help. She had no sign of dementia or memory loss when tested, and no history of drug abuse. Prior to her illness she had had one depressive episode after the death of her husband, and before that she had been a “rather jovial schoolmistress” – like Wertham’s patients, her baseline personality was cheerful.  She recovered after treatment with lithium.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A 65-year-old Indian man had been manic for 48 years,[6] with the onset beginning after a fever at age 12.  He was “cheerful, optimistic, talkative, outgoing, and overly confident,” and became involved in politics with some success. But he also engaged in reckless behavior, traveling by train across India without paying his fare, stealing objects and giving them away to the poor. He “would often describe himself as a messenger of God with special powers, stating God had created him for the welfare of poor people”.  He couldn’t hold down a job and he was divorced twice, but his mood was “persistently cheerful or irritable.”  He was eventually hospitalized due to complaints by neighbors and relatives, and recovered after a temporary course of treatment with antipsychotics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A 33-year-old woman who had been manic for 17 years[7] “expressed grandiose beliefs and evidenced a euphoric mood”, and had been unable to keep a job due to her “over-familiar” behavior.  She had never abused drugs.  “Her parents described her premorbid personality as generally affable, co-operative and creative but occasionally forceful and stubborn.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Chronic Mania and Brain Damage&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A variety of case studies of chronic mania identified a neurological cause.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One young woman who had mania-like symptoms since childhood (behavior problems, restlessness, talkativeness, labile and disinhibited mood, sexually provocative behavior starting at adolescence) was found upon radiological examination to have severe degeneration of the cerebellum.[8]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another patient, a young man who had been electrocuted by getting entangled with a wire two years previously, developed manic symptoms of grandiose and persecutory delusions, hallucinations, poor judgment, and increased appetite.[9]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A 55-year-old man who had become irritable, extremely sociable, and extravagant with money was found to have an oligodendroglioma, a large brain tumor in the left temporoparietal lobe, and his symptoms improved after surgery.[10]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An eight-year-old child who had been ill with polioencephalomyelitis had a marked personality change – “he started talking excessively, singing songs and dancing. The symptoms became worse once he came home. He started talking with relatives, neighbours and strangers, content of talk was how he would act in a movie, how he would build a big house, that he would marry a beautiful lady, etc. He was singing film songs, was going out of the house and it used to be very difficult to locate and bring him back. His appetite was increased, sleep was disturbed. Majority of the time, he was very happy and cheerful.”[11]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A patient with a stroke damaging the periventricular zone of the hypothalamus was reported to have developed “persistent euphoria”, while in another case of brain surgery on the hypothalamus, “every time the surgeon gently wiped coagulated blood from the ventricle floor the patient burst out laughing, whistled, made jokes, and uttered obscene remarks.”[12]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An 81-year-old woman with a stroke in the right thalamus “became increasingly euphoric and talkative, and had grandiose delusions…believed that her health was better than ever and joked inappropriately. She also reported a decreased need for sleep.” After treatment with a temporary course of antipsychotics, she recovered but was still “mildly euthymic.”[13]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Out  of 66 consecutive patients treated for head trauma, 6 (9%) developed mania[14]. The only lesion location significantly associated with mania was the temporal pole (p = 0.0005), which is also one of the first areas damaged in frontotemporal dementia and Alzheimer’s disease.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Compared to patients who developed bipolar disorder after brain injury, patients who developed only mania after brain injury were significantly more likely to have cortical lesions (esp. the orbitofrontal cortex and the right basotemporal cortex.)[15]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another study found that mania after brain injury was “was associated primarily with orbitofrontal, thatamic, caudate, and basotemporal lesions in the right hemisphere.”[16]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most common locations of lesions for patients with post-stroke mania (out of 74 cases) are the right frontal lobe and basal ganglia. Out of 16 patients who developed mania after a brain tumor, the tumor was in the frontal lobe, temporal lobe, or subcortical limbic structure in 13 patients, and two patients (12.5%) had chronic mania.  [17]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the symptoms of multiple sclerosis is reported to be euphoria, or “euphoria sclerotica”, an unusual cheerfulness, optimism, and lack of awareness of their physical disability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a study of 44 MS patients and 22 healthy controls, 13% of MS patients had euphoria and 13% had disinhibition while no control subjects had either.  There was a significant (p &amp;lt; 0.01) correlation between the degree of euphoria in the MS patients and the severity of frontotemporal degeneration observable on an MRI. [18]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Charcot’s original definition of multiple sclerosis in 1873 described “foolish laughter without cause” as one of the symptoms; Brown and Davis, in their survey of 100 cases in 1926, reported 63% of patients were euphoric.  In an 1986 study of 76 MS patients, 48% were found to be euphoric, and the euphoric patients were more likely than the non-euphoric ones to have a progressive course of disease, to have brain involvement, and to have more severe physical &amp;amp; functional disability.[19]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brain damage can cause mania, including chronic mania, in patients with no psychiatric history, particularly damage to the frontal and temporal lobes. Damage to other locations such as the cerebellum, thalamus, and hypothalamus can also cause mania.  There also seems to be a tendency for mania to be more common as a result of damage to the right brain hemisphere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The frontal and temporal lobes are involved in self-restraint and appropriate behavior, so it’s not surprising that damage to them should cause some of the disinhibitory and compulsive aspects of mania. Apparently, brain damage can also cause persistently euphoric states.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think we can safely say that it &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; possible for humans to remain in a euphoric state, continuously for months or years on end.  (Often in these case studies the euphoria is punctuated by irritability, but &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; sadness or depressed mood.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, most of the examples we know of these prolonged euphoric states are undesirable. They often come with reckless or harmful behavior, delusions, and cognitive impairment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They’re also unpredictable – some but not all people who get strokes, tumors, or injuries to these brain areas will become manic or otherwise euphoric.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the existence of persistent euphoric states suggests that it could be in principle possible to deliberately induce a long-lasting elevated mood without some of the problematic side effects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a common finding that deep brain stimulation of the nucleus accumbens or subthalamic nucleus can cause transient feelings of euphoria, and sometimes outright manic episodes.[21][22][23][24][25][26][27][28]  However, there is a tolerance effect here – with continuous stimulation for a year, the same stimulus that initially caused euphoria produced no perceivable effect at 12 months.[29]  It’s not impossible that some variant on this type of electrical stimulation could produce long-term euphoria, though, at a deliberately tuned dose (since higher voltages cause stronger mood effects).  So I’m intrigued by the prospects of developing a form of “&lt;a href=&quot;https://qualiacomputing.com/2016/08/20/wireheading_done_right/&quot;&gt;wireheading done right&lt;/a&gt;.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[1]Gambogi, Leandro Boson, et al. “Kraepelin’s description of chronic mania: a clinical picture that meets the behavioral variant frontotemporal dementia phenotype.” &lt;em&gt;Arquivos de neuro-psiquiatria&lt;/em&gt; 74.9 (2016): 775-777.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[2]Perugi, Giulio, et al. “Chronic mania.” &lt;em&gt;The British journal of psychiatry&lt;/em&gt; 173.6 (1998): 514-518.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[3]Cameron, Kenneth. “Chronic mania.” &lt;em&gt;Journal of Mental Science&lt;/em&gt; 82.340 (1936): 592-594.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[4]Wertham, F. I. “A group of benign chronic psychoses: prolonged manic excitements: with a statistical study of age, duration and frequency in 2000 manic attacks.” &lt;em&gt;American Journal of Psychiatry&lt;/em&gt; 86.1 (1929): 17-78.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[5]Fond, G., F. Jollant, and M. Abbar. “The need to consider mood disorders, and especially chronic mania, in cases of Diogenes syndrome (squalor syndrome).” &lt;em&gt;International psychogeriatrics&lt;/em&gt; 23.3 (2011): 505.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[6]Mendhekar, D. N., et al. “Chronic but not resistant mania: a case report.” &lt;em&gt;Acta Psychiatrica Scandinavica&lt;/em&gt; 109.2 (2004): 147-149.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[7]Malhi, G. S., P. B. Mitchell, and G. B. Parker. “Rediscovering chronic mania.” &lt;em&gt;Acta Psychiatrica Scandinavica&lt;/em&gt; 104.2 (2001): 153-156.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[8]Cutting, J. C. “Chronic mania in childhood: case report of a possible association with a radiological picture of cerebellar disease.” &lt;em&gt;Psychological medicine&lt;/em&gt; 6.4 (1977): 635-642.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[9]Ameen, Shahul, Siddhartha Dutta, and Vinod Kumar Sinha. “Electroencephalogram changes and its improvement with sodium valproate in a patient with electrocution-induced chronic mania.” &lt;em&gt;Bipolar disorders&lt;/em&gt; 5.3 (2003): 228-229.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[10]Rahul, S. A. H. A., and Kiran Jakhar. “Oligodendroglioma presenting as chronic mania.” &lt;em&gt;Shanghai archives of psychiatry&lt;/em&gt; 27.3 (2015): 183.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[11]Subrahmanya, B., and Shivaprakash HS Narayana. “CHRONIC MANIA FOLLOWING POLIOENCEPHALOMYELITIS—A CASE REPORT.” &lt;em&gt;Indian journal of psychiatry&lt;/em&gt; 23.3 (1981): 266.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[12]Barbosa, Daniel AN, et al. “The hypothalamus at the crossroads of psychopathology and neurosurgery.” &lt;em&gt;Neurosurgical focus&lt;/em&gt; 43.3 (2017): E15.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[13]Kulisevsky, Jaime, Marcelo L. Berthier, and Jesús Pujol. “Hemiballismus and secondary mania following a right thalamic infarction.” &lt;em&gt;Neurology&lt;/em&gt; 43.7 (1993): 1422-1422.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[14]Jorge, Ricardo E., et al. “Secondary mania following traumatic brain injury.” &lt;em&gt;American Journal of Psychiatry&lt;/em&gt; 150 (1993): 916-916.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[15]Starkstein, Sergio E., et al. “Manic-depressive and pure manic states after brain lesions.” &lt;em&gt;Biological Psychiatry&lt;/em&gt; 29.2 (1991): 149-158.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[16]Robinson, Robert G., et al. “Comparison of mania and depression after brain injury: causal factors.” &lt;em&gt;Am J Psychiatry&lt;/em&gt; 145.2 (1988): 172-178.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[17]Satzer, David, and David J. Bond. “Mania secondary to focal brain lesions: implications for understanding the functional neuroanatomy of bipolar disorder.” &lt;em&gt;Bipolar Disorders&lt;/em&gt; 18.3 (2016): 205-220.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[18]Diaz-Olavarrieta, Claudia, et al. “Neuropsychiatric manifestations of multiple sclerosis.” &lt;em&gt;The Journal of neuropsychiatry and clinical neurosciences&lt;/em&gt; 11.1 (1999): 51-57.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[19]Rabins, PETER V. “Euphoria in multiple sclerosis.” &lt;em&gt;Neurobehavioral aspects of multiple sclerosis&lt;/em&gt; (1990): 180-185.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[20]Mosley, Philip E., et al. “Persistence of mania after cessation of stimulation following subthalamic deep brain stimulation.” &lt;em&gt;The Journal of neuropsychiatry and clinical neurosciences&lt;/em&gt; 30.3 (2018): 246-249.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[21]Synofzik, Matthis, Thomas E. Schlaepfer, and Joseph J. Fins. “How happy is too happy? Euphoria, neuroethics, and deep brain stimulation of the nucleus accumbens.” &lt;em&gt;AJOB Neuroscience&lt;/em&gt; 3.1 (2012): 30-36&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[22]Haq, Ihtsham U., et al. “Smile and laughter induction and intraoperative predictors of response to deep brain stimulation for obsessive-compulsive disorder.” &lt;em&gt;Neuroimage&lt;/em&gt; 54 (2011): S247-S255.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[23]Anderson, Karen E., and Jake Mullins. “Behavioral changes associated with deep brain stimulation surgery for Parkinson’s disease.” &lt;em&gt;Current neurology and neuroscience reports&lt;/em&gt; 3.4 (2003): 306-313.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[24]Greenberg, Benjamin D., et al. “Three-year outcomes in deep brain stimulation for highly resistant obsessive–compulsive disorder.” &lt;em&gt;Neuropsychopharmacology&lt;/em&gt; 31.11 (2006): 2384-239&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[25]Kuhn, Jens, et al. “Transient Manic‐like Episode Following Bilateral Deep Brain Stimulation of the Nucleus Accumbens and the Internal Capsule in a Patient With Tourette Syndrome.” &lt;em&gt;Neuromodulation: Technology at the Neural Interface&lt;/em&gt; 11.2 (2008): 128-131.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[26]Mosley, Philip E., et al. “Persistence of mania after cessation of stimulation following subthalamic deep brain stimulation.” _The Journal of neuropsychiatry and clinical neurosciences _30.3&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[27]Chopra, Amit, et al. “Voltage-dependent mania after subthalamic nucleus deep brain stimulation in Parkinson’s disease: a case report.” &lt;em&gt;Biological psychiatry&lt;/em&gt; 70.2 (2011): e5-e7.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[28]Tsai, Hsin-Chi, et al. “Hypomania following bilateral ventral capsule stimulation in a patient with refractory obsessive-compulsive disorder.” &lt;em&gt;Biological psychiatry&lt;/em&gt; 68.2 (2010): e7-e8.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[29]Springer, Utaka S., et al. “Long-term habituation of the smile response with deep brain stimulation.” &lt;em&gt;Neurocase&lt;/em&gt; 12.3 (2006): 191-196.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="lit-review" /><category term="medicine" /><summary type="html">Can a human be happy all the time?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">COVID-19 Vaccine Update</title><link href="https://srconstantin.github.io/2020/07/24/COVID-19-vaccine-update.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="COVID-19 Vaccine Update" /><published>2020-07-24T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-07-24T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://srconstantin.github.io/2020/07/24/COVID-19-vaccine-update</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://srconstantin.github.io/2020/07/24/COVID-19-vaccine-update.html">&lt;p&gt;So far I’ve found 6 vaccine candidates that are reporting positive results from clinical trials.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moderna [1] has been testing an mRNA vaccine called mRNA-1273, consisting of the RNA encoding a portion of the COVID-19 virus’s spike protein, wrapped in a lipid nanoparticle. Their Phase 1 study on 45 healthy adults aged 18-55 found that there was a dose-dependent antibody response (relative to baseline) lasting until the end of the 60-day study, and that all participants’ antibodies were able to neutralize at least 80% of the COVID-19 virus in vitro. The antibodies were as effective at neutralizing virus as those in convalescent plasma from patients who had recovered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AstraZeneca [2] in collaboration with researchers from Oxford University, has been testing a vaccine called ChAdOx1, and has released interim results from a Phase 1 / 2 study on 1077 healthy adults aged 18-55. This vaccine is an adenovirus vector expressing the spike protein of the COVID-19 virus.  The trial found that the antibody levels were higher in vaccinated subjects than controls, with a comparable magnitude of antibody response to convalescent plasma, and with the elevated response lasting throughout the 60-day trial. Of the 35 vaccinated patients tested for a neutralizing response, all were able to neutralized COVID-19, while none of the control patients were.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Chinese group [3] also tested a vaccine consisting of an adenovirus vector expressing a part of the COVID-19 virus’ spike protein, on 508 adults aged 18-60. The vaccinated subjects had significantly more antibody response and neutralizing ability than the placebo group. 96-97% of vaccinated subjects had antibodies against spike protein; 59% had neutralizing antibodies.  The vaccine also produced significantly more T-cell response than placebo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A German company, BioNTek, produced another vaccine candidate based on mRNA of a portion of the spike protein, this one attached to a “foldon” peptide to improve immunogenicity. In an un-peer-reviewed preprint [4] they report an uncontrolled trial on 60 healthy adults age 18-55. Their average antibody response to the virus was significantly higher and more effective at neutralizing COVID-19 than the antibodies in convalescent plasma.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two other biotech companies, Sinovac [5] and Inovio [6], have announced in press releases that their initial human vaccine trials had positive results; Sinovac claims 90% of its vaccinated subjects had neutralizing antibodies and Inovio claims 94% of its vaccinated subjects had an antibody response to the vaccine.  Neither company has released a paper or additional data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ok, so what does this mean?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking for antibody response is a pretty standard way to test vaccines.  The purpose of a vaccine is to stimulate the immune system to produce antibodies (and potentially other responses) to the virus, so that when you get the actual virus you’ll be able to produce the right antibodies faster, in greater quantities, and for a greater length of time. So, given that experimental ethics rules make it hard to actually &lt;em&gt;infect&lt;/em&gt; people with the virus and seeing if the vaccine protects them, researchers usually use antibody response as a proxy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do the vaccinated subjects &lt;em&gt;produce&lt;/em&gt; antibodies that actually bind to the viral antigen? How much do they produce?  And do those antibodies &lt;em&gt;neutralize&lt;/em&gt; the virus, i.e. prevent it from spreading in a petri dish full of cells?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like all proxy metrics, antibody response is not a perfect substitute for finding out what happens in a real world scenario – in this case, how well the vaccine will protect against infection.  But I think it’s a reasonable proxy to use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The base rates of vaccines that enter clinical trials ultimately getting approved by the FDA are actually not bad – quite a bit higher than the clinical success rates of other drugs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on a dataset of clinical trials between 2000 and 2015, [7] it turns out that vaccines for infectious diseases have an overall success rate of 33.7% from Phase I trials to approval; that is, once a vaccine _enters _ clinical trials, it has about a ⅓ chance of being found safe and effective enough to satisfy the FDA.  For all drugs and vaccines taken as a whole, that number is more like 1/20.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another study on a clinical trial database ranging from 1995 to 2017 [8] reached a similar conclusion: a vaccine for infectious disease that enters clinical trials has a 31% chance of ultimately reaching approval.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The riskiest stage in this process is going from phase 2 to phase 3, which is a 61% probability; Moderna has already passed that test, having begun its phase 3 trial, and now, on priors alone, it has an 80% chance of approval.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a more pessimistic number floating around, that says vaccine candidates have only a 6% chance of success, but I don’t think it’s applicable to the current COVID-19 situation.  The number comes from a study [9] that looks at the probability that a _preclinical _vaccine candidate will ultimately be approved – that means, candidates that have only been tested on animals so far, which are obviously riskier than candidates that showed positive enough results to start testing in humans.  Moreover, that study included vaccines for _noninfectious _diseases in that group, including cancer vaccines, which have a dismal track record.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we’re thinking about how hopeful to be about COVID-19 vaccine candidates, we shouldn’t be lumping them in with chronic disease “vaccines”, which don’t work the same way and aren’t nearly as effective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With as many vaccine candidates as are currently in the pipeline, I think chances are quite good that we’re going to see an approval somewhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other big question, though, which _isn’t _going to show up in the clinical success rates, is how well this vaccine is going to work on the elderly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;COVID-19 is deadlier the older you get. Also, because immune system function declines with age, vaccines are less effective the older you get. Flu vaccines are basically ineffective on the old. And you don’t need to prove that a vaccine is effective on the elderly to get it approved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both the Moderna and Oxford vaccine teams are enrolling older adults in trials, so we’ll actually find out how well they work soon enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[1] Jackson, Lisa A., et al. “An mRNA Vaccine against SARS-CoV-2—Preliminary Report.”  &lt;em&gt;New England Journal of Medicine&lt;/em&gt; (202)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[2]Folegatti, Pedro M. et al. “Safety and immunogenicity of the ChAdOx1 nCoV-19 vaccine against SARS-CoV-2: a preliminary report of a phase 1/2, single-blind, randomised controlled trial” &lt;em&gt;The Lancet&lt;/em&gt; (2020)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[3] Zhu, Feng-Cai, et al. “Safety, tolerability, and immunogenicity of a recombinant adenovirus type-5 vectored COVID-19 vaccine: a dose-escalation, open-label, non-randomised, first-in-human trial.” &lt;em&gt;The Lancet&lt;/em&gt; (2020).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[4]Sahin, Ugur, et al. “Concurrent human antibody and TH1 type T-cell responses elicited by a COVID-19 RNA vaccine.” &lt;em&gt;medRxiv,&lt;/em&gt; 2020&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[5] &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.clinicaltrialsarena.com/news/sinovac-coronavac-data/&quot;&gt;https://www.clinicaltrialsarena.com/news/sinovac-coronavac-data/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[6] &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.statnews.com/2020/06/30/inovio-claims-positive-results-on-covid-19-vaccine-but-critical-data-are-missing/&quot;&gt;https://www.statnews.com/2020/06/30/inovio-claims-positive-results-on-covid-19-vaccine-but-critical-data-are-missing/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[7]Wong, Chi Heem, Kien Wei Siah, and Andrew W. Lo. “Estimation of clinical trial success rates and related parameters.” &lt;em&gt;Biostatistics&lt;/em&gt; 20.2 (2019): 273-286.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[8]DiMasi, Joseph A., et al. “Development times and approval success rates for drugs to treat infectious diseases.” &lt;em&gt;Clinical Pharmacology &amp;amp; Therapeutics&lt;/em&gt; 107.2 (2020): 324-332&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[9]Pronker, Esther S., et al. “Risk in vaccine research and development quantified.” &lt;em&gt;PloS one&lt;/em&gt; 8.3 (2013): e57755.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="lit-review" /><category term="medicine" /><category term="covid-19" /><summary type="html">So far I’ve found 6 vaccine candidates that are reporting positive results from clinical trials.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Moving to New York</title><link href="https://srconstantin.github.io/2020/07/20/moving-to-new-york.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Moving to New York" /><published>2020-07-20T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-07-20T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://srconstantin.github.io/2020/07/20/moving-to-new-york</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://srconstantin.github.io/2020/07/20/moving-to-new-york.html">&lt;p&gt;Well, it’s official – I’m going to start a new position at the R&amp;amp;D department of &lt;a href=&quot;https://nanotronics.co/&quot;&gt;Nanotronics&lt;/a&gt;, a company that does automation and AI for manufacturing process control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m going to be researching new applications for their core technology, a system that uses machine learning to tune parameters along a manufacturing pipeline – or to guide a human worker – to optimize output and quality.  I’m really excited about the possibilities here.  I’ve known some of the Nanotronics people for a long time, and feel lucky to be working with such brilliant and high-integrity folks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new job is in Brooklyn, so that’s where my family &amp;amp; I are going, at the end of the month. I’d love to catch up with New York friends (and make new ones) – outside, of course!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Does this mean Daphnia Labs is dead?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, yes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To recap, I started a company about a year ago with the goal of building an automated platform for drug screening in invertebrates, with the goal of discovering new life-extending drugs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still think that research thesis should be done, but we weren’t able to make it work as a business. We may have been too early; a new model organism &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; a new technology platform &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; being in the relatively new and controversial field of longevity means we had some skepticism to overcome.  Not to mention we were hit with a global pandemic before we could really get sales off the ground.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m disappointed that I couldn’t figure out a way to make Daphnia Labs work, but I’m moving on and excited for what lies ahead.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="personal" /><summary type="html">Well, it’s official – I’m going to start a new position at the R&amp;amp;D department of Nanotronics, a company that does automation and AI for manufacturing process control.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Dose-Response Effects of Viral Exposure in COVID-19</title><link href="https://srconstantin.github.io/2020/06/02/Dose-Response.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dose-Response Effects of Viral Exposure in COVID-19" /><published>2020-06-02T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-06-02T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://srconstantin.github.io/2020/06/02/Dose-Response</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://srconstantin.github.io/2020/06/02/Dose-Response.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/virus-infection.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;virus&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Does being exposed to a small quantity of SARS-CoV-2 virus result in less severe disease than being exposed to a large quantity?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The answer is relevant to how we should respond to COVID-19.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If high dose exposures are worse than low-dose exposures, then:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We should consider people who spend a lot of time with infected people, like healthcare workers and family members of COVID-19 patients, to be more at risk than people who get briefly exposed to the virus
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Reopening lower-risk public spaces (like outdoor cafes or parks) may be low-risk compared to reopening spaces that involve a lot of close contact (like gyms and nightclubs)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;We should prioritize PPE even &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; for people who regularly interact with COVID-19 patients&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Low dose exposure to SARS-CoV-2 may produce immunity without producing serious illness.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;If low dose exposure is safe and produces immunity, it may be good for people and available faster than a vaccine can be manufactured and approved.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bottom Lines&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People who have higher respiratory &lt;em&gt;viral loads&lt;/em&gt; are significantly more likely to have severe COVID-19; the same pattern held in both the SARS and MERS coronavirus epidemics.  More virus in the body does tend to correspond to more severe disease.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s far less data about how different forms of &lt;em&gt;exposure&lt;/em&gt; correlate to disease severity, but there are a few studies pointing towards a greater chance of severe COVID-19 from household contacts than from travel, and one study indicates that mask usage increases the probability that a SARS case will be asymptomatic.  These constitute weak evidence that larger doses of exposure to human coronaviruses cause more severe disease.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When human volunteers are experimentally exposed to viruses, some viruses cause more severe symptoms at higher doses, while some viruses don’t.  None of the relevant studies were on coronaviruses, however.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;em&gt;animal&lt;/em&gt; experimental exposures to virus, higher doses consistently cause more severe symptoms, including in experiments on the coronaviruses SARS, MERS, and PEDV.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The available evidence is highly incomplete, but tends towards the conclusion that lower dose exposure to COVID-19 should result in less severe disease.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Viral Load in COVID-19&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a table of studies that compared viral load in mild and severe COVID-19 patients.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt;
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mean Viral Load, Mild&lt;/strong&gt;
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mean Viral Load, Severe&lt;/strong&gt;
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Significance&lt;/strong&gt;
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Location of Sample&lt;/strong&gt;
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Context&lt;/strong&gt;
   &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;15
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Ct = 25 (n = 6, range 17-32)
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Ct = 27 (n = 9, range 19-33)
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;n.s. 
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Nasopharyngeal swab
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Private hospital, Mumbai, India[1]
   &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;92
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Ct = 28 (n = 62, sigma = 0.5)
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Ct = 25 (n = 30, sigma = 0.5)
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;p = 0.017
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Sputum
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Zhejiang, China; severe patients older &amp;amp; with more comorbidities but not different exposure histories. [2]
   &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;96
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;4.1 log copies/mL (n = 22, sigma = 1.4 )
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;5.1 log copies/mL (n = 74, sigma = 1.4)
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;p = 0.03
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Sputum (no difference between mild &amp;amp; severe pts  in serum or stool)
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Zhejiang, China; severe patients more likely to be from Wuhan[3]
   &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;76
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;delta-CT = -1.25 (n = 30, sigma = 5.2)
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;delta-CT = 4.48(n = 46, sigma = 3.0)
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;p &amp;lt; 0.001
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;nasopharyngeal
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Nanchang, China; median time from disease onset = 4 days[4]
   &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;23
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;5 log copies/mL (n = 10, sigma = 2.2)
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;6 log copies/mL (n = 13, sigma = 3.0)
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;n.s. 
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;oropharyngeal
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Hong Kong[5]; mild &amp;amp; severe patients had similar duration of illness at admission, age, sex, &amp;amp; comorbidities
   &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;12
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Ct = 35.2 (n = 10, sigma = 5)
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Ct = 26 (n = 3, sigma = 5.1)
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;p = 0.0177
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;nasal
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Guangdong, China [6]
   &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;18
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Ct = 30.9(n = 12, sigma = 5.6)
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Ct = 30.3 (n = 6, sigma = 5.3)
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;n.s. 
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;nasopharyngeal
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Singapore[7]
   &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;6
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Ct = 39 (n = 2, sigma = 1.2)
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Ct = 39 (n = 4, sigma = 1.1)
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;n.s.
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;nasopharyngeal
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Chongqing, China; all patients had previously recovered from COVID-19 and had reoccurence of disease.[8]
   &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;94
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Ct=30 (n = 76, sigma = 5) 
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Ct = 30 (n = 18, sigma = 4)
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;n.s
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Throat swabs
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Guangzhou, China [9]
   &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;11
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;6.39 log copies/mL (n = 5, sigma = 0.9)
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;6.15 log copies/mL (n = 6, sigma = 1.6)
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;n.s.
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;nasopharyngeal
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Hong Kong [10]; first 11 patients diagnosed with COVID-19
   &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;5
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;6.3 log copies/ 1000 cells (n = 2, sigma = 1.25)
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;5.3 log copies/1000 cells (n = 3, sigma = 2.4)
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;n.s.
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;nasopharyngeal
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;France [11]; patients traveling from Wuhan
   &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do severe COVID-19 patients have higher viral loads than mild patients?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a flawed proxy for the question of initial exposure, since patients are usually not tested for COVID-19 until at least several days after infection. Higher viral load could indicate that the virus replicated faster inside the body, or simply that the patients were later in their course of disease, rather than that the initial exposure was lower.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still, the correlation between viral load and disease severity is suggestive as to whether there’s a dose-response effect in COVID-19.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Viral load can be measured with Ct, the number of PCR amplification cycles necessary before viral RNA is detectable. Lower Ct numbers mean exponentially more virus.  It can also be measured by delta-Ct, the difference between the number of cycles to detection in a control sample (without virus) and the test sample.  Finally, it can be measured by the absolute concentration of viral particles per mL.  These numbers cannot be directly compared because the sensitivity of RT-PCR equipment varies and isn’t always given in the papers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For all studies measured in Ct value, mean Ct score is 29.6 for mild cases and 26.1 for severe cases; this is a significant effect, p = 0.0004.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the 4 studies measured in absolute concentration, mean concentration was 4.7 log copies/mL for mild cases and 5.3 log copies/mL for severe cases, which was not statistically significant, possibly because the sample size was too small.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also note that the two studies which looked at sputum samples both found significant effects, and sputum samples reliably contain more virus RNA than nasopharyngeal samples.  This suggests that viral load in the lungs is more predictive of the amount of lung damage &amp;amp; thus the severity of respiratory illness than viral load in the upper respiratory tract.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Severe COVID-19 patients have significantly higher initial viral loads than mild COVID-19 patients.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Exposure Effects in COVID-19&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another question we might ask is whether people with extensive exposure to the virus had more severe illness than people with transient or low-dose exposure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a study of 36 children with COVID-19, there was no significant difference in disease severity between those who had close contact with a family member with COVID-19 and those who had traveled to an area affected by COVID-19.[12]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1663 patients with COVID-19 in Wuhan, China, there was no significant difference in severity between those who did and did not have a family member with the disease or exposure to the Wuhan seafood market, but were significantly (p&amp;lt;0.0001) less likely to have severe disease if they were healthcare workers compared to the general population.  On the other hand this may be because healthcare workers are younger (most of the patients were retirees.)[13]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 568 COVID-19 patients in Wuhan, China, there was a nonsignificant trend (p = 0.06) for severe cases to be more likely to have had household exposure to the virus, while non-severe cases were more likely to have had hospital exposure to the virus.[14]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In another study of 487 patients with COVID-19 in Zhejiang Province, China, patients with severe disease were significantly less likely to have traveled to an affected area (49.0% vs. 65.1%, p = 0.027) but significantly more likely to be part of a family cluster of three or more patients (10.2% vs. 2.5%).[15]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall it doesn’t seem that the relationship between disease severity and magnitude of exposure to infected people has been much studied in COVID-19.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However we do have two Chinese studies indicating that severe cases of COVID-19 are more common in those who had frequent long-term exposure to other patients (i.e. sharing a household with many other patients) and less likely in those who have had transient contact with patients (as in travel to an epidemic-affected province.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Viral Load in Other Human Coronaviruses&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;SARS&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 75 SARS patients, there was no difference in the rate of positive viral RNA samples at diagnosis between patients who later developed ARDS and those who did not.[16]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 133 SARS patients, initial viral load was significantly (p = 0.025) associated with developing ARDS, and with shorter survival time (p = 0.006).[17]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 12 SARS patients, viral RNA levels were 30x higher in patients who required ICU admission than in those who didn’t (p &amp;lt; 0.005).[18]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 154 SARS patients, viral load in nasopharyngeal aspirated was associated (p &amp;lt; 0.01) with diarrhea, oxygen desaturation, mechanical ventilation, and death. Death was 54x as likely in patients positive for viral RNA than negative. [19]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;MERS&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 17 MERS patients, viral load was nonsignificantly (p = 0.06) higher in severe than mild cases.[20]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 21 MERS patients, blood positivity for MERS RNA was associated with much lower survival (p = 0.017) and higher rates of needing mechanical ventilation (p = 0.003).  Higher respiratory viral load was not associated with survival.[21]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 14 MERS patients, viral load was not significantly associated with mortality but plasma and respiratory viral loads were significantly higher in severe than mild cases.[22]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 102 MERS patients, respiratory viral titers were significantly (p = 0.0087) higher in patients who died than patients who survived.[23]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The evidence seems very consistent that_ higher viral load correlates with more severe and deadly disease_ in both SARS and MERS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Exposure Effects in Other Human Coronaviruses&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Among 80 health care workers in Singapore exposed to SARS, 45 were serologically positive for the virus. Of those 45, healthcare workers were significantly more likely to be asymptomatic (p = 0.025) if they used masks.[24]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the SARS epidemic in Hong Kong, there was no significant association between the risk of death and any disease source (household, hospital, community-acquired, airplane, or none of the above.)[25]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1649 SARS patients in Beijing, contact with a SARS patient prior to illness was not a significant predictor of mortality.[26]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Healthcare workers with confirmed MERS infection were younger, more likely to be female, and less likely to have comorbidities disease than other cases of MERS. They also had significantly (p &amp;lt; 0.001) lower risk of death and higher chance of being asymptomatic.[27]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MERS patients have a higher risk of mortality (HR = 2.9, p= 0.001) from hospital-acquired infections as opposed to other routes of infection such as household contacts or camels; even after adjusting for age and comorbidities.[28]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Healthcare workers may be exposed to larger doses of SARS or MERS, but it doesn’t show up in increased risk of death or severe disease for healthcare workers, possibly because healthcare workers tend to be younger than other patients.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hospital-acquired MERS infections are more deadly than other sources of infection, but this may be confounded by the fact that patients who are already in hospitals for other reasons tend to be sicker.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The one piece of evidence from SARS and MERS that points to low-dose exposure being safer is that wearing masks is more likely to result in asymptomatic SARS infection than not wearing masks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dose-Response Effects in Other Viruses: Human Studies&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Humans have been experimentally exposed to viruses (usually with milder effects than SARS or MERS) in a few challenge trials; this can help us ascertain whether there’s a dose-response effect to the quantity of initial viral exposure on the severity of the disease symptoms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Adenovirus Type 4&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 16 military recruits, the probability of infection varied with the dose of adenovirus they were exposed to, but the probability of illness did not.[29]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Echovirus&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 127 adult volunteers inoculated with various doses of ECHO-11 virus, there was a dose-response relationship with infectivity, but dose had no effect on the severity of upper respiratory symptoms in the infected group.  On the other hand, high-dose cases were significantly more likely than low-dose cases to have lower respiratory symptoms (cough, sore throat, laryngitis).  Prior challenge reduced symptoms upon rechallenge, and more for the high-dose-prior-exposed than the low-dose-prior-exposed group.[30]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Influenza&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Across 36 studies with different doses and strains, there was no association of higher doses of influenza with higher chance of the subjects becoming ill.[31]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Norovirus&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a study of 57 adults infected with different doses of Norwalk virus, higher doses were associated with significantly (p =0.001) faster time before symptom onset and longer (p = 0.04) duration of illness, as well as a dose-response relationship in probability of infection.[32]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Respiratory Synctial Virus&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 35 adult volunteers, there was no association between the dose of RSV administered and the viral load or the probability of infection.  Symptom severity, however, as well as cytokine levels, correlated closely with viral load, both across patients and within patients over time.[33]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Volunteers infected with low-dose RSV did not develop illness (0/16), while volunteers infected with high-dose RSV did develop colds (6/17). Illness was independent of the amount of viral shedding.[34]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 36 volunteers infected with high or low dose RSV, higher doses were associated with higher risk of infection but not higher risk of symptomatic illness.[35]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Rhinovirus&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 155 young adult volunteers infected with different doses of rhinovirus, daily symptom scores were consistently higher in those exposed to higher doses.  Higher antibody titers and higher doses of virus were associated with higher rates of infection.[36]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Rotavirus&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a study of 62 adult volunteers experimentally infected with different doses of rotavirus, there was a dose-response relationship between the concentration of virus and the probability of infection, but there was no relationship between the virus dose and the probability of experiencing symptoms.[37]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whether higher initial doses of virus correlate with more severe symptoms or higher probability of having symptoms at all, seems to depend on the virus.  There is no relationship between dose and symptom severity in human volunteers exposed to adenovirus, influenza, and rotavirus, but there is a relationship in echovirus, rhinovirus, and norovirus, and the results are ambiguous in respiratory synctial virus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It remains unclear how well any of these observations translate to COVID-19.  Unfortunately there were no studies comparing the effect of dose on the symptoms of any of the mild human coronaviruses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dose-Response Effects in Other Viruses: Animal Studies&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ebola&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Exposure to 100 plaque-forming units of Ebola virus in the nose was lethal to macaques; but exposure to 10 plaque-forming units caused no clinical symptoms or detectable antibodies or viral RNA.[38]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;EEV&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eastern Equine Encephalitis Virus is lethal in high doses in macaques (6/6 animals died) but less severe in low-dose exposure (2/6 animals died and clinical scores were lower). [39]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Herpes&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Serial dilutions of the baboon herpesvirus HPV2 inoculated into mice showed a dose-response curve with higher doses resulting in higher rates of infection, CNS symptoms, and death.[40]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Influenza&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was a dose-response relationship between initial inoculation dose, probability of infection, and probability of death, in H5N1 and H7N1 influenza  in turkeys, chickens, and ducks.[41]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Probability of infection, probability of clinical signs, and survival time all varied dose-dependently by the inoculation dose of H5N1 in pigeons.[42]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A H0N1 strain of influenza in mice had a dose-response relationship for both infectiousness and mortality; it was more deadly when introduced to the respiratory tract than intranasally.[43]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A PR8 strain of influenza has a dose-response relationship with serum viral load, weight loss, clinical score, and mortality. The low dose and high dose groups had similar antibody and leukocyte recruitment levels as the high dose, but no mortality. [44]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;MERS&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In transgenic mice, there was a dose-response effect in lethality for exposure to MERS virus: it killed 50% of the mice at a dose of 10 TCID50, compared to 25% at 1.25 TCID50 and 100% at 100 TCID50.[45]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;PEDV&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PEDV is a coronavirus that causes diarrhea in pigs. It has a dose-response relationship to symptoms: 0.056 TCID50 caused diarrhea in 25% of piglets while 0.56 TCID50 and higher caused diarrhea in 100% of piglets.[46]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;SARS&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both mice and guinea pigs exposed to SARS virus had a higher probability of increased rectal temperature at higher doses of virus exposure.  For guinea pigs, ID50 = 5.47 log CPE50, or 50% of guinea pigs were infected at 5.47 * log (the dose at which 50% of cells died).[47]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;SIV&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simian immunodeficiency virus, closely related to HIV, had a dose-response relationship with the probability of infection in macaque monkeys, but steady-state (2-week) viral load among those infected did not correlate with initial dose.  There was no correlation between survival time and dose.[48]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Low-dose challenge with SIV successfully produced “silent infection” (no symptoms or viral RNA but virus-specific T cell proliferation.) However, when these monkeys were exposed to a high dose of SIV, they were not immune but became infected and developed AIDS-like disease at the same rate as naive monkeys.[49]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dose-response relationships between virus inoculum and infection rate or death seem to be common in animal studies, and consistently, including in coronaviruses, higher doses cause more severe symptoms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, in at least one case (SIV) a dose of virus that was low enough to produce asymptomatic infection did &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; produce immunity to future exposures, so we can’t assume that low-dose exposure always brings immunity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[1]Shah, Sweta, et al. “Initial Observations with Molecular Testing for COVID-19 in a Private Hospital in Mumbai, India.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[2]Yu, Xia, et al. “SARS-CoV-2 viral load in sputum correlates with risk of COVID-19 progression.” &lt;em&gt;Critical Care&lt;/em&gt; 24.1 (2020): 1-4.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[3]Zheng, Shufa, et al. “Viral load dynamics and disease severity in patients infected with SARS-CoV-2 in Zhejiang province, China, January-March 2020: retrospective cohort study.” &lt;em&gt;bmj&lt;/em&gt; 369 (2020).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[4]Liu, Yang, et al. “Correlation Between Relative Nasopharyngeal Virus RNA Load and Lymphocyte Count Disease Severity in Patients with COVID-19.” &lt;em&gt;Viral Immunology&lt;/em&gt; (2020).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[5]To, Kelvin Kai-Wang, et al. “Temporal profiles of viral load in posterior oropharyngeal saliva samples and serum antibody responses during infection by SARS-CoV-2: an observational cohort study.” &lt;em&gt;The Lancet Infectious Diseases&lt;/em&gt; (2020).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[6]Zou, Lirong, et al. “SARS-CoV-2 viral load in upper respiratory specimens of infected patients.” &lt;em&gt;New England Journal of Medicine&lt;/em&gt; 382.12 (2020): 1177-1179.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[7]Young, Barnaby Edward, et al. “Epidemiologic features and clinical course of patients infected with SARS-CoV-2 in Singapore.” &lt;em&gt;Jama&lt;/em&gt; 323.15 (2020): 1488-1494.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[8]Wu, Jing, et al. “Clinical Characteristics and Outcomes of Discharged COVID-19 Patients with Reoccurrence of SARS-CoV-2 RNA in a County Hospital of Western Chongqing, China.” &lt;em&gt;China (4/14/2020)&lt;/em&gt; (2020).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[9]He, Xi, et al. “Temporal dynamics in viral shedding and transmissibility of COVID-19.” &lt;em&gt;Nature medicine&lt;/em&gt; (2020): 1-4.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[10]Lui, Grace, et al. “Viral dynamics of SARS-CoV-2 across a spectrum of disease severity in COVID-19.” &lt;em&gt;The Journal of Infection&lt;/em&gt; (2020).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[11]Lescure, Francois-Xavier, et al. “Clinical and virological data of the first cases of COVID-19 in Europe: a case series.” &lt;em&gt;The Lancet Infectious Diseases&lt;/em&gt; (2020).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[12]Qiu, Haiyan, et al. “Clinical and epidemiological features of 36 children with coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) in Zhejiang, China: an observational cohort study.” &lt;em&gt;The Lancet Infectious Diseases&lt;/em&gt; (2020).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[13]Xu, Xiao-Wei, et al. “Clinical findings in a group of patients infected with the 2019 novel coronavirus (SARS-Cov-2) outside of Wuhan, China: retrospective case series.” &lt;em&gt;bmj&lt;/em&gt; 368 (2020).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[14]Li, Xiaochen, et al. “Risk factors for severity and mortality in adult COVID-19 inpatients in Wuhan.” &lt;em&gt;Journal of Allergy and Clinical Immunology&lt;/em&gt; (2020).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[15]Shi, Y., et al. “Host susceptibility to severe COVID-19: a retrospective analysis of 487 case outside Wuhan.” (2020).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[16]Peiris, Joseph Sriyal Malik, et al. “Clinical progression and viral load in a community outbreak of coronavirus-associated SARS pneumonia: a prospective study.” &lt;em&gt;The Lancet&lt;/em&gt; 361.9371 (2003): 1767-1772.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[17]Chu, Chung-Ming, et al. “Initial viral load and the outcomes of SARS.” &lt;em&gt;Cmaj&lt;/em&gt; 171.11 (2004): 1349-1352.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[18] Ng, Enders KO, et al. “Quantitative analysis and prognostic implication of SARS coronavirus RNA in the plasma and serum of patients with severe acute respiratory syndrome.” &lt;em&gt;Clinical chemistry&lt;/em&gt; 49.12 (2003): 1976-1980.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[19]Hung, I. F. N., et al. “Viral loads in clinical specimens and SARS manifestations.” Emerging infectious diseases 10.9 (2004): 1550.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[20]Oh, Myoung-don, et al. “Viral load kinetics of MERS coronavirus infection.” &lt;em&gt;New England Journal of Medicine&lt;/em&gt; 375.13 (2016): 1303-1305.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[21]Kim, So Yeon, et al. “Viral RNA in blood as indicator of severe outcome in Middle East respiratory syndrome coronavirus infection.” &lt;em&gt;Emerging infectious diseases&lt;/em&gt; 22.10 (2016): 1813.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[22]Min, Chan-Ki, et al. “Comparative and kinetic analysis of viral shedding and immunological responses in MERS patients representing a broad spectrum of disease severity.” Scientific reports 6.1 (2016): 1-12.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[23] Feikin, Daniel R., et al. “Association of higher MERS-CoV virus load with severe disease and death, Saudi Arabia, 2014.” Emerging infectious diseases 21.11 (2015): 2029.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;APA&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[24] Wilder-Smith, Annelies, et al. “Asymptomatic SARS coronavirus infection among healthcare workers, Singapore.” Emerging infectious diseases 11.7 (2005): 1142.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[25]Leung, Gabriel M., et al. “The epidemiology of severe acute respiratory syndrome in the 2003 Hong Kong epidemic: an analysis of all 1755 patients.” Annals of internal medicine 141.9 (2004): 662-673.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[26]Liu, Min, et al. “Risk factors for SARS-related deaths in 2003, Beijing.” Biomedical and Environmental Sciences 19.5 (2006): 336.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[27]Elkholy, Amgad A., et al. “MERS-CoV infection among healthcare workers and risk factors for death: Retrospective analysis of all laboratory-confirmed cases reported to WHO from 2012 to 2 June 2018.” Journal of infection and public health (2019).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[28]Ahmed, Anwar E. “The predictors of 3-and 30-day mortality in 660 MERS-CoV patients.” BMC infectious diseases 17.1 (2017): 615.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[29]Couch, R. B., et al. “The minimal infectious dose of adenovirus type 4; the case for natural transmission by viral aerosol.” &lt;em&gt;Transactions of the American Clinical and Climatological Association&lt;/em&gt; 80 (1969): 205.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[30]Saliba, Gilbert S., Sylvia L. Franklin, and George Gee Jackson. “ECHO-11 as a respiratory virus: quantitation of infection in man.” &lt;em&gt;The Journal of clinical investigation&lt;/em&gt; 47.6 (1968): 1303-1313.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[31]Yezli, Saber, and Jonathan A. Otter. “Minimum infective dose of the major human respiratory and enteric viruses transmitted through food and the environment.” &lt;em&gt;Food and Environmental Virology&lt;/em&gt; 3.1 (2011): 1-30.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[32]Atmar, Robert L., et al. “Determination of the 50% human infectious dose for Norwalk virus.” &lt;em&gt;The Journal of infectious diseases&lt;/em&gt; 209.7 (2014): 1016-1022.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[33]DeVincenzo, John P., et al. “Viral load drives disease in humans experimentally infected with respiratory syncytial virus.” &lt;em&gt;American journal of respiratory and critical care medicine&lt;/em&gt; 182.10 (2010): 1305-1314.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[34]Mills, John, et al. “Experimental respiratory syncytial virus infection of adults: possible mechanisms of resistance to infection and illness.” &lt;em&gt;The Journal of Immunology&lt;/em&gt; 107.1 (1971): 123-130.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[35]Lee, F. Eun-Hyung, et al. “Experimental infection of humans with A2 respiratory syncytial virus.” &lt;em&gt;Antiviral research&lt;/em&gt; 63.3 (2004): 191-196.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[36]Hendley, J. Owen, William P. Edmondson Jr, and Jack M. Gwaltney Jr. “Relation between naturally acquired immunity and infectivity of two rhinoviruses in volunteers.” &lt;em&gt;Journal of Infectious Diseases&lt;/em&gt; 125.3 (1972): 243-248.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[37]Ward, Richard L., et al. “Human rotavirus studies in volunteers: determination of infectious dose and serological response to infection.” &lt;em&gt;Journal of Infectious Diseases&lt;/em&gt; 154.5 (1986): 871-880.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[38]Mire, Chad E., et al. “Oral and conjunctival exposure of nonhuman primates to low doses of Ebola Makona virus.” The Journal of infectious diseases 214.suppl_3 (2016): S263-S267.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[39]Reed, Douglas S., et al. “Severe encephalitis in cynomolgus macaques exposed to aerosolized eastern equine encephalitis virus.” The Journal of infectious diseases 196.3 (2007): 441-450.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[40]Ritchey, J. W., et al. “Comparative pathology of infections with baboon and African green monkey α-herpesviruses in mice.” &lt;em&gt;Journal of comparative pathology&lt;/em&gt; 127.2-3 (2002): 150-161.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[41]Aldous, E. W., et al. “Infection dynamics of highly pathogenic avian influenza and virulent avian paramyxovirus type 1 viruses in chickens, turkeys and ducks.” &lt;em&gt;Avian Pathology&lt;/em&gt; 39.4 (2010): 265-273.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[42] Phonaknguen, Rassameepen, et al. “Minimal susceptibility to highly pathogenic avian influenza H5N1 viral infection of pigeons (Columba livia) and potential transmission of the virus to comingled domestic chickens.” &lt;em&gt;Kasetsart J-Nat Sci&lt;/em&gt; 47 (2013): 720-732.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[43]Yetter, Robert A., et al. “Outcome of influenza infection: effect of site of initial infection and heterotypic immunity.” &lt;em&gt;Infection and immunity&lt;/em&gt; 29.2 (1980): 654-662.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[44]Powell, Timothy J., et al. “The immune system provides a strong response to even a low exposure to virus.” Clinical immunology 119.1 (2006): 87-94&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[45]Tao, Xinrong, et al. “Characterization and demonstration of the value of a lethal mouse model of Middle East respiratory syndrome coronavirus infection and disease.” &lt;em&gt;Journal of virology&lt;/em&gt; 90.1 (2016): 57-67.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[46]Neumann, Eric J., and William F. Hall. “Disease Control, Prevention, and Elimination.” &lt;em&gt;Diseases of Swine&lt;/em&gt; (2019): 123-157.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[47]Chepurnov, A. A., A. A. Dadaeva, and E. M. Malkova. “Symptoms of infection caused by SARS coronavirus in laboratory mice and guinea pigs.” &lt;em&gt;Doklady Biological Sciences&lt;/em&gt;. Vol. 397. No. 1. Nature Publishing Group, 2004.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[48]Holterman, Lennart, et al. “The rate of progression to AIDS is independent of virus dose in simian immunodeficiency virus-infected macaques.” &lt;em&gt;Journal of General Virology&lt;/em&gt; 81.7 (2000): 1719-1726&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[49]Dittmer, Ulf, et al. “Repeated exposure of rhesus macaques to low doses of simian immunodeficiency virus (SIV) did not protect them against the consequences of a high-dose SIV challenge.” Journal of general virology 76.6 (1995): 1307-1315.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="covid-19" /><category term="lit-review" /><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Avoiding Intubation in COVID-19 Silent Hypoxemia</title><link href="https://srconstantin.github.io/2020/05/04/silent-hypoxemia.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Avoiding Intubation in COVID-19 Silent Hypoxemia" /><published>2020-05-04T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-05-04T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://srconstantin.github.io/2020/05/04/silent-hypoxemia</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://srconstantin.github.io/2020/05/04/silent-hypoxemia.html">&lt;p&gt;One predictable feature of a novel disease is that initial guidelines for treatment may need to be revised, as medical understanding of the disease evolves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Initially, patients with COVID-19 experiencing severe respiratory distress were supposed to be intubated and placed on ventilators early, and non-invasive ventilation procedures like CPAP, BiPAP, and high-flow nasal cannula were to be avoided because they might spread the disease.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the course of the pandemic, we’ve seen additional evidence that a population of COVID-19 patients can be treated effectively with CPAP/BiPAP, and may not even need to be invasively ventilated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These patients are what’s informally called the “silent hypoxemic” – they have very low oxygen levels, but are otherwise surprisingly functional (they can talk, have minimal altered mental status, etc) and they do _not _have the noncompliant lungs typical of ARDS. Therefore, following typical ventilation procedures like ARDSNet, in which patients are intubated when their oxygen saturation drops below a certain point, and placed on mechanical ventilation with high pressures, is actually a _bad _idea.  Excessive PEEP for compliant lungs can cause barotrauma; and intubation in general carries risks (of e.g. hospital-acquired infections, damage to the airway, and PTSD) so if a patient can recover with _non-invasive _respiratory support, it’s safer to avoid intubation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This clinical picture was once purely anecdotal, but the data is starting to come in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Helmet CPAP, in which a continuous positive pressure of oxygenated air is administered through a clear helmet that covers the patient’s whole head, has been extensively used for COVID-19 patients in Italy. The helmet is more comfortable than traditional CPAP masks, and has a tighter seal, to avoid spreading virus particles to healthcare workers.  The RICU of the L. Sacco University hospital in Milan had 75% of their severe COVID-19 patients on helmet CPAP, and had an in-hospital mortality rate of only 25%, compared to Seattle ICUs, which had a 50% in-hospital mortality rate and had 100% of patients on invasive mechanical ventilation.[1]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Helmet CPAP is much less likely to disperse exhaled air than conventional CPAP, making the risks of infection to healthcare workers lower; a study found that air only dispersed 2.5 cm from the helmet.[6]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Italian intensive care physicians observed that 50% of the 150 severe COVID-19 patients in their ICU were the “silent hypoxemia” type, characterized by “severe hypoxemia often associated with near normal respiratory symptom compliance.”  They describe COVID-19 pneumonia as belonging to two separate “phenotypes”, Type L and Type H.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Type L COVID-19 has low elastance (= normally compliant lungs), low lung recruitability (most lung tissue is receiving air), but extreme hypoxemia due to ventilation-perfusion mismatch.  That is, the lung is receiving oxygen but not blood flow, so the blood doesn’t get properly oxygenated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These Type L patients may improve or suddenly worsen. Increased inflammation and negative intrathoracic pressure can cause swelling and fluid buildup in the lungs.  (High inspiratory pressures literally suck fluid from capillaries into lung tissue, which contributes to pulmonary edema.)  Increased edema transitions the patient to the Type H phenotype: high elastance (= noncompliant lungs), high recruitability (= lots of non-aerated lung tissue), and atelectasis (= collapsed alveoli).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This clinical picture implies that Type L patients should be treated noninvasively with high concentrations of oxygen (through masks or, in dyspneic patients, high-flow nasal cannula, CPAP, or BiPAP).  Patients at risk of transitioning to type H, as measured by high inspiratory pressures, should be intubated, and type H patients should be placed on standard invasive ventilation for severe ARDS.[2]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A case report from Norway illustrates a typical case of “silent hypoxemia” in COVID-19: a man in his sixties with an O2 saturation of 66% who nevertheless seemed calm, was “smiling bravely”, and breathing almost silently.  Hypocapnia (low CO2) meant there was little or no sensation of breathlessness despite the extremely low oxygen saturation.[5]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Three ICU doctors at the University College London hospital argued in the _Lancet Respiratory Medicine _against early intubation for COVID-19, saying&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Early intubation of a patient with known or suspected COVID-19 with respiratory distress could result in the intubation and mechanical ventilation of patients who would have otherwise improved on CPAP or NIV”.[3]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They note that the highest incidence of disease transmission to healthcare workers was on general wards, not ICU, i.e. where healthcare staff were least likely to wear personal protective equipment, and that NIV did not increase the risk of disease transmission during the SARS epidemic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, a statement by tropical disease experts about treating COVID-19 in low-resource areas argues&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It seems that in a significant proportion of relatively younger patients, hypoxemia, even less than 88%, is reasonably well tolerated and not accompanied by severe respiratory distress or exhaustion. With the current experience, the trigger for intubation should, within certain limits, probably not be based on hypoxemia alone but more on respiratory distress and fatigue….Invasive ventilation can save lives in patients with severe respiratory distress. However, it can also aggravate or even cause damage,including barotrauma (air leaks, caused by high ventilation pressures), volutrauma (pulmonary edema, due to large tidal volumes), atelectrauma (repetitive opening and closing of vulnerable lung parts with atelectasis), biotrauma (local inflammation with spill to the systemic circulation of inflammatory mediators, bacteria, or bacterial products), and oxytrauma (by free oxygen radicals).”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The authors recommend, when COVID-19 patients are intubated, using lower PEEP and lower tidal volume than would be typical for ARDS, to avoid ventilator-induced injury.[4]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Early awake self-proning in COVID-19 patients can be very beneficial for the “silent hypoxemic” or “type L” patient population. One emergency department in New York City found that in 50 patients, the median SpO2 was 80% at triage, 84% after supplemental oxygen, and 94% after patients were encouraged to lie on their stomachs (in the prone position.)  [7]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“In New York City, during the early stages of the COVID-19 pandemic, patients presented en masse with moderate to severe hypoxia. Some of these patients were distressed, quickly deteriorated and required endotracheal intubation.  COVID-19 produced another group of patients whose pathophysiology confounded existing disease patterns, however. These patients had low oxygen saturations (SpO2 &amp;lt;90%), but were not in significant respiratory distress and often appeared clinically well; this group has been informally referred to as happy hypoxemics.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the authors of the above article, Richard Levitan, an emergency physician in New York City, wrote a New York Times op-ed [8] about this phenomenon.  They were seeing COVID-19 pneumonia in nearly every patient who came into the emergency department, even those without respiratory symptoms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The patient stabbed in the shoulder, whom we X-rayed because we worried he had a collapsed lung, actually had Covid pneumonia. In patients on whom we did CT scans because they were injured in falls, we coincidentally found Covid pneumonia. Elderly patients who had passed out for unknown reasons and a number of diabetic patients were found to have it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“And here is what really surprised us: These patients did not report any sensation of breathing problems, even though their chest X-rays showed diffuse pneumonia and their oxygen was below normal. How could this be?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Patients compensate for the low oxygen in their blood by breathing faster and deeper — and this happens without their realizing it. This silent hypoxia, and the patient’s physiological response to it, causes even more inflammation and more air sacs to collapse, and the pneumonia worsens until oxygen levels plummet. In effect, patients are injuring their own lungs by breathing harder and harder. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.esicm.org/wp-content/uploads/2020/04/684_author-proof.pdf&quot;&gt;Twenty percent&lt;/a&gt; of Covid pneumonia patients then go on to a second and deadlier phase of lung injury. Fluid builds up and the lungs become stiff, carbon dioxide rises, and patients develop acute respiratory failure.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr. Levitan recommends that healthy people, and people who test positive for COVID-19, get pulse oximeters – available over at the counter at the drugstore – to monitor their oxygen levels _before _they get sick enough to need a hospital.  Silent hypoxemia doesn’t come with symptoms, so most infected patients don’t get supplemental oxygen until they’ve progressed to severe lung injury that requires ventilation.  If they caught the problem earlier, they could get supplemental oxygen and recover without ever needing to be ventilated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[1]Radovanovic, Dejan, et al. “Helmet CPAP to Treat Acute Hypoxemic Respiratory Failure in Patients with Covid-19: A Management Strategy Proposal.” &lt;em&gt;Journal of Clinical Medicine&lt;/em&gt; 9.4 (2020): 1191.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[2]Gattinoni, Luciano, et al. “COVID-19 pneumonia: different respiratory treatments for different phenotypes?.” &lt;em&gt;Intensive care medicine&lt;/em&gt; (2020): 1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[3]Arulkumaran, Nishkantha, et al. “Use of non-invasive ventilation for patients with COVID-19: a cause for concern?.” &lt;em&gt;The Lancet. Respiratory Medicine&lt;/em&gt; (2020).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[4]Dondorp, Arjen M., et al. “Respiratory Support in Novel Coronavirus Disease (COVID-19) Patients, with a Focus on Resource-Limited Settings.” &lt;em&gt;The American Journal of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene&lt;/em&gt; (2020): tpmd200283.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[5]Ottestad, William, Mari Seim, and Jens Otto Mæhlen. “COVID-19 with silent hypoxemia.” &lt;em&gt;Tidsskrift for Den norske legeforening&lt;/em&gt; (2020).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[6]Whittle, Jessica S., et al. “Respiratory Support for Adult Patients with COVID‐19.” &lt;em&gt;Journal of the American College of Emergency Physicians Open&lt;/em&gt; (2020).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[7]Caputo, Nicholas D., Reuben J. Strayer, and Richard Levitan. “Early Self‐Proning in Awake, Non‐intubated Patients in the Emergency Department: A Single ED’s Experience during the COVID‐19 Pandemic.” &lt;em&gt;Academic Emergency Medicine&lt;/em&gt; (2020).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[8]&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2020/04/20/opinion/sunday/coronavirus-testing-pneumonia.html&quot;&gt;https://www.nytimes.com/2020/04/20/opinion/sunday/coronavirus-testing-pneumonia.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="covid-19" /><category term="lit-review" /><summary type="html">One predictable feature of a novel disease is that initial guidelines for treatment may need to be revised, as medical understanding of the disease evolves.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Antibody Testing for COVID-19</title><link href="https://srconstantin.github.io/2020/04/27/antibody-testing.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Antibody Testing for COVID-19" /><published>2020-04-27T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-04-27T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://srconstantin.github.io/2020/04/27/antibody-testing</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://srconstantin.github.io/2020/04/27/antibody-testing.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/antibody.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;antibody&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What’s In A COVID-19 Antibody Test?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As of April 24, there are 4 COVID-19 antibody tests approved for diagnostic purposes in the US, and 44 approved for diagnostic or research purposes around the world.[1]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of these are ELISA tests, which detect the presence of antibodies to viral proteins, such as the N (nucleocapsid) protein or S (spike) protein.  The subject’s blood serum is incubated with the protein, and then washed with antibody-dye conjugates that fluoresce in proportion to the concentration of bound antibody/viral protein complexes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some tests, such as one approved in Singapore, is a viral neutralization assay that tests the patient’s serum for its ability to neutralize viral replication in vitro.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, some are rapid tests, which screen for the presence or absence of antibodies to the viral protein, but cannot measure the concentration. These can be very quick (&amp;lt;15 min) to perform, but tell us nothing about the concentration of the antibody.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Viral neutralization tests, compared to ELISA can tell us more about how likely the antibodies are to protect against infection, but they also take longer than ELISA tests (3-5 days vs 1-5 hours.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How Accurate Are COVID-19 Antibody Tests at Predicting Serum Viral RNA?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Manufacturer&lt;/strong&gt;
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Test Type&lt;/strong&gt;
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sensitivity&lt;/strong&gt;
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Specificity&lt;/strong&gt;
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sample Size (# of individuals)&lt;/strong&gt;
   &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;USTC (Hefei, China)
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;IgG/IgA rapid test for S protein receptor binding domain
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;99.2%
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;100%
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;570
   &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Jiangsu Medomics
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;IgM/IgG lateral flow immunoassay for S protein receptor binding domain
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;88.66%
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;90.63%
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;525
   &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;VITROS
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;ELISA against spike protein
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;83%
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;100%
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;436
   &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Cellex
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;IgM/IgG lateral flow immunoassay against N protein
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;93.8%
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;96.0%
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;378
   &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Euroimmun
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;IgG/IgA rapid test for S1 protein
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;94%
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;98%
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;310
   &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Zhejiang Orient
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;IgG rapid test
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;93.1%
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;99.2%
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;153
   &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Wantai
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;ELISA for S protein receptor binding domain
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;93%
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;100%
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;112
   &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Mount Sinai
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;ELISA for S protein
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;100%
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;100%
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;111
   &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;NIH
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;LIPS test for N protein 
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;67% all, 100% 14 days after symptoms
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;100%
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;81
   &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Dynamiker
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Rapid IgG/IgM
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;90%
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;100%
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;62
   &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;CTK Biotech
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Rapid IgG/IgM
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;90%
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;100%
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;62
   &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Unnamed
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Rapid IgG/IgM
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;36.4%
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;88.9%
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;39
   &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Beijing Diagreat Biotechnologies
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Rapid IgG/IgM
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;83%
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;93%
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;30
   &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Chinese-designed IgM/IgG combined assay for COVID-19 (Jiangsu Medomics)  testing for antibodies against the receptor binding domain of the spike protein, tested on confirmed COVID-19 cases selected from hospitals in 6 different provinces and healthy volunteers, had a sensitivity of 88.66% and a specificity of 90.63%.[2]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A German-designed IgG/IgA assay against the spike protein S1 of SARS-CoV-2 (Euroimmun) had a 100% specificity (did not react against healthy volunteers, patients with non-coronavirus viruses, or patients with endemic coronaviruses that cause the common cold.  All 3 SARS-CoV-2 patients got positive tests, for a specificity of 100%. 2/2 SARS-CoV patients also got positive results from this antibody test.  More severe patients had higher antibody titers.[3]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Swedish preprint study evaluating a Chinese-made rapid antibody test (Zhejiang Orient Gene Biotech) on 29 PCR-confirmed COVID-19 patients or convalescents and 100 healthy controls had a sensitivity of 93.1% and specificity of 99.2% for the IgG test. The IgM test had only a 69% sensitivity but a 100% specificity. [4]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Chinese preprint study of RBD antibody kits for combined IgA/IgG antibodies on 330 healthy subjects, 153 patients with non-COVID-19 diseases, and 87 SARS-CoV-2 cases, had a sensitivity of 99.1% and specificity of 100%. IgA levels but not IgM levels were higher in more severe patients (p &amp;lt; 0.0001).[5]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An ELISA test against the SARS-CoV-2 spike protein, developed at Mount Sinai Hospital in the US and approved for diagnostic use, was tested on 17 confirmed COVID-19 cases (3 convalescent, 14 acute) and 94 negative controls collected before the COVID-19 pandemic began.  All 17 COVID-19 patients had antibodies that reacted strongly in the test, while none of the controls did.  Additionally, the concentration of antibody correlates positively to viral neutralization ability (p &amp;lt;0.0001, r = 0.9279).[6]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An independent Danish preprint study of 9 antibody tests on 30 confirmed COVID-19 cases admitted to the ICU and 82 non-COVID-19 patients (healthy blood donors or people with other acute viral infections) found that the Wantai test for the spike protein receptor binding domain had a sensitivity of 93% and specificity of 100%, while the Euroimmun IgA test had a specificity of 93% and sensitivity of 93%.  Point-of-care rapid tests were less sensitive – the Dynamiker and CTK Biotech tests (both IgG/IgM tests) had sensitivities of 90% and specificities of 100%. The best two ELISA tests agreed 93% with each other.[7]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Briefer illnesses (7-13 days vs 14-20 and &amp;gt;21 days) had somewhat lower rates of positive test results, which is consistent with other studies finding that more severe disease correlated with higher antibody levels. [7]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A German study of an unnamed rapid IgG/IgM test on 39 randomly selected patients who were also tested for COVID-19 with RT-PCR (the benchmark), the sensitivity was only 36.4% while the specificity was 88.9%.  (Note that this could include patients who were in the early stages of the disease, when viral RNA is detectable but antibodies are not.)[8]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An Italian study of the Beijing Diagreat Biotechnologies rapid IgG/IgM test on 30 patients admitted to the hospital with either confirmed COVID-19, suspected COVID-19 that turned out to be something else, or asymptomatic controls, the sensitivity was 83% and the specificity was 93%.[9]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A novel type of immunoassay, LIPS (Luciferase Immunoprecipitation System) was  tested on 49 patients with confirmed COVID-19 and 32 blood bank donor controls. None of the controls had a positive result for nucleocapsid antibodies, while 67% of the COVID-19 patients did.  Similarly, none of the controls had a positive result for spike protein antibodies, while 57% of the COVID-19 patients did.  When restricted to samples taken &amp;gt;14 days after symptom onset, the sensitivity and specificity were 100%.[10]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Premarket testing for the Cellex rapid IgG/IgM test evaluated 128 confirmed COVID-19 cases and 250 negative subjects, and found a sensitivity of 93.8% and a specificity of 96.0%.[11]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The VITROS modified ELISA test against spike protein was positive in 30/36 patients with confirmed cases of COVID-19 (sensitivity of 83%) and negative in 100% of 400 non-COVID-19 samples.[12]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Bottom Lines&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All in all, the antibody tests are generally quite specific (at least in patients who have had the disease for at least two weeks) and fairly sensitive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Antibody levels tend to rise over the course of the disease and tend to be higher in more severe cases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How Should We Interpret The Antibody Seroprevalence Data in the US?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Several recent papers have come out with estimates of the prevalence of SARS-CoV-2 in US cities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;PCR Tests of Random Samples in the US&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Out of 131 patients presenting with mild influenza-like symptoms in a Los Angeles clinic, 7 tested positive for SARS-CoV-2, or 5%.[13]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Between March 22 and April 4, all pregnant women delivering at New York Presbyterian and Columbia University hospitals in New York were tested for COVID-19. 15.4% of all pregnant women tested positive for SARS-CoV-2.   Only 12% of the patients who tested positive had COVID-19 symptoms, consistent with a picture in which most infections are asymptomatic.[14]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A screening program of 24 homeless shelters in Seattle, Boston, San Francisco, and Atlanta found 25% of residents and 11% of staff members tested positive for SARS-CoV-2.  This is probably much higher than the general population in those cities since homeless people are sicker than others and living in institutional environments like shelters spreads disease.[20]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;PCR Tests of Random Samples In Other Countries&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Iceland did an extensive testing program for SARS-CoV-2, issuing an open invitation to 10,797 people and random invitations to 2283 people.  In total, 6% of the Icelandic population was screened.  0.6% of the open invitation group and 0.8% of the random invitation group tested positive for the virus.  57% of those who tested positive also reported symptoms of COVID-19.[16]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A study testing 1097 health care workers with mild respiratory symptoms in 9 hospitals in the Netherlands found that 4% tested positive for SARS-CoV-2.[17]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A screening study for SARS-CoV-2 in 1654 UK medical staff with symptoms of cough or fever found 14% tested positive.[22]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;South Korea has one of the largest COVID-19 testing programs in the world, testing 601,660 people between January 3 and April 27, or about 1% of its population. 1.8% of those tested were positive, and 2.3% of the confirmed cases were fatal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Antibody Tests in the US&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A study that recruited participants in Santa Clara County, California through Facebook ads tested 3330 participants with a rapid IgG/IgM test (Premier Biotech.)  This test had previously been found to have an 80% sensitivity rate and 99.5% specificity rate, from combining the manufacturer’s data and an independent experiment, 523 patients in all.[15]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The crude prevalence rate of antibodies in Santa Clara County was 1.5%; after weighting the sample to match Santa Clara County by zipcode, race, and sex, the rate was 2.81%.  Adjusting for the sensitivity and specificity of the test, the estimated prevalence is 2.75%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The authors conclude that, because the prevalence of antibodies is much higher than the number of confirmed cases (there were 985 confirmed cases in Santa Clara County, while this study’s data suggests 48,000-81,000 cases should exist), that COVID-19 is almost always asymptomatic and should have a much lower case fatality rate than previously assumed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t think this conclusion is reasonable.  Confirmed case numbers were low for a long time in the US, even when the pandemic was spreading rapidly, because there was a shortage of tests before the FDA approved several new tests.  Even a serious case of suspected COVID-19 can’t get a diagnostic confirmation if no tests are available.  It makes more sense to suppose that the confirmed case numbers (and, thus, the confirmed fatality numbers) are underestimates than to take those numbers literally and infer that the disease kills only 0.1-0.2% of those infected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Miami-Dade County in Florida has embarked on a random antibody screening program, and preliminary results from 1800 individuals indicate a rate of 6%, which is 16.5x higher than the number of confirmed cases captured by hospitals and testing sites alone.[24] About half of the individuals who tested positive had no symptoms.[25]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A random antibody test of New York State residents sampled from shoppers at grocery and big-box stores found 21% in New York City, 17% in Long Island, 12% in Westchester, and &amp;lt;4% in the rest of the state, had antibodies to the virus.[26]  These numbers may be overestimates because people who are shopping are less likely to be practicing social distancing and thus are more at risk for infection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Preliminary results from a random antibody screening program in Los Angeles County found that 4.1% of residents tested positive for SARS-CoV-19 antibodies.[29]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Antibody Tests in Other Countries&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1000 blood samples from blood donors in Scotland were screened for SARS-CoV-2 neutralizing antibodies; 0.5% tested positive. Note that blood donors are healthier on average than the general population, since donors with a history of recent respiratory infection are turned away; so this serves as more of a lower bound on the prevalence of SARS-CoV-2 antibodies in the Scottish population.[19]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Other Measurements of Prevalence&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SARS-CoV-2 levels in the wastewater of a major water treatment facility in Massachussetts suggest that roughly 5% of the stool samples in the state were positive for the virus between March 18-25, a number much higher than the 0.026% prevalence rate for confirmed SARS-CoV-2 cases in Massachusetts. This points towards COVID-19 being underdiagnosed, as we’d expect given the shortage of tests.[18]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A New York Times report on April 27th observed that New York City had triple the number of all-cause deaths compared to historical baselines, and other countries also had higher rates of all-cause mortality than their historical baselines. (Spain, 67% above normal; Equador, 83% above normal; Jakarta, Indonesia, 57% above normal.) These numbers can’t be confounded by any possible over-diagnosis of COVID-19, and constitute clear evidence that the epidemic is killing people. Moreover, there are more all-cause deaths than can be accounted for by confirmed COVID-19 deaths alone; so either the disease is underdiagnosed or people are dying from other effects of the pandemic (such as a shortage of hospital care.)[21]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In March 2020, the number of LA County cases of influenza-like symptoms was double that in March of the past 4 years, despite it being past the peak of flu season.[13]  This likewise points to COVID-19 causing a large number of symptomatic cases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Conclusions&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most screens of random population samples – that is, _not _specifically selected for having symptoms or for having contacts with COVID-19 – seem to show 0.5-5% prevalence for the disease, in different cities and countries, whether measured by antibodies, viral RNA, or even wastewater RNA concentrations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prevalence numbers are higher among high-risk populations (healthcare workers and homeless people) and _much _higher in New York City, the center of the US epidemic and a very dense population.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the US specifically, where testing has been scarce, this means that the number of confirmed cases has been underestimated by at least an order of magnitude.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The antibody screening experiments have been criticized on the grounds that antibody tests are not perfectly accurate. I don’t think this is a valid argument against the main point (that there are probably &amp;gt;10x as many true cases as confirmed cases in the US.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Antibody tests vary in their _sensitivity _(how likely they are to give a positive result in a real infection) and tend to not show up as positive until 2 weeks after the onset of symptoms.  But, if anything, this should mean the true positive rate is even _larger _than the numbers in the studies. Antibody tests tend to have fairly high _specificity _– the maximum % of false positives I’ve seen reported is 10% – and so even if 10% of the reported positives are false ones, that would still mean that the seroprevalence of COVID-19 is many times higher than the rate of confirmed cases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some commentators have concluded that this means that the danger of COVID-19 has been overstated; that the risk of dying given a SARS-CoV-19 infection is much lower than previously supposed.  I think this is misleading.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The official case fatality rate (# of confirmed COVID-19 deaths/ # of confirmed COVID-19 cases) may be an overestimate, because when testing is scarce, more severe cases are more likely to be tested. Right now the cumulative global case fatality rate is a whopping 7% and the US case fatality rate is 2.8%.[27][28]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, estimating an infection fatality rate defined by # of confirmed deaths / expected # of antibody-positive individuals is likely to be an &lt;em&gt;underestimate&lt;/em&gt;, since if testing capacity is scarce, we can expect even some fatal COVID-19 cases to go unconfirmed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These “optimistic” estimates of infection fatality rate are about 0.3% for Santa Clara County, 0.2% for L.A. County, 0.1% for Miami-Dade County, and 0.7% for New York City.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we compare these estimates to two countries that had extensive COVID-19 testing, Iceland and South Korea, the cumulative case fatality rate for Iceland is 0.5% (in line with the optimistic US estimates) and the rate for South Korea is 2.3% (quite a bit higher than the optimistic US estimates.)  So it’s not clear what conclusion to draw from international comparisons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One consideration is that the South Korean testing program is not a random sample of the population, though it was extensive – people with symptoms or connections to COVID-19 patients are prioritized for testing.  So its 2.3% mortality rate may be an overestimate as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we consider the 3x elevated all-cause mortality rate in NYC, and assume that _all _excess deaths are COVID-19 deaths, and that 21% of New Yorkers are infected, this gives a “pessimistic” estimate of 1.2% of COVID-19 infections being fatal in NYC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My current best guess is that the true estimate of infection fatality rate in the US is somewhere between the “optimistic” and “pessimistic” probabilities, i.e. between 0.1% and 1.2%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is still not, by any means, &lt;em&gt;good&lt;/em&gt;. If the US ended all quarantines today, without a vaccine or effective treatment, and allowed the virus to spread until herd immunity was achieved, or about 60% of the US population, this would mean about 200,000-2,000,000 deaths this year.  On the high end, that’s as deadly per capita as the US Civil War,[30] and deadlier than the Spanish Flu.[31]  “Less deadly than previously estimated” does not mean “no big deal.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Do Viral Antibodies Generally Correspond to Past Viral Infection?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Outside of COVID-19, what’s the track record of accuracy of viral antibody tests?  Are there a sizable population who have positive antibodies to viruses they were never infected with?  Do many people get infected with viruses that they never develop antibodies to?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This can put the credibility of antibody tests for COVID-19 in a broader context. If antibody false positives are really common overall, then the apparently good specificity of the COVID-19 tests (derived from small studies, often by the manufacturers) may be too optimistic, and the actual prevalence of COVID-19 may be quite a bit lower than it appears in the antibody screening studies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Test Type&lt;/strong&gt;
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Virus&lt;/strong&gt;
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sensitivity&lt;/strong&gt;
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Specificity&lt;/strong&gt;
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;# Of Individuals&lt;/strong&gt;
   &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Rapid
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;HIV
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;&amp;gt;95%
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;&amp;gt;99%
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;6282
   &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;NS1 ELISA, IgM/IgG
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Zika
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;100%
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;100%
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;1379
   &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Rapid
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;HCV
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;97.8% \
88.3% \
99.3%
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;99.5%
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;1083
   &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Rapid test and ELISA
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;H5N1
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;18.2% \
38.7%
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;100% \
100%
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;
   &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;IgM ELISA
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Dengue
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;96%
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;84%
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;225
   &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;rapid
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Chikungunya
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;20.5% \
50.8%
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;100% \
89.2%
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;206
   &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;NS1 ELISA
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Dengue
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;83.2%
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;100%
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;138
   &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;NS1 Rapid
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Dengue
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;73.8%
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;100%
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;138
   &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;
   &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;
   &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An ELISA test and rapid antibody test for dengue virus, tested in 138 Vietnamese patients admitted to the ICU with clinical suspicion of dengue, had sensitivities of 83.2% and 73.8% respectively, and specificities of 100%.[32]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a study of antibody tests for dengue virus on 225 patients from around the world, some with dengue, some with other viruses, and some healthy controls, the ELISA tests for NS1 antigen had sensitivities of 60-75% in acute cases and 19-31% in convalescent cases, and the rapid tests had sensitivities of 40-60% in acute cases and 12-59% in convalescent cases.  The anti-dengue IgM ELISA test had a sensitivity of 98% in both acute and convalescent cases, while the anti-dengue IgM rapid tests had a sensitivity of 45-95 in both acute and convalescent cases.  The specificity of NS1 tests was 71-80%, and the IgM ELISA test had a specificity of 84%.[33]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3 rapid tests for HCV (hepatitis C) on 1083 samples: all specificities over 99.5%, sensitivities were 97.8%, 88.3%, 99.3%[34]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;6 rapid tests for HIV on 6282 study participants, compared to a gold standard of Western blot, ELISA, &amp;amp; treatment status.  All sensitivities were &amp;gt;95% and specificities were &amp;gt;99%.[35]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a study of an IgG/IgM ELISA test for Zika virus, on 112 patients with RT-PCR confirmed or suspected Zika, 1015 healthy patients, and 252 patients with other viruses, the sensitivity of combined IgG and IgM tests was 100% and specificity was 100%.[36]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two rapid tests for chikungunya virus, tested on 132 patients with confirmed chikungunya and 74 patients with a different febrile illness; one had a 20.5% sensitivity and 100% specificity, while the other had a 50.8% sensitivity and 89.2% specificity.[37]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a study of 524 patients tested for H5N1 (avian flu) a rapid test had a sensitivity of 18.2% and an ELISA test had a sensitivity of 38.7%.  Both had specificities of 100%.[38]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Conclusions&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the performance of antibody tests for different viruses depends on the test itself, most have high specificities.  There is no reason to suppose that the measured specificity levels for SARS-CoV-2 tests are unrealistically low.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Do Viral Antibodies Generally Predict Immunity to Future Infection?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The WHO has been saying there’s “no evidence” that antibodies in recovered patients indicate immunity to COVID-19.[39] It’s too soon to tell whether this is true for COVID-19, but do antibody levels predict viral immunity in other viruses?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a longitudinal cohort of 7547 Nicaraguan children monitored for dengue virus, preinfection antibody titer correlated with lower risk of having a symptomatic second infection (p &amp;lt; 0.005).  Children with serologically confirmed but asymptomatic second infections had preinfection antibody titers 2.3-fold higher than children with symptomatic second infections.  Also, children with symptomatic first infections were less likely to have symptomatic second infections independent of antibody titer – apparently infection grants immunity through mechanisms other than antibody quantity.[40]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 17 infants born to mothers with HSV1 or HSV2 infections during pregnancy, the babies with milder (or asymptomatic) infections had higher neutralizing antibody titers at birth than the babies with severe cases.  Average titer was 1:13 for severe cases, 1:65 for mild cases, and 1:69 for asymptomatic cases.[41]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nine studies of human volunteers previously infected with influenza in the 60’s and 70’s and challenged with exposure to an influenza virus found that _no _volunteers developed symptomatic illness after challenge, out of a total of 86 patients.  “The titer of serum anti-HA antibodies remains the most consistent correlate of immunity to influenza virus infection.”[42]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a cohort of 200 Mexican infants monitored for rotavirus, children with higher (&amp;gt; 1:800) rotavirus IgA titers were less likely to have rotavirus infection (RR = 0.21, p &amp;lt; 0.001) and rotavirus diarrhea (RR = 0.16, p &amp;lt; 0.01) and never got severe diarrhea.[43]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1164 healthy children immunized with varicella vaccine, children with lower antibody titers after the vaccine (&amp;lt;5 gpELISA units) were 3.5x as likely to develop a varicella infection in the next 7 years as children with higher antibody titers (&amp;gt;5 gpELISA units.)[44]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a study of 38 adults challenged with rotavirus, patients who got ill from the exposure had higher preinoculation rotavirus IgG antibody (7.3 vs 6.1, p = 0.041).  There was no significant difference in infection rate between those exposed to a larger vs. smaller quantity.[45]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a study of 696 adults and children in rural Bangladesh, serum IgG rotavirus antibodies were on average 4x higher in cases of symptomatic rotavirus than healthy controls.[46]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 33 volunteers experimentally infected with human coronavirus 223E, those who had higher antibody titers prior to exposure were much less likely to get symptomatic disease (average ELISA ratio for neutralizing antibodies was 6.5x higher in the affected group vs the unaffected group, p &amp;lt;0.001)  Those who had had a cold in the last six months had significantly (p&amp;lt;0.05) lower clinical scores than those who had not.[47]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have very consistent results across all viruses studied indicating that yes, higher pre-challenge virus-specific antibody titers are predictive of lower rates of symptomatic disease.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We don’t know yet whether reinfection of people previously infected with COVID-19 is _ever _possible, but we _do _have evidence from other viruses suggesting that if you’ve recovered successfully from a COVID-19 illness you are _less _susceptible to getting a symptomatic disease if you’re exposed again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[1]&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.centerforhealthsecurity.org/resources/COVID-19/serology/Serology-based-tests-for-COVID-19.html&quot;&gt;https://www.centerforhealthsecurity.org/resources/COVID-19/serology/Serology-based-tests-for-COVID-19.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[2]Li, Zhengtu, et al. “Development and clinical application of a rapid IgM‐IgG combined antibody test for SARS‐CoV‐2 infection diagnosis.” &lt;em&gt;Journal of medical virology&lt;/em&gt; (2020).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[3]Okba, Nisreen MA, et al. “SARS-CoV-2 specific antibody responses in COVID-19 patients.” &lt;em&gt;medRxiv&lt;/em&gt; (2020).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[4]Ma, Huan, et al. “COVID-19 diagnosis and study of serum SARS-CoV-2 specific IgA, IgM and IgG by a quantitative and sensitive immunoassay.” &lt;em&gt;medRxiv&lt;/em&gt; (2020).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[5]Zhang, Pingping, et al. “Evaluation of recombinant nucleocapsid and spike proteins for serological diagnosis of novel coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19).” &lt;em&gt;MedRxiv&lt;/em&gt; (2020).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[6]Amanat, Fatima, et al. “A serological assay to detect SARS-CoV-2 seroconversion in humans.” &lt;em&gt;MedRxiv&lt;/em&gt; (2020).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[7]Lassaunière, Ria, et al. “Evaluation of nine commercial SARS-CoV-2 immunoassays.” &lt;em&gt;medRxiv&lt;/em&gt; (2020).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[8]Döhla, M., et al. “Rapid point-of-care testing for SARS-CoV-2 in a community screening setting shows low sensitivity.” &lt;em&gt;Public Health&lt;/em&gt; (2020).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[9]Spicuzza, Lucia, et al. “Reliability and usefulness of a rapid IgM‐IgG antibody test for the diagnosis of SARS-CoV-2 infection: a preliminary report.” &lt;em&gt;Journal of Infection&lt;/em&gt; (2020).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[10]Burbelo, Peter D., et al. “Detection of Nucleocapsid Antibody to SARS-CoV-2 is More Sensitive than Antibody to Spike Protein in COVID-19 Patients.” &lt;em&gt;medRxiv&lt;/em&gt; (2020).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[11]&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fda.gov/media/136625/download&quot;&gt;https://www.fda.gov/media/136625/download&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[12] &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fda.gov/media/136967/download&quot;&gt;https://www.fda.gov/media/136967/download&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[13]Spellberg, Brad, et al. “Community prevalence of SARS-CoV-2 among patients with influenzalike illnesses presenting to a Los Angeles medical center in March 2020.” &lt;em&gt;JAMA&lt;/em&gt; (2020).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[14]Sutton, Desmond, et al. “Universal screening for SARS-CoV-2 in women admitted for delivery.” &lt;em&gt;New England Journal of Medicine&lt;/em&gt; (2020).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[15]Bendavid, Eran, et al. “COVID-19 Antibody Seroprevalence in Santa Clara County, California.” &lt;em&gt;medRxiv&lt;/em&gt; (2020).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[16]Gudbjartsson, Daniel F., et al. “Spread of SARS-CoV-2 in the Icelandic population.” &lt;em&gt;New England Journal of Medicine&lt;/em&gt; (2020).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[17]Reusken, Chantal B., et al. “Rapid assessment of regional SARS-CoV-2 community transmission through a convenience sample of healthcare workers, the Netherlands, March 2020.” &lt;em&gt;Eurosurveillance&lt;/em&gt; 25.12 (2020): 2000334.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[18]Wu, Fuqing, et al. “SARS-CoV-2 titers in wastewater are higher than expected from clinically confirmed cases.” &lt;em&gt;medRxiv&lt;/em&gt; (2020).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[19]Thompson, Craig, et al. “Neutralising antibodies to SARS coronavirus 2 in Scottish blood donors-a pilot study of the value of serology to determine population exposure.” &lt;em&gt;medRxiv&lt;/em&gt; (2020).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[20]Mosites, Emily. “Assessment of SARS-CoV-2 Infection Prevalence in Homeless Shelters—Four US Cities, March 27–April 15, 2020.” &lt;em&gt;MMWR. Morbidity and Mortality Weekly Report&lt;/em&gt; 69 (2020).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[21]&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2020/04/21/world/coronavirus-missing-deaths.html&quot;&gt;https://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2020/04/21/world/coronavirus-missing-deaths.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[22]Hunter, Ewan, et al. “First experience of COVID-19 screening of health-care workers in England.” &lt;em&gt;The Lancet&lt;/em&gt; (2020).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[23]&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.statista.com/statistics/1095848/south-korea-confirmed-and-suspected-coronavirus-cases/&quot;&gt;https://www.statista.com/statistics/1095848/south-korea-confirmed-and-suspected-coronavirus-cases/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[24]&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.miamidade.gov/releases/2020-04-24-sample-testing-results.asp&quot;&gt;https://www.miamidade.gov/releases/2020-04-24-sample-testing-results.asp&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[25]&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.miamiherald.com/news/coronavirus/article242260406.html&quot;&gt;https://www.miamiherald.com/news/coronavirus/article242260406.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[26]&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2020/04/23/nyregion/coronavirus-antibodies-test-ny.html&quot;&gt;https://www.nytimes.com/2020/04/23/nyregion/coronavirus-antibodies-test-ny.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[27]&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cdc.gov/nchs/nvss/vsrr/covid19/index.htm&quot;&gt;https://www.cdc.gov/nchs/nvss/vsrr/covid19/index.htm&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[28]&lt;a href=&quot;https://coronavirus.jhu.edu/map.html&quot;&gt;https://coronavirus.jhu.edu/map.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[29]&lt;a href=&quot;http://publichealth.lacounty.gov/phcommon/public/media/mediapubhpdetail.cfm?prid=2328&quot;&gt;http://publichealth.lacounty.gov/phcommon/public/media/mediapubhpdetail.cfm?prid=2328&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[30]&lt;a href=&quot;https://prospect.org/power/american-war-dead-numbers/&quot;&gt;https://prospect.org/power/american-war-dead-numbers/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[31]&lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/20160923152823/http://www.flu.gov/pandemic/history/1918/&quot;&gt;https://web.archive.org/web/20160923152823/http://www.flu.gov/pandemic/history/1918/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[32]Hang, Vu Ty, et al. “Diagnostic accuracy of NS1 ELISA and lateral flow rapid tests for dengue sensitivity, specificity and relationship to viraemia and antibody responses.” &lt;em&gt;PLoS neglected tropical diseases&lt;/em&gt; 3.1 (2009).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[33]Hunsperger, Elizabeth A., et al. “Evaluation of commercially available diagnostic tests for the detection of dengue virus NS1 antigen and anti-dengue virus IgM antibody.” &lt;em&gt;PLoS neglected tropical diseases&lt;/em&gt; 8.10 (2014).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[34]Smith, Bryce D., et al. “Evaluation of three rapid screening assays for detection of antibodies to hepatitis C virus.” &lt;em&gt;Journal of Infectious Diseases&lt;/em&gt; 204.6 (2011): 825-831.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[35]Delaney, Kevin P., et al. “Evaluation of the performance characteristics of 6 rapid HIV antibody tests.” &lt;em&gt;Clinical Infectious Diseases&lt;/em&gt; 52.2 (2011): 257-263.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[36]Steinhagen, Katja, et al. “Serodiagnosis of Zika virus (ZIKV) infections by a novel NS1-based ELISA devoid of cross-reactivity with dengue virus antibodies: a multicohort study of assay performance, 2015 to 2016.” &lt;em&gt;Eurosurveillance&lt;/em&gt; 21.50 (2016).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[37]Kosasih, Herman, et al. “Evaluation of two IgM rapid immunochromatographic tests during circulation of Asian lineage Chikungunya virus.” &lt;em&gt;Southeast Asian Journal of Tropical Medicineand Public Health&lt;/em&gt; 43.1 (2012): 55.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[38]Ganzenmueller, Tina, et al. “Comparison of the performance of direct fluorescent antibody staining, a point-of-care rapid antigen test and virus isolation with that of RT-PCR for the detection of novel 2009 influenza A (H1N1) virus in respiratory specimens.” &lt;em&gt;Journal of medical microbiology&lt;/em&gt; 59.6 (2010): 713-717.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[39]&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cnbc.com/2020/04/17/who-issues-warning-on-coronavirus-testing-theres-no-evidence-antibody-tests-show-immunity.html&quot;&gt;https://www.cnbc.com/2020/04/17/who-issues-warning-on-coronavirus-testing-theres-no-evidence-antibody-tests-show-immunity.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[40]Katzelnick, Leah C., et al. “Neutralizing antibody titers against dengue virus correlate with protection from symptomatic infection in a longitudinal cohort.” &lt;em&gt;Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences&lt;/em&gt; 113.3 (2016): 728-733.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[41]Yeager, Anne S., et al. “Relationship of antibody to outcome in neonatal herpes simplex virus infections.” &lt;em&gt;Infection and immunity&lt;/em&gt; 29.2 (1980): 532-538.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[42]Couch, Robert B., and Julius A. Kasel. “Immunity to influenza in man.” &lt;em&gt;Annual review of microbiology&lt;/em&gt; 37.1 (1983): 529-549.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[43]Velázquez, F. Raúl, et al. “Serum antibody as a marker of protection against natural rotavirus infection and disease.” &lt;em&gt;The Journal of infectious diseases&lt;/em&gt; 182.6 (2000): 1602-1609.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[44]Li, Shu, et al. “Inverse relationship between six week postvaccination varicella antibody response to vaccine and likelihood of long term breakthrough infection.” &lt;em&gt;The Pediatric infectious disease journal&lt;/em&gt; 21.4 (2002): 337-342.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[45]Ward, Richard L., et al. “Effects of antibody to rotavirus on protection of adults challenged with a human rotavirus.” &lt;em&gt;Journal of Infectious Diseases&lt;/em&gt; 159.1 (1989): 79-88.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[46]Ward, Richard L., et al. “Effects of antibody to rotavirus on protection of adults challenged with a human rotavirus.” &lt;em&gt;Journal of Infectious Diseases&lt;/em&gt; 159.1 (1989): 79-88.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[47]Callow, Kathleen A. “Effect of specific humoral immunity and some non-specific factors on resistance of volunteers to respiratory coronavirus infection.” Epidemiology &amp;amp; Infection 95.1 (1985): 173-189.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="covid-19" /><category term="lit-review" /><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Variolation for COVID-19</title><link href="https://srconstantin.github.io/2020/04/13/variolation.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Variolation for COVID-19" /><published>2020-04-13T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-04-13T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://srconstantin.github.io/2020/04/13/variolation</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://srconstantin.github.io/2020/04/13/variolation.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/anti-vaccination-cartoon.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;variolation&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Variolation refers to a historical precursor of vaccination used for smallpox. Healthy subjects were inoculated with material from the scabs of smallpox patients, which usually gave them a mild version of the disease and protected them from contracting the full disease.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By analogy, is it possible that a low-dose exposure to the SARS-CoV-2 virus could result in a mild illness and immunity to subsequently contracting the disease?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Are Low Doses of COVID-19 Virus Safer?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One (imperfect) proxy for this question is whether lower viral titers of SARS-CoV-2 correspond to less severe disease.  It seems intuitively plausible – smaller quantities of the virus in the body might be easier for the immune system to fight off and/or cause less extensive tissue damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking at viral RNA titers in COVID-19 patients doesn’t tell us whether they were initially exposed to large or small amounts of virus, though. If there’s a correlation between viral titer and disease severity, it could either be because the sicker patients got a higher initial “dose” of virus, or because the virus was more successful at multiplying in them.  However, we can somewhat alleviate this ambiguity by looking at the trajectories of virus titer over time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A retrospective study of 76 Chinese patients found that viral loads (as measured by nasal swab) were significantly higher in severe than mild cases of COVID-19, p &amp;lt; 0.005. All patients’ viral loads followed a similar trajectory over time – they started high and steadily declined.  However, severe cases had detectable levels of virus for much longer – all severe cases still had viral RNA after 10 days from disease onset, while most mild cases were virus-free by 10 days.[1]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Viral load does not correlate perfectly with disease.  Asymptomatic patients [2][3] can have similar viral loads to sick ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another, smaller study with 23 COVID-19 patients found a significant association of peak viral load with age but no significant association of either initial or peak viral load with disease severity.[4]  The correlation of viral load with age is explainable by immunosenescence (aging weakens the immune system) and tells us that higher viral load can be caused by a weaker immune system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the SARS epidemic, healthcare workers who were exposed to one of three index patients and tested positive for SARS were significantly more likely to be asymptomatic if they wore masks, which suggests that masks lower the amount of virus exposure and that lower virus exposure results in less severe disease.[5]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another study of 16 individuals exposed to a single SARS index patient showed that the healthcare workers, who were wearing PPE, had significantly lower viral load than the non-healthcare workers, who had no masks. The non-healthcare workers were also more likely to have severe disease, but they were also older on average.[7]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Among people with exposure to a SARS index patient, they were significantly (p &amp;lt; 0.001) more likely to get SARS the longer the index patient stayed home after the onset of fever; when the patient stayed home for &amp;gt;6 days, as opposed to &amp;lt;=2 days, the risk of getting the disease jumps from 38% to 66%.  You were more likely to get the disease if you shared a room and bed with the index patient, if you dined more frequently with the index patient, and if you had more frequent close contact with the index patient.  This indicates that the volume of contact with the SARS virus influences the risk of contracting disease.[8]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Higher initial viral load is also associated with worse prognosis and shorter survival times in SARS.[6]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The evidence is relatively sparse but consistent with the hypothesis that lower volumes of exposure to SARS-CoV-2 and SARS-CoV result in lower viral titers and less severe disease.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Is COVID-19 Reinfection Possible?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Deliberately infecting a human with a low dose of virus, of course, has not been done enough for there to be a research literature about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what happens when we do it with animals?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have mixed results on reinfection in animals, some studies showing that prior exposure to a coronavirus protects against subsequent infection, while others showed that reinfection can indeed occur.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rhesus monkeys that have been infected with SARS-CoV-2 do not get reinfected after a second challenge; they do not show viral replication or clinical symptoms.[15]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mice who have previously been exposed to SARS-CoV are protected from disease for at least 28 days. Serum from mice that had previously been exposed to the virus, injected into SARS-naive mice, also had a protective effect, while serum from non-exposed mice did not.[12]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ferrets infected with SARS-CoV who were reinfected 4 weeks later did not have as high viral titers upon reinfection and did not show lung histopathology.[14]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alpacas and camels experimentally infected with MERS-CoV are protected against reinfection.[17]  On the other hand, a longitudinal study of a camel herd showed that reinfection can occur in camels who have previously acquired antibodies to MERS-CoV.[18]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reinfection is possible in cats previously exposed to feline coronavirus [19], and in cows with bovine coronavirus [20].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Exposure to an inactivated form of a virus is a standard type of vaccine, and it has been found effective in rodents for SARS-CoV.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Partially inactivated SARS-CoV virus samples (treated with formaldehyde) were no longer able to replicate in vitro. When mice were treated with this inactivated virus (by injection or intranasal administration) they produced detectable antibody responses.[9][10]  SARS-CoV virus inactivated with UV radiation also produced an antibody response in mice.[11]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whole killed SARS-CoV vaccine (inactivated with beta-propiolactone)  protected mice against a challenge infection.[13]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hamsters immunized with beta-propiolactone inactivated SARS-CoV virus had lower virus titers than non-immunized hamsters upon challenge with active SARS-CoV and had less severe lung lesions than non-immunized hamsters.[16]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There have been reports of reinfected COVID-19 patients in China and Japan[21] but some think that these are due to testing errors where the patients erroneously tested as having recovered when they were still infected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The current state of evidence hasn’t ruled out that reinfection could occur for SARS-CoV-2, but tentatively it seems more likely that people who have been infected once are protected against further infections for some period of time. The duration of protection, and whether there are any individuals who don’t get immunological protection, is still unknown.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusion&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s reason to believe that exposure to a lower dose of the SARS-CoV-2 virus produces a milder disease than exposure to larger quantities of SARS-CoV-2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And there’s reason to believe that people who have recovered from COVID-19 have some protection against the disease.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What we _don’t _know is whether a dose low enough not to cause severe symptoms is also high enough to cause immune protection against subsequent infections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Deliberate Exposure as a Policy&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A trial of deliberate exposure of young, healthy volunteers to COVID-19 has been &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.overcomingbias.com/2020/04/variolation-test-design.html&quot;&gt;proposed&lt;/a&gt; by Robin Hanson.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The case for deliberate exposure is to produce a population of immune people who don’t have to be quarantined – for instance, so that they can continue to work as healthcare workers, janitors, and other essential employees in a mostly housebound economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The downside, of course, is that deliberately infecting people with a disease harms them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Deliberate exposure looks better relative to other options under certain conditions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;if deliberate exposure causes little harm to the exposed (either because the dose is low or because young people rarely get severe disease)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;if reinfection after safe doses of virus is rare or impossible&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;if exposure to the active virus is much easier and/or more effective than alternative, safer types of immune protection (like convalescent serum or inactivated virus)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;if containing the virus is expected to be impossible (i.e. most people will get the disease, the question is when) or so costly that countries decide it’s not worth continuing the lockdowns.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;if developing an effective vaccine or treatment is expected to be slow&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am doubtful about the first three conditions.  We don’t know much about what a “safe” dose of SARS-CoV-2 is, and we haven’t fully ruled out reinfection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And young people, while less vulnerable than older people, are not immune from severe COVID-19 – in New York, 9% of patients age 18-44 had to be &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cbsnews.com/news/young-people-coronavirus-new-york-city-percentage-patients-covid-19-symptoms-dying-hospitalizations/&quot;&gt;hospitalized.&lt;/a&gt;  For any given young person, it might be safer to try to stay home and avoid getting the disease until a vaccine or treatment can be developed than to risk deliberate exposure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An animal study prior to a human one can identify what the infectious dose of the virus is, as well as what the minimum active dose to produce an immune response and protection against reinfection is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover, it seems that it would be safer, and not obviously less effective, to treat healthy subjects with convalescent serum or inactivated virus rather than live virus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[1]Liu, Yang, et al. “Viral dynamics in mild and severe cases of COVID-19.” &lt;em&gt;The Lancet Infectious Diseases&lt;/em&gt; (2020).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[2]Zou, Lirong, et al. “SARS-CoV-2 viral load in upper respiratory specimens of infected patients.” &lt;em&gt;New England Journal of Medicine&lt;/em&gt; 382.12 (2020): 1177-1179.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[3]Kam, Kai-qian, et al. “A Well Infant with Coronavirus Disease 2019 with High Viral Load.” &lt;em&gt;Clinical Infectious Diseases&lt;/em&gt; (2020).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[4]To, Kelvin Kai-Wang, et al. “Temporal profiles of viral load in posterior oropharyngeal saliva samples and serum antibody responses during infection by SARS-CoV-2: an observational cohort study.” &lt;em&gt;The Lancet Infectious Diseases&lt;/em&gt; (2020).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[5]Wilder-Smith, Annelies, et al. “Asymptomatic SARS coronavirus infection among healthcare workers, Singapore.” &lt;em&gt;Emerging infectious diseases&lt;/em&gt; 11.7 (2005): 1142.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[6]Chu, Chung-Ming, et al. “Initial viral load and the outcomes of SARS.” &lt;em&gt;Cmaj&lt;/em&gt; 171.11 (2004): 1349-1352.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[7]Lu, Yen-Ta, et al. “Viral load and outcome in SARS infection: the role of personal protective equipment in the emergency department.” &lt;em&gt;The Journal of emergency medicine&lt;/em&gt; 30.1 (2006): 7-15.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[8]Lau, Joseph TF, et al. “Probable secondary infections in households of SARS patients in Hong Kong.” &lt;em&gt;Emerging infectious diseases&lt;/em&gt; 10.2 (2004): 236.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[9]Yang, Zhi-yong, et al. “A DNA vaccine induces SARS coronavirus neutralization and protective immunity in mice.” &lt;em&gt;Nature&lt;/em&gt; 428.6982 (2004): 561-564.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[10]Xiong, Sheng, et al. “Immunogenicity of SARS inactivated vaccine in BALB/c mice.” &lt;em&gt;Immunology letters&lt;/em&gt; 95.2 (2004): 139-143.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[11]Takasuka, Naomi, et al. “A subcutaneously injected UV-inactivated SARS coronavirus vaccine elicits systemic humoral immunity in mice.” &lt;em&gt;International immunology&lt;/em&gt; 16.10 (2004): 1423-1430.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[12]Subbarao, Kanta, et al. “Prior infection and passive transfer of neutralizing antibody prevent replication of severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus in the respiratory tract of mice.” &lt;em&gt;Journal of virology&lt;/em&gt; 78.7 (2004): 3572-3577.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[13]See, Raymond H., et al. “Comparative evaluation of two severe acute respiratory syndrome (SARS) vaccine candidates in mice challenged with SARS coronavirus.” &lt;em&gt;Journal of general virology&lt;/em&gt; 87.3 (2006): 641-650.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[14]Cameron, Mark J., et al. “Lack of innate interferon responses during SARS coronavirus infection in a vaccination and reinfection ferret model.” &lt;em&gt;PLoS one&lt;/em&gt; 7.9 (2012).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[15]Bao, Linlin, et al. “Reinfection could not occur in SARS-CoV-2 infected rhesus macaques.” &lt;em&gt;bioRxiv&lt;/em&gt; (2020).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[16]Roberts, Anjeanette, et al. “Immunogenicity and protective efficacy in mice and hamsters of a β-propiolactone inactivated whole virus SARS-CoV vaccine.” &lt;em&gt;Viral immunology&lt;/em&gt; 23.5 (2010): 509-519.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[17]Wernery, Ulrich, Susanna KP Lau, and Patrick CY Woo. “Middle East respiratory syndrome (MERS) coronavirus and dromedaries.” &lt;em&gt;The Veterinary Journal&lt;/em&gt; 220 (2017): 75-79.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[18]Hemida, Maged Gomaa, et al. “Longitudinal study of Middle East respiratory syndrome coronavirus infection in dromedary camel herds in Saudi Arabia, 2014–2015.” &lt;em&gt;Emerging microbes &amp;amp; infections&lt;/em&gt; 6.1 (2017): 1-7.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[19]Addie, D. D., and O. Jarrett. “Use of a reverse-transcriptase polymerase chain reaction for monitoring the shedding of feline coronavirus by healthy cats.” &lt;em&gt;Veterinary Record&lt;/em&gt; 148.21 (2001): 649-653.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[20]Heckert, R. A., et al. “Epidemiologic factors and isotype-specific antibody responses in serum and mucosal secretions of dairy calves with bovine coronavirus respiratory tract and enteric tract infections.” &lt;em&gt;American journal of veterinary research&lt;/em&gt; 52.6 (1991): 845-851.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[21]Omer, Saad B., Preeti Malani, and Carlos del Rio. “The COVID-19 Pandemic in the US: A Clinical Update.” &lt;em&gt;JAMA&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="covid-19" /><category term="lit-review" /><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">CPAP for COVID-19</title><link href="https://srconstantin.github.io/2020/04/05/CPAP-for-COVID19.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="CPAP for COVID-19" /><published>2020-04-05T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-04-05T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://srconstantin.github.io/2020/04/05/CPAP-for-COVID19</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://srconstantin.github.io/2020/04/05/CPAP-for-COVID19.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/mercedes-CPAP.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;shield&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As COVID-19 sweeps the world, there are more patients who have severe cases of respiratory failure than there are ICU beds and ventilator machines to help them breathe.  Doctors have been forced to find creative solutions to the crisis – and they’re turning to a technique called CPAP, which is gaining credence as a treatment for severe COVID-19.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CPAP stands for continuous positive airway pressure, and refers to a device that blows a steady stream of air into the lungs (which may be supplemented with extra oxygen) to help patients who have moderate difficulty breathing independently.  It may reduce the need for ventilation, which is crucial when ventilators are scarce.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-020-00926-4&quot;&gt;Nature&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; reports on a team of clinicians from the UK, China, and Italy using a CPAP device, now being used in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bmj.com/content/368/bmj.m1294.full&quot;&gt;clinical trials&lt;/a&gt; at University College London Hospital.  These machines have been widely used in Italy, where they prevented the need for ventilation in 50% of patients. (A prospective study on the effectiveness of CPAP on COVID-19 in Italy is &lt;a href=&quot;https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/show/NCT04307459?term=covid-19+cpap&amp;amp;draw=2&quot;&gt;ongoing&lt;/a&gt;; in &lt;a href=&quot;https://srconstantin.github.io/2020/03/22/non-invasive-ventilation.html&quot;&gt;China&lt;/a&gt;, non-invasive ventilation such as CPAP successfully avoided the need for invasive ventilation in 77% of treated patients.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cnn.com/2020/03/30/tech/mercedes-f1-breathing-aid-coronavirus/index.html&quot;&gt;Mercedes F1&lt;/a&gt; engineers designed the device, which can be quickly mass produced and has been recommended for use by the UK Medicines and Healthcare Products Regulatory Agency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the US, Elon Musk has been &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.teslarati.com/tesla-elon-musk-cpap-ventilator-coronavirus/&quot;&gt;donating CPAP/BiPAP machines&lt;/a&gt; to hospitals; these machines can be converted into ventilators if necessary, or used as-is on patients with milder respiratory distress to prevent them needing invasive (and scarce) mechanical ventilation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CPAP and BiPAP for respiratory disorders are &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npr.org/sections/health-shots/2020/03/27/822211604/cpap-machines-were-seen-as-ventilator-alternatives-but-could-spread-covid-19&quot;&gt;controversial&lt;/a&gt;, as they are considered “aerosol generating procedures” that could spread particles of the virus around. However, evidence suggests that these non-invasive ventilation procedures actually produce &lt;a href=&quot;https://srconstantin.github.io/2020/03/22/contagion-risk-from-NIV.html&quot;&gt;droplets rather than aerosols&lt;/a&gt;, larger particles which usually land less than one meter from the patient, and CPAP masks don’t leak much exhaled air (less than a meter away from the patient) when the mask is a good fit, as a 2019 Hong Kong study &lt;a href=&quot;https://sci-hub.tw/10.1183/13993003.02339-2018&quot;&gt;showed.&lt;/a&gt;  ResMed, the leading manufacturer of CPAP machines, recommends that they be used in COVID-19 patients only when caregivers have protective equipment such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.resmed.com/en-us/covid-19/?utm_source=vanity&amp;amp;utm_medium=print&amp;amp;utm_content=covid19&amp;amp;utm_campaign=covid19-update&quot;&gt;N95 masks and eye protection.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even the WHO’s guidance on treatment of &lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.who.int/iris/bitstream/handle/10665/331446/WHO-2019-nCoV-clinical-2020.4-eng.pdf&quot;&gt;COVID-19 &lt;/a&gt;acknowledges a place for CPAP and BiPAP machines.  The document recommends patients be given non-invasive ventilation only in monitored circumstances where they can be intubated and placed on mechanical ventilation if their condition worsens, but it still offers CPAP as an option, particularly in the case of children in low-resource settings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The FDA’s new guidance on COVID-19 clears the way for modifying respiratory support devices without needing to get the modifications separately approved, including the use of CPAP machines in COVID-19: __&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;_Wherever possible, health care facilities should use FDA-cleared conventional/standard full- featured ventilators when necessary to support patients with respiratory failure, or a device subject to an Emergency Use Authorization (EUA), if any. However, to help ensure the availability of the greatest possible number of devices for this purpose, and as described in more detail below, FDA does not intend to object to limited modifications to the indications, claims, functionality, or to the hardware, software, or materials of FDA-cleared devices used to support patients with respiratory failure or respiratory insufficiency, without prior submission of a premarket notification under section 510(k) of the FD&amp;amp;C Act and 21 CFR 807.81 , for the duration of the declared public health emergency…_


_Examples of circumstances where FDA currently believes a modification would not create such undue risk include:_


_1) The use of powered emergency ventilators and anesthesia gas machines for patients needing mechanical ventilation; _


_2) The use of ventilators outside their cleared environment of use (for example, use of a ventilator in a health care facility when it is only cleared for use at home or during transport);_


_3) **The use of devices indicated for sleep apnea (including noncontinuous ventilators delivering continuous positive airway pressure (CPAP) or bilevel positive airway pressure (BiPAP)) to treat patients with respiratory insufficiency, provided that appropriate design mitigations are in place to minimize aerosolization**;_


_4) The use of oxygen concentrators for primary supply when medically necessary and clinically appropriate._
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s time to give CPAP for COVID-19 a second look. Yes, it can disperse air, but the evidence that it spreads disease particles is ambiguous at best; and the risks can be mitigated by using full-face masks with good seals, using filters on the exhaust vents, and making sure medical staff have adequate protective equipment. We know from past pandemics and some early retrospective data in COVID-19 that a sizable fraction of patients improve on CPAP alone without intubation; in a world where invasive ventilation may not be an option for an overwhelmed healthcare system, that means saving lives.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="covid-19" /><category term="lit-review" /><summary type="html"></summary></entry></feed>