<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-03-20T22:44:10-06:00</updated><id>/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Sarah Constantin</title><subtitle>Math/machine learning person currently trying to solve aging and make sense of our world. Founder, www.daphnia-labs.com and www.thelri.org.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Non Invasive Ventilation</title><link href="/2020/03/20/non-invasive-ventilation.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Non Invasive Ventilation" /><published>2020-03-20T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2020-03-20T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>/2020/03/20/non-invasive-ventilation</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2020/03/20/non-invasive-ventilation.html">&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Layout: tag_post
title: Non-Invasive Ventilation Outcomes
tags: [covid-19, lit-review]
–&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Does non-invasive ventilation (providing oxygenated air under pressure to patients who have trouble breathing) prevent the need for intubation and being placed on a mechanical ventilator?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This matters because, in the event of a shortage of ICU beds and mechanical ventilators, if a device that can be used at home can reduce a COVID-19 patient’s risk of needing to be hospitalized, it could save potentially millions of lives in the US.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Results&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I looked at a total of 19 randomized controlled trials, comprising 3979 patients in all, which directly compared either a type of non-invasive ventilation, high-flow nasal cannula therapy, or both to standard oxygen therapy, for adult patients with acute respiratory failure who had not received surgery or intubation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using a t-test to compare the risk of intubation between treatments, I found that there was a 15% rate of intubation in the non-invasive ventilation (NIV) group vs. a 30% rate of intubation in the standard therapy group, for a significant (p &amp;lt; 0.0001) difference in intubation risk; the NIV group had half the odds of failing and needing intubation, compared with standard oxygen mask therapy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Likewise, there was a significant (p &amp;lt; 0.0001) difference in the mortality risk; the NIV group had a mortality risk of 15% at follow-up, while the standard treatment group had a mortality rate of 24%, a relative risk of 0.625.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was no significant reduction in risk of mortality or intubation between standard and high flow nasal cannula (HFNC) therapy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When restricted to studies of community-acquired pneumonia, NIV still significantly (p &amp;lt; 0.0001) reduces risk of intubation and significantly (p &amp;lt; 0.0001) reduces the risk of mortality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Non-Invasive Ventilation Vs. Standard Treatment&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In an RCT of 236 patients admitted to the hospital for exacerbations of COPD, randomized to either standard treatment or non-invasive ventilation (NIV), NIV was associated with a reduced (RR = 0.56, p = 0.038) risk of needing intubation.[1]  Even in the NIV group, 15% of patients still needed intubation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a randomized study of 82 elderly patients with chronic pulmonary disease, randomized to receive NIV or standard therapy, the patients receiving NIV had a 7.3% chance of needing intubation, while the patients on standard (oxygen) therapy had a 63% chance; this is a significant difference (RR  = 0.11, p &amp;lt; 0.001).  The mortality rate at one year was also significantly lower in the NIV group (RR = 0.83, p = 0.014).[3]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a study (the 3CPO trial)  of 1069 patients with severe cardiogenic pulmonary edema, randomized to CPAP, non-invasive ventilation, or standard oxygen therapy, there was no significant difference in the rate of mortality (9.8% vs 9.5%) or intubation (2.8% vs 2.9%) between groups.[4]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a randomized multicenter study over 19 hospitals in China, patients given NIV for exacerbations of COPD were much less likely than patients given standard therapy, (4% vs 15%, RR = 0.13, p = 0.002) but there was no significant difference in in-hospital mortality.[5]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a randomized study of 40 patients with acute lung injury, assigned either NIV or standard oxygen therapy, the proportion of patients requiring intubation was much lower in the NIV group (5% vs 37%: RR = 0.14, p = 0.02) and there was a nonsignificant trent (p = 0.09) towards lower mortality in the NIV group.[6]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a randomized study of 40 patients with acute cardiogenic pulmonary edema, assigned to either NIV or standard oxygen therapy, intubation was required in fewer patients in the NIV group (5% vs 33%, RR = 0.15, p = 0.037).[7]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a study of 85 patients with acute exacerbations of COPD, randomized to standard therapy or noninvasive ventilation, significantly fewer of the NIV patients (26% vs 74%, RR = 35%, p &amp;lt; 0.001) were intubated.  NIV patients also had fewer complications, shorter hospital stays, and lower in-hospital mortality (9% vs 29%, RR = 0.31, p =0.02).[9]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a randomized study of 105 patients with severe hypoxemic respiratory failure, randomized to NIV or standard oxygen therapy, NIV reduced the need for intubation (13% vs 29%, RR = 0.45, p = 0.01) and ICU mortality (9% vs 21%, RR = 0.42, p = 0.028).[13]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the FLORALI trial, which randomized 310 patients with acute hypoxemic respiratory failure to high-flow nasal cannula oxygen (HFNC), non-invasive ventilation, or standard oxygen therapy through a nonrebreather mask, there was no significant difference in intubation rate between the three groups; but in the patient subgroup with the worst blood oxygenation levels, the high-flow oxygen group had a significantly lower intubation rate (35% vs 53%, RR = 0.66, p = 0.009).  Mortality at 90 days was also significantly lower in the high-flow nasal cannula group (12% vs 23%, RR = 0.52, p= 0.02).[14]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the HOT-ER trial of 302 patients with hypoxia and tachypnea presenting to an emergency department, randomly assigned to standard oxygen therapy or HFNC therapy, there was no significant difference between mortality and intubation rates, but this may have been because both groups had low rates of intubation (0.6% and 2.2%) and in-hospital mortality (9.1% and 8.0%).[15]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the HIGH trial of 776 adult immunocompromised patients with acute hypoxemic respiratory failure, randomized to HFNC or standard oxygen, there was no significant difference between groups in mortality at day 28 (35.6% vs 36.1%) or intubation rate (38.7% vs 43.6%).[17]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a trial of 376 immunocompromised patients, mostly with cancer, randomized to either non-invasive ventilation or standard oxygen therapy, there was no significant difference in intubation rates between the two groups (24.1% vs 27.3%) and no significant difference in 28-day mortality (24.1% vs 27.3%)[19]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a randomized study of 31 patients with acute respiratory failure, randomized to non-invasive ventilation or standard oxygen, significantly fewer patients in the NIV group needed intubation (31% vs 73%, RR = 0.42, p = 0.03), but there was no significant difference in mortality.[20]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 52 immunosuppressed patients with acute respiratory distress, pulmonary infiltrates, and fever, randomized either to NIV or standard oxygen, fewer patients in the NIV group required intubation (46% vs 76%, RR = 0.6, p = 0.03) and fewer patients in the NIV died in the hospital (50% vs 81%, RR= 0.58, p = 0.02).[21]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a randomized study of 60 patients with acute cardiogenic pulmonary edema, assigned to CPAP, BIPAP, or standard oxygen, patients assigned to CPAP were more likely to survive to hospital discharge (100% vs 70 % vs 75%, p = 0.02).  There was no difference in the number of patients needing intubation: (20% vs 5% vs 5%).[22]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In an Indian study of 40 patients with acute exacerbations of COPD randomized to NIV or standard oxygen, the NIV group had a lower rate of intubation (15% vs 60%, RR = 0.25, p = 0.003) but there was no significant difference in hospital mortality (15% vs 20%).[23]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pneumonia-Specific Studies&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a randomized study of 56 cases of severe pneumonia, assigned to NIV (with a CPAP mask) or standard oxygen therapy, significantly fewer patients in the NIV group (21% vs 61%, RR = 34%, p = 0.007) met criteria for intubation.  There was no significant difference in hospital death rates or 2-month survival rates.[8]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a randomized study of 81 patients with acute respiratory failure due to pneumonia, randomized to NIV with a CPAP or standard oxygen therapy with a Venturi mask, significantly fewer from the CPAP group met criteria for intubation (15% vs 63%, RR = 0.24, p &amp;lt; 0.001), and the CPAP group showed a faster and greater oxygenation response.[12]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Types of Non-Invasive Ventilation Compared&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a meta-analysis comprising 290 patients with cardiogenic pulmonary edema, there was no significant difference in either hospital mortality or intubation risk between CPAP and BIPAP machines. [2]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 36 patients with acute hypercapnic pulmonary edema randomized to either non-invasive pressure support ventilation or CPAP, there was no significant difference in intubation rates or mortality rates.[18]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 83 women with ARDS randomized to NIV either with a face mask or a helmet, the rate of intubation was significantly lower with the helmet (18% vs 63%, RR = 0.29, p &amp;lt; 0.001) and the 90-day mortality rate was also significantly lower (34% vs 56%, RR= 0.6, p = 0.02).  The helmet may be more effective because it prevents air leak.[16]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Out-of-Hospital Non-Invasive Ventilation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a randomized study of 54 patients with acute respiratory failure given standard oxygen therapy or NIV by paramedics, significantly fewer of the NIV patients needed to go to the ICU (36% vs 65%, RR = 0.55, p &amp;lt; 0.05) and there was a nonsignificant trend towards fewer NIV patients needing to be intubated (4% vs 23%, p = 0.1) [10]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Past Pandemics&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;20-30% of patients with respiratory failure due to H1N1 influenza were given NIV, but 70-80% of those later needed intubation and invasive ventilation.[11]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the SARS outbreak, a Hong Kong hospital that treated patients with respiratory failure through non-invasive ventilation first had 21% of patients need invasive mechanical ventilation, while 41% of SARS patients in a ventilation-first hospital were on mechanical ventilation.  Mortality was also lower in the NIV hospital: 9.5% vs 25.1%.[24]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusion&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It looks like, for acute respiratory distress in general and pneumonia specifically, non-invasive ventilation can help prevent it from getting so bad that intubation is necessary.  NIV reduces both intubation risk and mortality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This means that, in a world where ICUs are overrun, there’s a good chance that a home non-invasive ventilation device could save lives for people with COVID-19.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, we have correlational evidence that non-invasive ventilation can work for acute respiratory failure outside a hospital setting, and can reduce mortality in a past coronavirus epidemic (SARS). This points in favor of the possibility of non-invasive ventilation being useful in COVID-19.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because non-invasive ventilation aerosolizes the virus, it is not safe in hospital settings, where it could spread COVID-19.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If someone has the option of going to a hospital in the event of severe respiratory failure due to COVID-19, it’s better to go immediately than to try to self-treat at home; intubation can’t be done safely by an untrained person, and about 40% of severe COVID-19 cases require intubation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, if hospitals are unavailable, as seems quite likely if the US doesn’t drastically increase its supply of medical personnel and equipment, a home non-invasive ventilation device may be a distinct improvement over either home oxygen supplementation or, obviously, no treatment at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[1]Plant, Paul Keith, J. L. Owen, and M. W. Elliott. “Non-invasive ventilation in acute exacerbations of chronic obstructive pulmonary disease: long term survival and predictors of in-hospital outcome.” Thorax 56.9 (2001): 708-712.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[2]Ho, Kwok M., and Karen Wong. “A comparison of continuous and bi-level positive airway pressure non-invasive ventilation in patients with acute cardiogenic pulmonary oedema: a meta-analysis.” Critical care 10.2 (2006): R49.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[3]Nava, Stefano, et al. “Non-invasive ventilation in elderly patients with acute hypercapnic respiratory failure: a randomised controlled trial.” Age and ageing 40.4 (2011): 444-450.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[4] Gray, A. J., et al. “A multicentre randomised controlled trial of the use of continuous positive airway pressure and non-invasive positive pressure ventilation in the early treatment of patients presenting to the emergency department with severe acute cardiogenic pulmonary oedema: the 3CPO trial.” Health technology assessment (Winchester, England) 13.33 (2009): 1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[5]Collaborative Research Group of Noninvasive Mechanical Ventilation for Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease. “Early use of non-invasive positive pressure ventilation for acute exacerbations of chronic obstructive pulmonary disease: a multicentre randomized controlled trial.” Chinese medical journal 118.24 (2005): 2034.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[6]Zhan, Qingyuan, et al. “Early use of noninvasive positive pressure ventilation for acute lung injury: a multicenter randomized controlled trial.” Critical care medicine 40.2 (2012): 455-460.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[7]Masip, Josep, et al. “Non-invasive pressure support ventilation versus conventional oxygen therapy in acute cardiogenic pulmonary oedema: a randomised trial.” The Lancet 356.9248 (2000): 2126-2132.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[8]Confalonieri, Marco, et al. “Acute respiratory failure in patients with severe community-acquired pneumonia: a prospective randomized evaluation of noninvasive ventilation.” American Journal of Respiratory and Critical Care Medicine 160.5 (1999): 1585-1591.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[9]Wedzicha, J. A. “Noninvasive ventilation for acute exacerbations of chronic obstructive pulmonary disease.” Thorax 51.Suppl 2 (1996): S35.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[10]Roessler, Markus Sören, et al. “Early out-of-hospital non-invasive ventilation is superior to standard medical treatment in patients with acute respiratory failure: a pilot study.” Emerg Med J 29.5 (2012): 409-414.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[11]Winck, João Carlos, and Anabela Marinho. “Non-invasive ventilation in acute respiratory failure related to 2009 pandemic influenza A/H1N1 virus infection.” Critical Care 14.2 (2010): 1-2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[12]Brambilla, Anna Maria, et al. “Helmet CPAP vs. oxygen therapy in severe hypoxemic respiratory failure due to pneumonia.” Intensive care medicine 40.7 (2014): 942-949.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[13]Ferrer, Miquel, et al. “Noninvasive ventilation in severe hypoxemic respiratory failure: a randomized clinical trial.” American journal of respiratory and critical care medicine 168.12 (2003): 1438-1444.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[14]Frat, Jean-Pierre, et al. “High-flow oxygen through nasal cannula in acute hypoxemic respiratory failure.” New England Journal of Medicine 372.23 (2015): 2185-2196.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[15]Jones, Peter G., et al. “Randomized controlled trial of humidified high-flow nasal oxygen for acute respiratory distress in the emergency department: the HOT-ER study.” Respiratory care 61.3 (2016): 291-299.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[16]Patel, Bhakti K., et al. “Effect of noninvasive ventilation delivered by helmet vs face mask on the rate of endotracheal intubation in patients with acute respiratory distress syndrome: a randomized clinical trial.” Jama 315.22 (2016): 2435-2441.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[17] Azoulay, Elie, et al. “Effect of high-flow nasal oxygen vs standard oxygen on 28-day mortality in immunocompromised patients with acute respiratory failure: the HIGH randomized clinical trial.” Jama 320.20 (2018): 2099-2107.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[18]Bellone, Andrea, et al. “Noninvasive pressure support ventilation vs. continuous positive airway pressure in acute hypercapnic pulmonary edema.” Intensive care medicine 31.6 (2005): 807-811.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[19]Del Sorbo, Lorenzo, et al. “Non-invasive ventilation in immunocompromised patients with acute hypoxemic respiratory failure.” Journal of thoracic disease 8.3 (2016): E208.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[20]Kramer, Naomi, et al. “Randomized, prospective trial of noninvasive positive pressure ventilation in acute respiratory failure.” American journal of respiratory and critical care medicine 151.6 (1995): 1799-1806.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[21]Hilbert, Gilles, et al. “Noninvasive ventilation in immunosuppressed patients with pulmonary infiltrates, fever, and acute respiratory failure.” New England Journal of Medicine 344.7 (2001): 481-487.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[22]Crane, S. D., et al. “Randomised controlled comparison of continuous positive airways pressure, bilevel non-invasive ventilation, and standard treatment in emergency department patients with acute cardiogenic pulmonary oedema.” Emergency medicine journal 21.2 (2004): 155-161.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[23]Khilnani, Gopi C., et al. “Non-invasive ventilation for acute exacerbation of COPD with very high PaCO2: a randomized controlled trial.” Lung India: official organ of Indian Chest Society 27.3 (2010): 125.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[24]Yam, L. Y., et al. “Non-invasive versus invasive mechanical ventilation for respiratory failure in severe acute respiratory syndrome.” Chin Med J 118.17 (2005): 1413-1421.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Layout: tag_post title: Non-Invasive Ventilation Outcomes tags: [covid-19, lit-review] –</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Oxygen Supplementation 101</title><link href="/2020/03/19/oxygen-supplementation-101.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Oxygen Supplementation 101" /><published>2020-03-19T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2020-03-19T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>/2020/03/19/oxygen-supplementation-101</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2020/03/19/oxygen-supplementation-101.html">&lt;p&gt;COVID-19 causes shortness of breath and in severe cases requires artificial ventilation.    
There is a shortage of mechanical ventilators in hospitals, and a shortage of medical personnel to treat patients with severe COVID-19, so there’s widespread interest in contributing to open source ventilation projects. For these efforts to be effective, though, we need to understand what COVID-19 patients need in terms of ventilators and other supplemental oxygen sources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;COVID-19 Symptoms and Clinical Guidelines&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most patients who go to a hospital for COVID-19 have pneumonia or infection of the lungs, which is visible on a chest X-ray.  A large fraction (41.3%) receive supplemental oxygen therapy; a smaller fraction (5%) needed to be admitted to the ICU, and 6.1% needed mechanical ventilation.[1] &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ARDS&lt;/strong&gt; 
Severe cases of COVID-19 result in developing Acute Respiratory Distress Syndrome (ARDS). Fluid builds up in the lungs; the lungs may collapse; blood oxygen drops; and mechanical ventilation is required. Merely providing air with a higher oxygen content than room air isn’t enough; pressure needs to be administered to keep the alveoli open.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Oxygen Therapy: Bag Mask&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/bagvalvemask.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;bagvalvemask&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A bag valve mask is used in emergencies and for temporary ventilation while preparing for intubation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=1goz1l28kUQ&quot;&gt;Here&lt;/a&gt; is a doctor demonstrating how to use a bag valve mask.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Oxygen Therapy: Nasal Cannulas and Simple Masks&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/nasalcannula.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;nasalcannula&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/simplefacemask.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;simplefacemask&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When a patient has difficulty getting enough oxygen but can breathe on their own, they get oxygen therapy. That is, they’re given a supply of air with an increased concentration of oxygen, but without any additional pressure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oxygen can be administered non-invasively through a nasal cannula or a simple mask. This can safely be done outside a hospital setting.  Oxygen concentrators are standard to keep in the home for people with chronic lung conditions like emphysema and COPD. Simple oxygen masks are regularly used by non-medical rescue personnel like firefighters and lifeguards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Oxygen Concentrators&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To produce a supply of filtered, high-oxygen air from room air, you need an oxygen concentrator, which removes nitrogen from the air through filters. This oxygen-enriched air can then be provided to the patient through a mask or nasal cannula.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Home oxygen concentrators are available with a prescription.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oxygen Therapy: Non-Rebreather Masks
A non-rebreather mask is an oxygen mask with a sealed bag that prevents inhalation of room air or previously exhaled air, which allows for higher concentrations of oxygen to be administered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Oxygen Therapy: High Flow Nasal Cannula&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/HFNC.png&quot; alt=&quot;HFNC&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[5]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A high flow nasal cannula provides a higher flow of oxygen, and warms and humidifies it, so that it is less irritating to mucous membranes and easier for the patient to breathe.  The higher flow also increases ventilation and causes the patient to rebreathe less exhaled air, which increases ventilation (the elimination of CO2).  It also provides a small amount of PEEP (positive end-expiratory pressure, keeping the alveoli open) which can be helpful for patients whose lungs are collapsing due to respiratory failure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;High-flow nasal cannulas will aerosolize the COVID-19 virus, infecting everyone nearby. They are not allowed in hospitals for COVID-19 because they spread disease. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Noninvasive Ventilation: CPAP and BIPAP&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/CPAP.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;CPAP&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/BIPAP.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;BIPAP&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CPAP machines keep the patient’s airway open by forcing air continuously through a mask.  It is usually used for sleep apnea and other conditions that cause difficulty breathing.  The patient must initiate all breaths, but has additional pressure support to keep the airway and alveoli open.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;BIPAP machines work the same way, except that they have two pressure settings instead of just one: a higher pressure for inhalation and a lower one for exhalation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;BIPAPs and CPAPs can be used safely at home and don’t need medical supervision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like high-flow nasal cannulas, CPAP and BIPAP machines aerosolize the COVID-19 virus and are an infection risk for everyone nearby.  They are not allowed in hospitals for COVID-19; they will spread disease.  (Source: doctor interview.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Invasive Mechanical Ventilation for ARDS&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the alveoli can’t stay open on their own, supplemental oxygen isn’t enough; this is when the patient needs to be intubated and placed on a ventilator that can provide enough pressure to keep the airway and alveoli open, so gas exchange can occur and the blood can be oxygenated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pressure on a mechanical ventilator needs to be precisely calibrated to the patient. Too much pressure and the lung can tear; too little, and the patient’s blood will fill with CO2 and not get enough oxygen. This is one reason why patients need to be placed on ventilators by trained experts (typically ICU nurses, doctors, and respiratory therapists). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another reason is that intubation is an invasive procedure; an endotracheal tube is inserted into the airway, which requires sedatives and anaesthetics to avoid pain and the gag reflex. Mistakes with aiming the tube or dosing the medications could cause permanent injury or death.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/laryngoscope.jpg = 300x&quot; alt=&quot;laryngoscope&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You don’t want an untrained person sticking this blade down someone’s throat!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How Effective Is Outpatient Oxygen Therapy or Noninvasive Ventilation?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are multiple projects underway to produce open-source oxygen therapy or non-invasive ventilation devices for COVID-19. Are these projects actually useful?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They’re not going to be used in hospitals, because of the risk that they’ll spread infection.  But could they still be useful for patients self-quarantining at home, in a context where ICU beds and ventilators are scarce?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words, how often do patients who need non-invasive ventilation go on to need invasive ventilation, how long does it take before they need to escalate to invasive ventilation, and how helpful is non-invasive ventilation in preventing the need for invasive ventilation?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 310 patients with acute respiratory failure in ICUs (typically due to pneumonia), randomized to standard oxygen therapy in a nonrebreather mask, oxygen therapy in a high flow nasal cannula, or noninvasive ventilation, there was no significant difference in the intubation rate (30-40% needed intubation within 4 days).  However, the high-flow oxygen group had a significantly lower 90-day mortality rate than the other two groups: 7% of the high-flow oxygen group died within 90 days, compared to 28% on standard oxygen and 23% on non-invasive ventilation.  The high-flow oxygen group also had significantly better blood oxygenation and spent fewer days on ventilators than the other two groups.[3]  High-flow nasal cannulas were also more effective than conventional oxygen masks at avoiding the need for repeated ventilation, in another randomized trial.[4]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, suppose you’re a person with respiratory failure, but you have an oxygen mask, CPAP, BIPAP, or high-flow nasal cannula at home. 40% of the time or so, your noninvasive home equipment is going to fail and you’ll need to be intubated. Usually this happens quite urgently; if you need to take an ambulance to get to the hospital it might be too late.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since NIV (noninvasive ventilation) does not significantly reduce the risk of needing intubation, it’s strictly inferior to have people on NIV at home (where they may not be able to get to a doctor in time if their condition worsens) than to have them on conventional nonrebreather oxygen masks in the hospital (where they can get an emergency intubation if their condition worsens.) The improved mortality stats for high-flow nasal cannula are probably swamped by the increased risk associated with being at home and not being able to get an emergency intubation quickly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, building open-source CPAP, BIPAP, or high-flow nasal cannulas is not valuable for COVID-19, in any world where ICUs and ventilators are still available.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the situation deteriorates so badly that most people can’t go to ICUs at all, non-invasive home ventilation may be better than nothing, but it’s not the top priority for increasing capacity to respond to the COVID-19 pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Existing Ventilator Design Projects&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve seen a lot of links to projects to design open-source ventilators to handle the current ventilator shortage. Many of these are automated bag masks, or CPAPs, which aren’t recommended for use in hospitals because they spread COVID-19; and they won’t work on the more severe cases of respiratory distress anyway.  Only two projects that I found, the Pandemic Ventilator and the Flometrics project, are explicitly trying to match the specifications of the type of mechanical ventilators found in ICUs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.3dprintingmedia.network/covid-19-3d-printed-valve-for-reanimation-device/&quot;&gt;3D-Printed Venturi Valve&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A hospital in Italy, after being unable to source valves for Venturi oxygen masks, got emergency supplies from a local 3D printing company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While this is a worthwhile project, it is of course just a single part for an oxygen mask, not a ventilator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=1t2t8d8xtD0&amp;amp;feature=youtu.be&quot;&gt;Auto Bag Ventilator&lt;/a&gt; – a Rice University engineering student designed a low-cost, automatically pumping bag ventilator for low resource settings.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a type of ventilator for very short term use, in first aid emergencies. It is not a substitute for a mechanical ventilator because there is no way to calibrate the pressure exactly.  (A mechanical ventilator needs to be accurate to within at least 0.001 psi.)[6]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is also not safe for COVID-19 in hospital settings because of the risk of aerosolization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/OpenSourceVentilators/comments/fgrsdg/pandemic_ventilator_project_requirements/&quot;&gt;Flometrics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a low cost mechanical ventilator based on a Shopvac, designed by one of the patent holders for the Phillips Espirit ventilator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the kind of thing that &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; designed to substitute for the mechanical ventilators used in ICUs, and could be very valuable if it works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jcl5m1/ventilator&quot;&gt;Low-Cost Open Source Ventilator&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a design for a modified CPAP machine for non-invasive ventilation.  
That means it’s not going to be usable in hospitals because of disease spread issues, and ~40% of the time, a person with COVID would need to escalate to intubation within a few days anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://web.mit.edu/2.75/projects/DMD_2010_Al_Husseini.pdf&quot;&gt;Low-Cost Portable Mechanical Ventilator&lt;/a&gt; – this is an MIT student project. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This too is a bag ventilator equipped with a mechanical pump; therefore, not usable for COVID-19 in hospital settings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.metrictechnologies.com/&quot;&gt;Metric Technologies&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They &lt;a href=&quot;https://helpwithcovid.com/projects/24&quot;&gt;claim&lt;/a&gt; to have a low-cost (&amp;lt;$300) ventilator design and are capable of training staff and deploying the devices. Unclear what type of device this is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.onebreathventilators.com/&quot;&gt;OneBreath Ventilators&lt;/a&gt;
 
This Stanford-founded company is working to develop a low cost ICU ventilator for use in the developing world. These could be suitable for severe COVID-19 cases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They are not yet available for sale but they are open to outreach,  info@onebreathventilators.com.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://gitlab.com/TrevorSmale/OSV-OpenLung&quot;&gt;OpenLung&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another motorized Ambu-bag. Again, these are not designed to be used for more than 10 hours at a time &amp;amp; won’t work for ARDS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/document/d/1Dz7eMgXowFBtBA_0PKzfAXweHnNMbGlIAXPshCbI2Vk/edit#&quot;&gt;Pandemic Ventilator&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a project to build a mechanical ventilator for ARDS. They also have a blog at &lt;a href=&quot;https://panvent.blogspot.com/&quot;&gt;https://panvent.blogspot.com/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the type of thing that could potentially be valuable for severe cases of COVID-19; it’s meant to substitute for the type of mechanical ventilators that are currently in short supply. Any new, rapidly developed machine will not meet regulatory approval standards in the US, but in emergencies or in countries with less stringent laws, an unapproved (but functional) machine may be better than nothing.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This ventilator is designed to be deployed in hospitals, specifically in rural Latin America.  It is not for home care.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@brucefenton/we-need-ventilators-we-need-you-to-help-build-them-30805e5ee2ea&quot;&gt;The Ventilator Project&lt;/a&gt;
	This is a group from NECSI, the New England Complex Systems institute, working to
	a.) increase production of ventilators by existing manufacturers
	b.) work on open-source plans for building ventilators for hospitals
	c.) regulatory efforts to approve hospitals to use emergency ventilators&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Current Shortages of Oxygen &amp;amp; Breathing Equipment&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oxygen Concentrators
Oxygen concentrators were in short supply even before the pandemic – a June 2019 article notes that half of people who use portable oxygen supplies had problems with broken equipment or inadequate supplies of oxygen.[7]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ventilators
In a pandemic crisis, New York State is predicted to be short 15,783 mechanical ventilators a week at the peak of the outbreak.[8]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Evidence that Non-Invasive Ventilation Spreads COVID-19&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An ICU in Hong Kong gave guidance against bag mask ventilators:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We recommend avoiding bag mask ventilation for as long as possible; and optimising preoxygenation with nonaerosol-generating means. Methods include the bed-up-head-elevated position, airway manoeuvres, use of a positive end expiratory pressure valve, and airway adjuncts. If manual bagging is required, we suggest gentle ventilation via a supraglottic device instead of bag mask ventilation.[9]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The same guidelines were implemented by the largest acute care hospital in Singapore:
Infection prevention entails reducing aerosol-generating procedures (i.e., airway manipulation, face mask ventilation, open airway suctioning, patient coughing) as far as possible…Non-invasive positive pressure ventilation and high flow nasal cannulae such as the transnasal humidified rapid-insufflation ventilatory exchange should be avoided to reduce the risk of viral aerosolization…Venturi masks should be avoided as they may aerosolize the virus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[1]Guan, Wei-jie, et al. “Clinical characteristics of coronavirus disease 2019 in China.” New England Journal of Medicine (2020).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[2]Murthy, Srinivas, Charles D. Gomersall, and Robert A. Fowler. “Care for Critically Ill Patients With COVID-19.” JAMA (2020).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[3]Frat, Jean-Pierre, et al. “High-flow oxygen through nasal cannula in acute hypoxemic respiratory failure.” New England Journal of Medicine 372.23 (2015): 2185-2196.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[4]Hernández, Gonzalo, et al. “Effect of postextubation high-flow nasal cannula vs conventional oxygen therapy on reintubation in low-risk patients: a randomized clinical trial.” Jama 315.13 (2016): 1354-1361.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[5]Papazian, Laurent, et al. “Use of high-flow nasal cannula oxygenation in ICU adults: a narrative review.” Intensive Care Medicine 42.9 (2016): 1336-1349.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[6]http://www.ardsnet.org/files/ventilator_protocol_2008-07.pdf&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[7]https://www.statnews.com/2019/06/14/access-lifesaving-oxygen-therapy/&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[8]https://www.nytimes.com/2020/03/17/nyregion/ny-coronavirus-ventilators.html&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[9]Cheung, Jonathan Chun-Hei, et al. “Staff safety during emergency airway management for COVID-19 in Hong Kong.” The Lancet Respiratory Medicine (2020).&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="covid-19" /><category term="lit-review" /><summary type="html">COVID-19 causes shortness of breath and in severe cases requires artificial ventilation.     There is a shortage of mechanical ventilators in hospitals, and a shortage of medical personnel to treat patients with severe COVID-19, so there’s widespread interest in contributing to open source ventilation projects. For these efforts to be effective, though, we need to understand what COVID-19 patients need in terms of ventilators and other supplemental oxygen sources.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">COVID-19 Risks For Young People</title><link href="/2020/03/16/COVID-19-young-people-risks.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="COVID-19 Risks For Young People" /><published>2020-03-16T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2020-03-16T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>/2020/03/16/COVID-19-young-people-risks</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2020/03/16/COVID-19-young-people-risks.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/N95mask.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;maskpic&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This analysis was commissioned by the Open Philanthropy Project and shared with their permission.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-the-true-case-fatality-rate-for-young-people&quot;&gt;What Is The True Case Fatality Rate For Young People?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Chinese data says 0.2% for ages 0-39 but this may be misleading for a several reasons:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;a.) only includes data up to Feb. 11
b.) may be biased upwards, because the overall case fatality rate was higher in the early days of the Wuhan outbreak while hospitals were overwhelmed
c.) may be biased upwards, because cases that had only mild symptoms might never have been reported or tested
d.) may be biased downwards, not counting the higher death rates from people who never got access to a hospital and so never got diagnosed&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/CSSEGISandData/COVID-19/tree/master/csse_covid_19_data&quot;&gt;Johns Hopkins data&lt;/a&gt;, which is current up to March 4th, the overall/cumulative case fatality rate in China is 3.4%, and the case fatality rate outside China is 1.8%.  This lower number may be more predictive of the current case fatality rate since the case fatality rate inside China has dropped over time, from 17% (in January) to under 2% by Feb. 20th, as more individuals have been tested and hospital resources have been mobilized.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The overall case recovery rate from the Johns Hopkins data is 54% worldwide but only 8% outside China. This may simply indicate recency; according to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.who.int/docs/default-source/coronaviruse/who-china-joint-mission-on-covid-19-final-report.pdf&quot;&gt;WHO&lt;/a&gt;, mild cases take 2 weeks to recover and severe cases take 3-6 weeks. Or it may indicate that countries outside China are not following up with confirmed cases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jama/article-abstract/2762130&quot;&gt;Chinese data&lt;/a&gt; on 72,314 cases of COVID-19 (which gives ages for cases, unlike the global data) only about 10% of cases were in people younger than 30, and only 1% of the deaths among confirmed cases were in people younger than 30.  27% of the cases were in people younger than 40, and 2.5% of the deaths. While reporting of cases of coronavirus can be expected to be biased to more severe cases, there is no systematic reason why cases of similar severity would be more or less likely to be reported based on age, so the 10% case risk seems like a credible estimate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A sample of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thelancet.com/journals/landig/article/PIIS2589-7500(20)30026-1/fulltext&quot;&gt;509 cases&lt;/a&gt; whose demographic information was reported in the media, including cases from outside China, found that 12% of cases were younger than 30, which is similar to the Chinese figure; the sample included no deaths in patients younger than 30.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;South Korea may be our best possible estimate of the true case fatality rate, since it is a developed country with a very extensive testing program of more than &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2020-03-04/south-korea-tests-hundreds-of-thousands-to-fight-virus-outbreak&quot;&gt;140,000 people&lt;/a&gt; to date. It has &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.businessinsider.com/coronavirus-new-cases-soar-south-korea-slow-in-china-2020-3&quot;&gt;6088 cases and 37 deaths&lt;/a&gt;, or a 0.6% case fatality rate.  In Korea, 35.2% of all cases were in people under 30, and 46.2% under age 40, but there have been no fatalities for people under 30.  There was 1 death of a person age 30-39, out of 693 cases in that age range.  This suggests that in a country with extensive testing for COVID-19, young people are more likely to contract the disease than the Chinese numbers would suggest, but no more likely to die of it. In fact, Korean case fatality rates across all age groups are lower than the corresponding Chinese case fatality rates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cbsnews.com/live-updates/coronavirus-outbreak-death-toll-us-infections-latest-news-updates-2020-03-04/&quot;&gt;“At least 11 people have died of the COVID-19 disease in the U.S., all but one of them in Washington state, and most of them from a single nursing home in the Seattle area. The other death occurred in California, just outside Sacramento. The coronavirus has been confirmed in 17 states so far.”&lt;/a&gt;, according to a news article on March 5.  Since the number of US cases to date is currently 211, this gives a whopping 5% case fatality rate, but this number is likely inaccurate since the US is barely testing at all for COVID-19.  We don’t have enough data on US cases to get a believable US-specific case fatality rate by age group, but the pattern of deaths is consistent with the story that the disease is much more deadly for the elderly than for younger people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Conclusion: the true case fatality rate for Americans under age 40 is likely to be LOWER than the Chinese estimate of 0.2%.  The proportion of COVID-19 cases under age 40 is likely to be HIGHER than the Chinese estimate of 27%, perhaps as high as the Korean estimate of 46%.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;chronic-non-fatal-sequelae-of-covid-19&quot;&gt;Chronic Non-Fatal Sequelae of COVID-19&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neurological manifestations of COVID-19 may be relatively common: 78 out of 214 patients in one &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.medrxiv.org/content/medrxiv/early/2020/02/25/2020.02.22.20026500.full.pdf]&quot;&gt;hospital study&lt;/a&gt;, or 36%, had neurological symptoms, most commonly muscle injury and loss of consciousness, but also a few cases of stroke.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was a &lt;a href=&quot;https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s00415-020-09773-9&quot;&gt;case study&lt;/a&gt; of a 62-year-old man in Wuhan who presented with oculomotor nerve palsy and whose throat swab tested positive for 2019-nCOV.  Other possible causes of the nerve palsy, such as stroke, diabetic neuropathy, brain tumor, and Guillain-Barre syndrome were ruled out, so his doctors hypothesized that the virus caused the nerve failure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.xinhuanet.com/english/2020-03/05/c_138846529.htm&quot;&gt;case&lt;/a&gt; of COVID-19, in Beijing, was confirmed to contain the virus in cerebrospinal fluid, in the first case of viral encephalitis due to COVID-19.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is evidence that COVID-19 can infiltrate the central nervous system, and evidence that neurological symptoms are common during COVID-19 infection, but it’s not as yet clear whether the neurological symptoms are usually caused by the virus infiltrating nerve and muscle tissue or whether they’re caused by other organ damage, by the treatments for COVID-19, or by the body’s inflammatory response.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SARS, an earlier coronavirus epidemic, did frequently cause chronic sequelae.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Out of 233 formerly hospitalized SARS survivors in one &lt;a href=&quot;https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jamainternalmedicine/fullarticle/415378&quot;&gt;follow-up study&lt;/a&gt;, 27.1% met the criteria for chronic fatigue syndrome, 40% had a psychiatric disorder, and 40% mentioned a chronic fatigue problem. Only 3%, by contrast, had a psychiatric disorder before contracting SARS; this indicates that SARS may have caused psychiatric problems. (Relatedly, the most common psychiatric disorder was post-traumatic stress disorder.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Johnny_Chan9/publication/228620287_Severe_Acute_Respiratory_Syndrome_SARS_A_Brief_Review_With_Exploration_of_the_Outcomes_Prognostic_Factors_and_Sequelae/links/541157e90cf2f2b29a412dc0.pdf&quot;&gt;Half of SARS survivors&lt;/a&gt;  who were hospitalized experienced mild reduction in pulmonary function even 3 months after being discharged from the hospital.  30-45% of survivors had bone necrosis in their hips or knees; this may be a consequence of the long-term use of corticosteroids in treating SARS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SARS has been found in one &lt;a href=&quot;https://academic.oup.com/clinchem/article/49/12/2108/5642159&quot;&gt;case&lt;/a&gt; to infiltrate the cerebrospinal fluid, causing seizures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neurological symptoms are &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ant-tnsjournal.com/Mag_Files/14-3/14-3_p113.pdf&quot;&gt;uncommon but possible&lt;/a&gt; in SARS; out of 664 SARS patients in Taiwan, eight (1%) were found to have neurological disorders: neuropathy, myopathy, and rhabdomyolysis.  5 out of 206 SARS patients in Singapore, or 2%, had strokes, while none had risk factors for strokes; this may be because SARS, like some other viral infections, causes a hypercoagulable state. These neuromuscular symptoms look similar to the ones observed in COVID-19.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s reasonable to suppose that COVID-19, like SARS, can increase the risk of stroke and cause chronic nerve disorders in perhaps a few percent of patients.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though we don’t yet know whether COVID-19 causes chronic fatigue, there is a plausible mechanism: virus-induced immune dysfunction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;COVID-19 patients have &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.medrxiv.org/content/medrxiv/early/2020/02/20/2020.02.18.20024364.full.pdf&quot;&gt;diminished T-cell levels&lt;/a&gt;, and more severe cases have a larger reduction.  75% of 522 COVID-19 patients from a Chinese hospital had low T-cell levels, with the lowest levels found in the oldest patients. Inflammatory cytokine levels (IL-6, IL-10, and TNF-alpha) was negatively correlated with T-cell count and positively correlated with the severity of the disease. This is consistent with the “cytokine storm” phenomenon, in which a spike in inflammatory cytokines is responsible for the Acute Respiratory Distress Syndrome (ARDS) and Multiple Organ Dysfunction Syndrome (MODS) which occur in severe and deadly cases of respiratory infections, including COVID-19, SARS, and H5N1.  This opens the door to a mechanism by which COVID-19 could cause long-term immune system dysregulation, if T-cell levels don’t go back to normal after a patient recovers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In conclusion, it seems at least somewhat likely that a high percentage of hospitalized COVID-19 patients, like SARS patients, may develop a chronic fatigue syndrome, and that a low percentage may develop chronic nerve damage.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-likely-are-young-people-to-have-severehospital-worthy-cases-of-covid-19&quot;&gt;How Likely Are Young People To Have Severe/Hospital-Worthy Cases of COVID-19?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once again, let’s look at South Korea, as a baseline for a country with an outbreak of COVID-19 and extensive testing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Korean officials said that &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cnn.com/2020/03/09/asia/south-korea-coronavirus-intl-hnk/index.html&quot;&gt;only about 10%&lt;/a&gt; of coronavirus patients had cases severe enough to need hospitalization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In China, &lt;a href=&quot;https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jama/article-abstract/2762130&quot;&gt;19% of confirmed cases&lt;/a&gt; were “severe” or “critical”, but this number is likely higher than the true figure, due to limited access to test kits and mild cases of COVID-19 going unreported.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.medrxiv.org/content/10.1101/2020.03.03.20028423v1.full.pdf&quot;&gt;study&lt;/a&gt; of 391 patients in Shenzhen, China, 0 cases of COVID-19 among those &amp;lt;30 years old were “severe” (in need of mechanical ventilation, in a state of septic shock or multiple organ failure, or other serious criteria) and only 1% of those aged 30-39 were severe; overall, there was an 0.6% rate of severe cases among cases younger than age 40.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rate of contracting COVID-19 among close contacts of confirmed cases, however, was relatively constant across age groups – 7-8%, including among children ages 0-9.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a study of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.journalofinfection.com/article/S0163-4453(20)30101-8/fulltext&quot;&gt;262 patients in Beijing&lt;/a&gt;, however, 8% of cases younger than age 44 were “severe”, compared to 41% of cases older than age 65 and 17% of cases age 45-64.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a study of 221 confirmed COVID-19 cases in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.medrxiv.org/content/10.1101/2020.03.02.20030452v1.full.pdf&quot;&gt;Wuhan&lt;/a&gt;, 8% of patients age 44 and under were classified as “severe”,  compared to 29% of cases aged 45-64 and 39% of cases over age 65.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In all three Chinese cities, this comes to a rate of 3% of cases in under-40 or under-45 patients being severe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we assume the age distribution of severity is the same in Korea vs. China, but that the Korean rate of severe illness is the correct one, this gives us 3/19*10 = 1.6% probability of a person under 40 having a severe case, given that they have been infected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;bottom-lines&quot;&gt;Bottom Lines&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Young people exposed to COVID-19 are as likely as old people to become infected and contagious. Avoiding infection is prosocial, as it prevents passing COVID-19 to more vulnerable people.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Young (&amp;lt;40) people who contract COVID-19 have a very low death rate, 0.1-0.2%.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Young (&amp;lt;40) people who contract the virus have a low (~1.6%) chance of having a “severe” case, requiring mechanical ventilation or other intensive care.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, if hospital beds are unavailable, people with severe cases who don’t go to the hospital will likely die.  So this 1-2% severe case rate translates to more like a 1-2% fatality rate if a young person catches the disease when hospitals are over capacity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Whether severe or mild, a high proportion of confirmed cases of SARS had chronic psychiatric and fatigue symptoms after recovery from acute illness, and it’s possible that similar problems may arise from COVID-19.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;COVID-19 can infect the cerebrospinal fluid, and a few percent of severe SARS cases had chronic neurological problems, so perhaps a similar number of severe COVID-19 cases might have chronic neurological sequelae.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="lit-review" /><category term="covid-19" /><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Potentially Effective Drugs for COVID-19</title><link href="/2020/03/16/COVID-19-drugs.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Potentially Effective Drugs for COVID-19" /><published>2020-03-16T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2020-03-16T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>/2020/03/16/COVID-19-drugs</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2020/03/16/COVID-19-drugs.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/coronavirus.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;virus&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Name&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Evidence Type&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Remdesivir&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;In-vitro effective against COVID-19;  Effective (esp. prophylactically) against MERS in macaque monkeys; More effective than lopinavir/ritonavir against MERS in mice&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Chloroquine&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;In-vitro effective against COVID-19; In-vitro effective against SARS; &lt;strong&gt;Not&lt;/strong&gt; in-vitro effective against MERS in monocyte-derived cells&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Cinanserin&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;In-vitro effective against COVID-19;In-vitro effective against SARS&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Lopinavir/Ritonavir&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Human retrospective evidence of effectiveness in MERS and SARS but &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; COVID-19; In-silico predicted effectiveness against COVID-19&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Indinavir&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;In-silico predicted effectiveness against COVID-19;  &lt;strong&gt;Not&lt;/strong&gt; effective in-vitro against SARS&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Thalidomide&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Improved symptoms in one case study of severe COVID-19&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Remdesivir&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An in-silico study of HIV drugs for their docking affinity to a key enzymes in the COVID-19 virus – RdRp, the main protein for RNA replication – found an almost perfect match in the antiviral drug remdesivir, suggesting it might be a good candidate drug for treating COVID-19.[3]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remdesivir also inhibits the COVID-19 virus in vitro.[7]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remdesivir is effective at reducing the clinical signs of infection and viral load from MERS coronavirus in rhesus macaque monkeys; if given prophylactically, it prevents the monkeys from getting any disease symptoms at all and keeps their viral loads negligible.[10]  In mice, remdesivir is more effective than lopinavir/ritonavir in improving pulmonary function and reducing viral load from MERS infection.[11]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 3 US patients treated with remdesivir, 2 patients saw fever drop immediately upon receiving the drug (the third didn’t have a fever); one was able to go off supplemental oxygen; all recovered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remdesivir is currently in trials in China and the US for COVID-19.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Chloroquine&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A brief summary document [1] claims that clinical trials in China including over 100 patients have found the antimalarial drug chloroquine phosphate “superior to control treatment” in treating COVID-19 pneumonia and shortening disease course. The paper provided no documentation about experimental methods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chloroquine also inhibits the replication of the COVID-19 virus in vitro,[7] as well as the SARS coronavirus in vitro.[9]  It does not inhibit the MERS coronavirus in vitro in a culture of monocyte-derived cells.[13]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chloroquine frequently causes gastrointestinal side effects (diarrhea, nausea), problems with visual acuity, insomnia, and paresthesias (prickling skin sensations.)[15]  More rarely, chloroquine can cause psychiatric symptoms like depression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cinanserin&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cinanserin is a serotonin receptor antagonist which was also found to inhibit the replication of the SARS virus in vitro. Cinanserin inhibits the activity of COVID-19’s main protease in vitro, and inhibits the virus’s replication in vitro.[5]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cinanserin also inhibits the replication of the SARS coronavirus in vitro.[14]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lopinavir/Ritonavir&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lopinavir/Ritonavir is a combination of two antiviral drugs approved for the treatment of HIV.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In one Korean patient, aged 54, with mild pneumonia and a diagnosis of COVID-19, treatment with the antiviral drug combination of lopinavir and ritonavir diminished coronavirus load to undetectable levels.[2]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lopinavir/Ritonavir was also used by the Thai infectious disease team to successfully treat patients with severe COVID-19.[3]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lopinavir also had a high binding affinity to the COVID-19 protein 3CL-PRO in an in-silico screen of 3118 FDA-approved drugs.[4]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lopinavir is a protease inhibitor, effective in vitro against the main protease of the SARS coronavirus; it also has in vitro antiviral activity against SARS-CoV. Lopinavir reduced viral load and clinical symptoms of the MERS coronavirus in mice and marmoset monkeys.[6]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In human SARS cases, treatment with lopinavir was associated with lower death rate (2.3%) and intubation rate (0%) compared with standard treatment (11% and 15.6% respectively.). Another case-control study of SARS found a lower rate of ARDS in patients treated with lopinavir (2.4% vs 28.8%).  [6]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A retrospective study of 40 patients found that post-exposure prophylaxis including lopinavir/ritonavir reduced the spread of MERS-CoV by 40% in healthcare workers.  However, a retrospective study of 134 COVID-19 patients found no significant difference between lopinavir/ritonavir treatment, Abidol treatment, and control treatment.[6]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Indinavir&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indinavir is an antiviral drug used to treat HIV.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In an in-silico screen of the binding affinity of 3118 FDA-approved drugs to several key enzymes of the COVID-19 virus, the highest-affinity drug for the protease PDB-6LU7 was indinavir, an antiviral drug approved for use against HIV.  (Even higher affinity were human proteins that closely resemble the enzyme’s ligand – ACE2 and GHRP-2.)  Indinavir also had a high binding affinity to another COVID-19 protein, 3CL-PRO.[4]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, in an in-vitro test against the SARS coronavirus, indinavir did not block replication.[12]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Thalidomide&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thalidomide is an immunomodulatory drug used to treat cancers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A 45-year-old woman with a severe case COVID-19, with fever, pneumonia, dyspnea, nausea, and vomiting, improved and went into remission after being treated with thalidomide, which has anti-inflammatory effects, reducing the “cytokine storm” responsible for the severe symptoms of COVID-19.[7]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[1]Gao, Jianjun, Zhenxue Tian, and Xu Yang. “Breakthrough: Chloroquine phosphate has shown apparent efficacy in treatment of COVID-19 associated pneumonia in clinical studies.” BioScience Trends (2020).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[2]Lim, Jaegyun, et al. “Case of the Index Patient Who Caused Tertiary Transmission of COVID-19 Infection in Korea: the Application of Lopinavir/Ritonavir for the Treatment of COVID-19 Infected Pneumonia Monitored by Quantitative RT-PCR.” Journal of Korean medical science 35.6 (2020).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[3]Chang, Yu-Chuan, et al. “Potential therapeutic agents for COVID-19 based on the analysis of protease and RNA polymerase docking.” (2020).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[4]Contini, Alessandro. “Virtual screening of an FDA approved drugs database on two COVID-19 coronavirus proteins.” (2020).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[5]Jin, Zhenming, et al. “Structure-based drug design, virtual screening and high-throughput screening rapidly identify antiviral leads targeting COVID-19.” bioRxiv (2020).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[6]Yao, Tian‐Tian, et al. “A Systematic Review of Lopinavir Therapy for SARS Coronavirus and MERS Coronavirus–A Possible Reference for Coronavirus Disease‐19 Treatment Option.” Journal of Medical Virology (2020).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[7]Wang, Manli, et al. “Remdesivir and chloroquine effectively inhibit the recently emerged novel coronavirus (2019-nCoV) in vitro.” Cell research 30.3 (2020): 269-271.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[8]Chen, Chengshui, et al. “Thalidomide combined with low-dose glucocorticoid in the treatment of COVID-19 Pneumonia.” (2020).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[9]Vincent, Martin J., et al. “Chloroquine is a potent inhibitor of SARS coronavirus infection and spread.” Virology journal 2.1 (2005): 69.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[10]de Wit, Emmie, et al. “Prophylactic and therapeutic remdesivir (GS-5734) treatment in the rhesus macaque model of MERS-CoV infection.” Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences (2020).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[11]Sheahan, Timothy P., et al. “Comparative therapeutic efficacy of remdesivir and combination lopinavir, ritonavir, and interferon beta against MERS-CoV.” Nature Communications 11.1 (2020): 1-14.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[12]Tan, Emily LC, et al. “Inhibition of SARS coronavirus infection in vitro with clinically approved antiviral drugs.” Emerging infectious diseases 10.4 (2004): 581.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[13]Cong, Yu, et al. “MERS-CoV pathogenesis and antiviral efficacy of licensed drugs in human monocyte-derived antigen-presenting cells.” PloS one 13.3 (2018).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[14]Chen, Lili, et al. “Cinanserin is an inhibitor of the 3C-like proteinase of severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus and strongly reduces virus replication in vitro.” Journal of virology 79.11 (2005): 7095-7103.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[15]Martins, Antonio Camargo, et al. “Side effects of chloroquine and primaquine and symptom reduction in malaria endemic area (Mâncio Lima, Acre, Brazil).” Interdisciplinary perspectives on infectious diseases 2015 (2015).&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="lit-review" /><category term="covid-19" /><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Intro Post</title><link href="/2020/03/13/intro-post.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Intro Post" /><published>2020-03-13T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2020-03-13T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>/2020/03/13/intro-post</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2020/03/13/intro-post.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/rembrandtfaust.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;faust&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been blogging in various places for nearly a decade, but I’ve never actually hosted my own site, or consolidated all my writing in one place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But now it’s past time for me to start taking my writing/blogging more seriously.&lt;br /&gt;
I want it to be searchable and all in one place, and I want to own my own data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thankfully, Github now makes hosting easy, and supports the blogging framework Jekyll.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I always find it nice when people are transparent about their process, so I’ll share  mine: it’s taken me about 3-4 days to get Jekyll working and my posts migrated from all my old blogs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On this site I’ll be aggregating my old posts from &lt;a href=&quot;https://srconstantin.wordpress.com&quot;&gt;Otium&lt;/a&gt;, my &lt;a href=&quot;https://srconstantin.posthaven.com&quot;&gt;Posthaven site&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://parentingwithevidence.wordpress.com&quot;&gt;Parenting with Evidence&lt;/a&gt;, and the now defunct Hourglass Bio.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll cross-promote posts on &lt;a href=&quot;//https://twitter.com/s_r_constantin&quot;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt; (where my handle is @s_r_constantin) and, of course, you can subscribe using RSS.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="blog-meta" /><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Tangled Thinking 2 – Motivated Cognition and Its Opposite</title><link href="/2020/02/24/tangled-thinking-2.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Tangled Thinking 2 -- Motivated Cognition and Its Opposite" /><published>2020-02-24T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-02-24T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>/2020/02/24/tangled-thinking-2</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2020/02/24/tangled-thinking-2.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/escherlizards.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;lizards&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Motivated cognition is the state of emotionally needing to believe something is true, whether it actually is true or not. 
I’ve found that a good kinaesthetic metaphor for motivated cognition is pressure.  If you’re forcing things with your mind – if you’re going “it’s GOT to be this way, or ELSE” – then you aren’t actually open to the truth being whatever it might happen to be.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Defensiveness, anxiety, revulsion, despair, eagerness to please or to be acceptable, can motivate you to believe that the convenient and pleasant thing is true – or that the awful worst-case scenario is – or both at once (e.g. anxiety can make you fear the worst but flinch from it and profess the best-case scenario.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s not motivated cognition for &lt;em&gt;motivation to be involved in cognition&lt;/em&gt;.  We think most clearly, in fact, when we’re motivated to do so; for instance, someone who stands to make money by making the correct prediction will be more motivated to be correct than someone who’s merely having a conversation.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, I think motivation is &lt;em&gt;essential&lt;/em&gt; to all the words we use to talk about thinking well  – rationality, wisdom, objectivity, science, empiricism, common sense, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/tMhEv28KJYWsu6Wdo/kensh&quot;&gt;“Looking”&lt;/a&gt;, etc. These words get corrupted by connotations of smugness, coldness, superiority, or authoritarianism, and new words have to be continually invented to point at the same thing the old words were intended to point at.  The &lt;em&gt;thing itself&lt;/em&gt; is, perhaps, best described as “thinking in the way everyone naturally does when they actually care about the object of their thought.”  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you care about the thing in the real world, you will not want to be wrong about it; a delusion, however pleasant, won’t give you what you want.  You still can be wrong about it, of course, but your incentives are to be as correct as you can be.  A certain amount of pretense and posturing and game-playing may drop away suddenly when, for instance, you find your child’s safety is at stake; suddenly it is vitally important to get real.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Of course, phrases like “get real”, “be sensible”, “be reasonable”, often are used to mean “shut up and do what I tell you”, which is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; the thing. A person who Actually Cares about getting something done may often be perceived as an unreasonable or irrational person, because she is doing something that doesn’t meet with everyone’s approval.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s something related about words like “literally”, “truly”, “actually”, “really”, “very”, “honestly” – and it’s telling that over time language evolves to make them all used as words for emphasis instead of denoting literal exact truth.  It’s hard to find a way to phrase in words “I’m pointing at reality now” as opposed to pointing at a model of reality, or playing a game with language, or speaking ‘in character’ as the persona you want to embody right now.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notions like “rationality” are attempts to encourage people to think and speak literally rather than performatively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seems like sort of a mistake to present them as a specialized discipline to be taught rather than a stance to be adopted that most people naturally have by default from time to time. Doing science doesn’t actually involve going through The Scientific Method as you’re taught in elementary school; but while there may not really be a Scientific Method, there is definitely a scientific mindset. It’s the same mindset you have automatically when you’re curious. 
 
If you try to codify how people think when they’re being curious, it winds up sounding like nothing at all.  “Just, y’know, think! Look! Care! Try!”
Or it comes across as condescending: “Most people go through life never actually trying! You should actually try!” There’s not much content to this, but the “actually” is gesturing at something: the rubber meeting the road, the moon and not the pointing finger. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By contrast, motivated cognition is being motivated to have certain cognitions, inside your head, rather than being motivated to seek outcomes out in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s kind of weird that we have this feature at all. Why would we have evolved to self-deceive? If an apparently self-destructive behavior is common, this cries out for explanation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why do we (often) care more about the insides of our heads than what’s going on outside them?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="tangled-thinking" /><category term="cog-psych" /><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Tangled Thinking 1 – Mental Objects, Contradictions, Reconciliation</title><link href="/2020/02/21/tangled-thinking-1.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Tangled Thinking 1 -- Mental Objects, Contradictions, Reconciliation" /><published>2020-02-21T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-02-21T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>/2020/02/21/tangled-thinking-1</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2020/02/21/tangled-thinking-1.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/ascending-and-descending-escher.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;ascending&quot; /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Mental Objects&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s call a &lt;strong&gt;mental object&lt;/strong&gt; anything that you’re aware of, anything that is in your conscious mind. A sense perception, a feeling, a thought, a concept, anything that is under the spotlight of your consciousness at a given moment. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tautologically, if you have &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; access to something in the world, it must be a mental object; it must enter your perception.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So how do you even know there &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; an external world?  Why isn’t it “all in your mind”?  What’s even the difference between a totally imaginary world playing out in your consciousness, and a “real world” that’s “out there”?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Without being knowledgeable about the history of philosophy and the many people who have attempted to answer this question, I think there’s a pretty straightforward way to solve this problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Difference Detection&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the things your mind can do is ask the question “same or different?” about two mental objects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Same or different?” can apply on multiple meta-levels.  You can say “do these propositions contradict?”  You can say “do these motives conflict?”  You can say “does my observation match my prediction?” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The “evidence” for this proposition is just that you can try it out in your own mind and see if it works.  It’s also analytically necessary that this be true if we believe that people have goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any kind of optimizing behavior can be viewed as optimizing to minimize a distance or difference between the desired and actual situation. Which means you need to be able to detect differences. If we are goal-achieving machines, we must also be difference-detecting machines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover, there are some computational models that fit psychophysics data quite well, like &lt;a href=&quot;http://citeseerx.ist.psu.edu/viewdoc/summary?doi=10.1.1.15.2644&quot;&gt;Waltz Filtering&lt;/a&gt;, where you can view the process of visually parsing a line drawing, as an optimization problem where we try to minimize the number of inconsistencies in interpretations of the drawing as representing a 3-d object. (Unreconcilable inconsistencies lead to &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Impossible_object&quot;&gt;impossible figures&lt;/a&gt;, where we “see” the figure as representing a 3-d form locally, but then can’t extend that same interpretation consistently to the whole figure.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Psychophysics data also tells us that our sensory perceptions are keyed to differences, not absolute magnitudes; far more people have relative pitch than absolute pitch, for instance, and our color perceptions are relative to background and lighting, not absolute.  Detecting “same or different?” seems to be more “primitive” or “fundamental” an operation in the brain than detecting “how much?”  In many cases, at least, it seems that we have “difference detectors” and construct absolute measurements out of those, rather than having “absolute magnitude detectors” and computing differences by subtracting them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Resolving Contradictions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“A” and “Not A” is a flat contradiction – an impossibility.  The mind boggles. It cannot be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But not all differences, of course, are impossibilities. It’s possible to notice that a dress has fabric in two different colors, and this doesn’t slow us down a bit.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What happens is a kind of “going meta”, I think.  You say “oh, no problem: it’s A here, and not-A there.”  Distinction by dividing up the mental world. “Hey, A and not-A, you can share.”  Now there is no contradiction and everything is hunky-dory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or, you can explain away one half of the contradiction: “oh, I only believed not-A because I was misled by such-and-such; now I can safely discard it as a mistake.”  Again, no problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or, you can reframe A and not-A so they are both parts of a whole, or not really opposites after all.  There are a lot of things you can do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Essentially what you’re doing is handling an &lt;a href=&quot;https://intelligence.org/files/OntologicalCrises.pdf&quot;&gt;ontological crisis&lt;/a&gt;.  You resolve an apparent contradiction by adding some complexity to your mental world, such that both apparently contradicting mental objects are compatible and explainable (or explain-away-able) by your new, expanded view of the world.  It’s the process of noticing that the blind men were seeing different parts of the elephant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There seems to be a contradiction, but really, if you shake it all around, if you learn more, if you do some trial and error, you can get into a new configuration where the knot untangles and it all makes sense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is what “thinking” is, I believe. Messing around with your mental objects until apparent contradictions resolve.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And this tells us what it means to believe in an external “world.”  It means that you believe that your space of mental objects will come to include things that it does not yet include, but which recontextualize today’s apparent contradictions so they make sense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It means &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=GIol4aENNEw&quot;&gt;“we will understand it better by and by.”&lt;/a&gt;  Everything has an explanation; everything came from the same world.  If we took a wide enough view, everything would make sense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is a kind of faith, but a very minimal sort – the faith that you live in an intelligible universe, that ultimately you can make more and more sense of things.  Or the stance of trying to see things from the perspective of how they would look once you had made sense of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Solving Problems Is What Brains Like Doing&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lulie Tanett likes to write about how “reason is fun” and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.reasonisfun.com/blog/problems-are-good/&quot;&gt;“problems are good”&lt;/a&gt; – that humans literally enjoy the process of problem-solving.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you think about it, most of our “play” is puzzle-solving – trying to achieve an objective despite an apparent obstacle, or trying to make sense of something initially confusing. Videogames are puzzles even when they’re not “puzzle games”. Sports are puzzles.  Even reading or watching a work of fiction, or listening to music, gets much of its “fun” from a dance between predictability and surprise (and ultimate resolution of the apparent mystery or discordance.) Many of the things we do for no reason other than enjoyment are problem-solving activities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have an instinctive desire to tug on problems in attempts to solve them. That doesn’t mean all problems are perceived as unpleasant.  Sometimes the “problem-solving” happens faster than we can be aware of it; sometimes the process itself is pleasurable. Only sometimes do we have a negative feeling around the problem, and it’s not merely because the problem exists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Suffering = Problems Metastasizing&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just having a problem – your conscious mind includes both “A” and “Not A” – doesn’t necessarily cause suffering. But if you then go “there IS a contradiction” and “but there CAN’T be a contradiction”, then things start to get worse. Or “I have mixed feelings” but “but I MUSTN’T have mixed feelings”, or “this is hard” and “but it SHOULDN’T be hard”, and so on. Somehow a problem can result in, not an attempt at resolution, but more problems!  More contradictory beliefs, which vibrate against each other, and make more and more friction in your mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think this is usually what’s going on when something really bothers us.  Have you ever noticed that sometimes a big life problem stops being upsetting, not when it goes away, but when you find something you can do about it?  You flip out of “bemoaning and denying that the issue is there at all”, focus instead on some constructive activity toward solving the issue, and suddenly it gets easier? Because now all you have to cope with is the issue itself, not the exhausting “is it real or isn’t it”, “should I admit it hurts or tough it out”, internal debates. You now have one less problem to solve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have problems about problems, issues about issues, etc, it gets much harder to deal with them. These are psychological truisms: negative emotions are worse if you’re ashamed of feeling them; abuse is harder to recover from if everyone around you insists it’s not real; dealing with misfortune is harder if you’re still in denial about it.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having a “meta-problem” means having an internal contradiction around the concept of the problem itself.  “This problem exists” and “this problem doesn’t exist” battle in your head. Trying to believe in a contradiction, trying to do the literally impossible, maintaining the conviction that you should be able to believe contradictions or do the impossible – all of these are ways of making meta-problems out of problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Buddhist concept of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ta%E1%B9%87h%C4%81&quot;&gt;tanha&lt;/a&gt; is usually translated as “craving” or “desire”, but it literally means “fuel” and is associated with clinging or persistence, trying to make mental states stick around.  If I were to try to map it to this model, I’d say that tanha is the mental motion of returning to a contradiction or a knot in the mind, and trying to will it to not be a knot, thereby creating a bigger meta-knot.  It’s what you do when you remind yourself of a frustration in a way that makes it more and more frustrating.  You keep the contradiction bouncing back and forth, louder and louder – it IS, but it SHOULDN’T BE, and moreover nothing should BE HOW IT SHOULDN’T, but some people told me I should ACCEPT THINGS AS THEY ARE, but I DON’T LIKE THAT…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That “outward spiral” makes it harder and harder to resolve the problem at the root of the whole thing, because every time you notice it, it activates all the other meta-problems.  I think this is the structural underpinning of what we experience as negative emotions, “touchy subjects”, and “sore spots.”  They’re wounds that defend themselves from healing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, if we believe in a world, we must believe that this process too comes from the world, that there is a reason why problems sometimes grow their own defenses. But it’s tricky and deserves exploration at length.  You’re looking at a process that doesn’t “want” to be looked at.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="tangled-thinking" /><category term="cog-psych" /><summary type="html">Mental Objects</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Aging Interventions from Older Publications that Deserve a New Look</title><link href="/2020/01/15/aging-interventions-from-old-papers.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Aging Interventions from Older Publications that Deserve a New Look" /><published>2020-01-15T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-01-15T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>/2020/01/15/aging-interventions-from-old-papers</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2020/01/15/aging-interventions-from-old-papers.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why Read Old Papers?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These days, from what I’m told by knowledgeable people, there’s a fairly tight feedback loop between current aging research and the biotech industry. When a new, major aging-related paper comes out, there are people seriously evaluating whether they can start a company around it. 
But that isn’t necessarily true when it comes to old research. There’s no automatic means by which old papers “go viral.”  There are no conferences (that I know of) where people call their colleagues’ attention to remarkable, decades-old results that haven’t received follow-up investigation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think old papers deserve a second look, for a few reasons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1.) Often a result that had little interpretability or applicability in the past can benefit from contemporary tools. 
Let’s say, twenty years ago researchers found a way to extend life in rats – but it was a surgical operation that would be too invasive or risky to try on healthy humans. And maybe that was the end of that research direction.  But now we have lots of new options! We can take tissue samples with and without the intervention, and look at gene and protein expression, even down to the individual cell level. We can identify genetic modifications or drug targets that could be used to simulate the intervention in a safer, more targeted way.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2.) Looking at old papers reduces some of the biases that come from looking at the latest, most-cited papers.
The volume of scientific publications is increasing at an exponential rate, up to 4% a year.[1] &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/morepapers.png&quot; alt=&quot;morepapers&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the reliability of the average publication has probably decreased. If there are indeed “diminishing returns to science” in recent decades, as Patrick Collison and Michael Nielsen argue [2], with roughly constant rates of important discoveries (as rated by experts) and flat economic productivity (a measure that we’d expect to correlate with technological progress) despite exponentially growing numbers of scientists, publications, and dollars devoted to science, then the quality of the average paper, scientist, or dollar allocated to research must have gone down. In that case, a randomly chosen older paper should be more trustworthy than a newer paper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One might counter that the new papers that get the most attention aren’t randomly chosen – they’re the highly cited papers, or the papers in prominent journals. Maybe the average paper has gotten worse, but the average is being pulled down by junk papers in journals so low-quality and obscure that barely anybody reads them; so, perhaps, the typical new paper that a colleague (or your twitter feed) brings to your attention is no less credible than a comparable old paper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think that optimistic outlook is doubtful; in fact, articles in prestigious (high-impact-factor) journals are more likely than average to be retracted, and many measures of research reliability anticorrelate with impact factor, implying that articles the most prestigious journals are less trustworthy than average[3]:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;overestimating effect size in gene-association&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;studies increases with impact factor (more bias in more prestigious journals)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;sample size in gene-association studies decreases with impact factor&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;statistical power in psychology and cognitive science papers decreases with impact factor&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;randomization in animal studies is reported less frequently in papers from high-impact-factor journals&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;errors in supplemental data (eg Excel auto-converting a gene name to a date) are more common in papers from high-impact-factor journals&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;p-value reporting errors, usually in the direction of misinterpreting a non-significant result as significant, are more common in papers from high-impact-factor journals&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;metrics to identify tell-tale signs of questionable research practices find lower research quality in higher-impact-factor journals.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, no, we can’t assume that the most-cited papers of today are the cream of the crop. If anything, there’s more pressure today than ever to get dramatic but untrustworthy results, and that pressure is highest at the most competitive journals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One way to reverse this effect is to go back in time.  If the amount of noise in the system is increasing, an old paper is more likely to have a valid signal than a new one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3.) Low technology can be a blessing in disguise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The miracle of modern molecular biology is that we keep developing better tools to affordably do breadth-first searches. “Sequence ALL the genes!” “Quantify ALL the transcripts!” “Quantify ALL the proteins!” And so on.
The danger of having these incredible tools is that you can cherrypick positive results – and people do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s much harder to erroneously get an apparently therapeutic intervention if your tools are blunter and your search space is smaller. If somebody in 1944 says that shining light on a duck’s head makes its testes grow[4], then by gum I bet that actually happens!  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because it’s not coming from a breadth-first search, somebody had to have a specific reason to think that the experiment would work, and because there just aren’t that many experiments being done at random, you can expect that to be a well-informed reason. The prior is higher.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a similar sense in which lack of standardization is a blessing in disguise. Most mammal experiments today are done on the same handful of strains of inbred mice, for instance. The standardization is a boon to researchers in many ways (you can make apples-to-apples comparisons, you don’t have to spend time inventing the basics of experimental methods yourself) but it also means that experimental results can just turn out to be an artifact of the “standard methodology.”  Looking at older experiments, which have greater diversity in model organisms and other experimental methods, can be a corrective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4.) Old papers are undervalued opportunities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The author of the latest exciting result is a ready-made advocate for the discovery and a potential founder or collaborator for new ventures to put it into practice.  The author of an old paper, by contrast, might be dead or retired, with nobody to champion the potential applications of the discovery. It’s very easy for an area of research to quietly fall out of fashion through no inherent lack of merit, just because it never met the right opportunity for application. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m just barely old enough to remember when neural nets were thought of as an embarrassing phase in the history of computer science; they became “hot” again in 2012, with AlexNet, when newly affordable GPUs proved that deep learning algorithms could suddenly outperform the competition. In other words, advances in a totally different technology made a “failed” research approach into an overnight success. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Going through old, not necessarily well-known experiments to see if there are opportunities is something I don’t believe is being done that often, and is probably an unusually good place to apply a little bit of time and attention for big returns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That said, let’s look at some specific examples!  These are all results from prior to the year 2000, that are experimental interventions affecting vertebrate lifespan or aging, and which aren’t currently the focus of a research program that I’m aware of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lowering Body Temperature: 71% Life Extension in Fish&lt;/strong&gt; 
Unusually long-lived vertebrates (tortoises, sharks, rockfish, etc, which can survive for centuries, or naked mole rats, which are extremely long-lived for their size) are frequently cold-blooded.  Warm-blooded animals which are long-lived (in absolute terms, like whales, or relative to their size, like bats, hummingbirds, and squirrels) often undergo temporary reductions in body temperature, during diving or hibernation.  Moreover, interventions like dietary restriction which extend lifespan have the effect of reducing body temperature.  So can reducing body temperature directly extend life?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a cold-blooded example, transferring fish from 20-degree water to 15-degree water extended lifespan by 71%, in a 1972 study.[5]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To reduce the body temperature of a warm-blooded animal, it’s not enough to reduce ambient temperature, since warm-blooded animals generate heat to compensate. In fact, reducing the ambient temperature actually shortens mouse lifespan. However, there are tricks to lower body temperature in a warm-blooded animal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mice genetically modified to overexpress the uncoupling protein, UCP2, in the hypothalamus have lower body temperature than wild-type[6], and they live longer than their wild-type counterparts (20% increase in female median lifespan, 12% in male.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can also induce hypothermia by stimulating the heat-detecting cells in the hypothalamus, either by injecting capsaicin [7], heating the hypothalamus directly with a thermode [8], or stimulating the heat-sensing neurons optogenetically [9].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The natural next experiments to do are a.) see if any of these other methods of inducing hypothermia affect lifespan and diseases of aging in mice or other mammals; b.) do longitudinal transcriptomics or other broad assays to see what reduced body temperature is doing and whether its effects can be simulated chemically or genetically.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Altered Photoperiod Cycle Length: Short “Years” Shorten Lifespan 30% in Lemurs&lt;/strong&gt; 
Days get longer in summer and shorter in winter; by lengthening or shortening the cycle of alteration in photoperiod length (by changing artificial lighting) you can give an animal a shorter or longer subjective “year”. 
This turns out to affect lifespan!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The gray mouse lemur is a prosimian primate, native to Madagascar, that is long-lived for its size. During the long-day summer, gray mouse lemurs breed and are more active; during the short-day winter, they gain weight, become lethargic, and don’t copulate. If you alter the photoperiod cycle artificially, you can alter the timing of these behavioral and morphological changes accordingly – and if you reduce the “year length” by a third, from 12 months to 8 months, lifespan also shortens by 30% and the onset of white fur happens 30% earlier. [10] . In other words, lemurs live 9-10 “subjective years”, whether those are 8-month years or 12-month years. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The obvious follow-up experiment is to go the other direction – do lemurs (or other animals) live longer if you subject them to 16-month subjective years? And to take some tissue and blood samples and try to identify how this effect works – do we see pathological changes, transcriptional changes, hormonal changes, metabolic changes?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Constant Light Exposure: 25% Life Extension in Hamsters&lt;/strong&gt; 
A Syrian hamster model of congenital heart disease showed delayed onset of heart failure and 25% life extension if they were kept in continuously lit conditions.[11] 
The obvious corollary studies are to take heart tissue samples and blood samples and look for altered gene expression or metabolic parameters that might explain the effect of light exposure on preventing heart failure. It also might be possible to experiment directly with continuous light exposure on humans, since it’s probably not dangerous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pineal-Thymus Graft: 24% Life Extension in Aged Mice&lt;/strong&gt; 
Implanting the pineal gland of a young mouse into the thymus of an old (16-22 month) mouse extends lifespan 19% in C57BL6 mice, 20% in Balb/c mice, and 35% in hybrid mice, for an average of 24% overall.[12] This is consonant with a more extensive literature about the pineal gland or the main hormone (melatonin) it secretes having a life-extending effect through preventing the dysregulation of the circadian rhythm which occurs with age. 
The obvious follow-up study to do is a replication of the same implantation experiment, along with longitudinal expression data, to find out how this works and work towards identifying how a similar effect could be replicated by a less invasive intervention.
Splenectomy: 19% Life Extension in Aged Mice 
In a 1969 experiment, adding spleen cells to mice of the same age as the cell donors shortened lifespan; adding spleen cells from younger mice (14 week) to older mice (76 week) extended median lifespan from 105 weeks to 128 weeks, a 13% lifespan effect; and removing the spleens of mice altogether at age 97 weeks increased median remaining lifespan from 118 to 158 weeks, a 19% lifespan effect.
Clearly, the aged mouse spleen contains some factor that accelerates age-related decline. The obvious question is to find out what this is, through expression or proteomics studies on young, aged, and splenectomized mice, and see if there’s a way to target the culprit pharmacologically.
Induced Hypothyroidism: 17% Life Extension in Rats 
Exposing newborn rats to thyroid hormone permanently reduces their bodyweight and thyroxine levels; it’s a way of artificially inducing hypothyroidism.[13] It also has the effect of dramatically elevating their prolactin levels; as prolactin is stimulated by TSH release from the hypothalamus, clearly neonatal T4 exposure doesn’t prevent TSH release in the brain, but rather impairs the thyroid’s ability to respond to it.  This induced hypothyroidism also extends median lifespan by 17% and maximal lifespan by 6%. 
Obviously, inducing hypothyroidism isn’t a viable intervention for humans, but looking at changes in hormone levels and gene regulation in induced hypothyroidism might give clues to what downstream mechanisms are responsible for the lifespan increase and whether there’s a less-side-effect-heavy way to induce it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Castration: 17% Life Extension in Rats&lt;/strong&gt; 
Removing the testes of male Wistar rats has been found to extend lifespan 17% relative to unbred intact males; removing the ovaries extends lifespan 29% relative to unbred females. [14] 
This isn’t too surprising given that caloric restriction (a reliable life-extending intervention in rodents under typical lab conditions) has antigonadal effects, and that extremely dramatic lifespan effects can come from removing the germ cells in C. elegans.[15] There’s also some correlational evidence – for instance, castrated male cats arriving at veterinary hospitals lived 67% longer than intact males.[16]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obviously, castration isn’t a practical intervention for most humans, but it’s possible that there’s some downstream effect that doesn’t alter fertility or observable sex characteristics and preserves some of the anti-aging effect; this is a good opportunity for looking at longitudinal expression changes in castrated vs. intact animals and trying to identify the mechanism of lifespan extension.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lateral Hypothalamic Stimulation: 5% Life Extension in Aged Rats&lt;/strong&gt; 
Stimulating the lateral hypothalamus is pleasurable, and animals given the opportunity to self-stimulate will do so; this is what’s known as wireheading.  Interestingly enough, there are interactions with aging here as well.  Young adult rats have more neurons and more electrical activity in the lateral hypothalamic area (LHA) than old rats; young rats also exhibit more self-stimulatory behavior than old rats when given access to a button that turns on the electrode. Moreover, in old rats, chronic stimulation in the LHA extended lifespan from 1075 days to 1125 days (5% of total median lifespan, 8% of total maximum lifespan, 35% of residual lifespan); stimulation reduced body mass as well.[17] 
Is this just a dietary restriction effect, or is it something else? The natural thing to do is to try the experiment again, this time compared against controls given the exact same amount of food to eat; and also, to take brain samples after death and possibly other blood samples during lifespan to try to identify metabolic or regulatory changes caused by the stimulation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Blindness: Increases Survival in Rats&lt;/strong&gt; 
Blindness affects the circadian rhythm; it effectively gives the same hormonal signals as perpetual darkness. Rats blinded at 25 days had increased lifespan relative to controls; at 748 days, when the experiment concluded, the blind rats had a 95% survival rate while the control rats had a 50% survival rate. 
The natural follow-up is to do a full lifespan study so we can get an actual measurement of the effect on median lifespan, as well as measurements of other biomarkers so we can identify a mechanism and possibly a way to replicate the anti-aging effect without actually inducing blindness.
Fetal Hypothalmic Graft: Restores Fertility and Circadian Rhythm in Rats and Hamsters 
In keeping with the pattern of neuroendocrine effects on aging, it turns out that transplanting the suprachiasmatic nucleus (the part of the hypothalamus responsible for entraining the circadian rhythm in response to day length) from fetal animals into the brains of aged animals can restore the periodicity of the circadian rhythm and restore diminished fertility. With age, circadian rhythms become less regular; animals wake more during the periods when they should be sleeping, and/or are more lethargic during the periods when they should be awake.  Fetal SCN grafts reverse this phenomenon in both hamsters [18] and rats.[19] 
Moreover, 7 of 10 aged rats given fetal anterior hypothalamus transplants regained fertility and fathered a total of 106 pups[20], while medial basal hypothalamus transplants from rat fetuses into aged female rats reversed hypogonadism.[21]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The hypothalamus regulates a variety of hormonal signals, which become dysregulated with age; it seems that some of these effects can be reversed by transplanting a younger hypothalamus. The most natural question to ask is, first, does this extend life? Second, can we identify on the genetic or molecular level what the younger hypothalamus tissue is doing that improves aging-related phenotypes? If so, there might be a non-invasive way to replicate the effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What Now?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are ten very broad suggestions for animal experiments to run, which might yield targets that are ripe for intervention.  I’d expect, without looking too deeply into details, that each of these ten experiments would have a 6-figure price tag. And I’m aware of nobody who’s working on these projects (please correct me if I’m wrong!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Could these projects turn into biotech companies? It’s hard to say, of course; it depends on whether the experimental results are good, among other things. But I’m pretty inclined to believe that we don’t know all the aging-modulating targets yet. That points to phenotypic screening approaches (like what we’re doing at Daphnia Labs) or target-discovery studies (like the ones proposed in this post, or like the ones being done at Gordian, BioAge, or Fauna), being quite valuable. We don’t know everything that’s out there, and early-stage exploration is a lot cheaper than depth-first drug development, so on the margin more exploration is a “good buy”, it seems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[1]https://www.stm-assoc.org/2018_10_04_STM_Report_2018.pdf
[2]https://www.theatlantic.com/science/archive/2018/11/diminishing-returns-science/575665/
[3]Brembs, Björn. “Prestigious science journals struggle to reach even average reliability.” Frontiers in human neuroscience 12 (2018): 37.
[4]Benoit, Jacques, and L. Ott. “External and internal factors in sexual activity: effect of irradiation with different wave-lengths on the mechanisms of photostimulation of the hypophysis and on testicular growth in the immature duck.” The Yale journal of biology and medicine 17.1 (1944): 27.
[5]Liu, R. K., and R. L. Walford. “The effect of lowered body temperature on lifespan and immune and non-immune processes.” &lt;strong&gt;Gerontology&lt;/strong&gt; 18.5-6 (1972): 363-388.
[6]Conti, Bruno, et al. “Transgenic mice with a reduced core body temperature have an increased life span.” &lt;strong&gt;Science&lt;/strong&gt; 314.5800 (2006): 825-82
[7]Jancsó-Gábor, Aurelia, J. Szolcsanyi, and N. Jancso. “Stimulation and desensitization of the hypothalamic heat‐sensitive structures by capsaicin in rats.” &lt;strong&gt;The Journal of physiology&lt;/strong&gt; 208.2 (1970): 449-459.
[8]Hammel, H. T., J. D. Hardy, and MiM Fusco. “Thermoregulatory responses to hypothalamic cooling in unanesthetized dogs.” &lt;strong&gt;American Journal of Physiology-Legacy Content&lt;/strong&gt; 198.3 (1960): 481-486.
[9]Zhao, Zheng-Dong, et al. “A hypothalamic circuit that controls body temperature.” &lt;strong&gt;Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences&lt;/strong&gt; 114.8 (2017): 2042-2047.
[10]Perret, Martine. “Change in Photoperiodic Cycle Affects Life Span in a Prosimian Primate (Microcebus murinus.” &lt;strong&gt;Journal of biological rhythms&lt;/strong&gt; 12.2 (1997): 136-145.
[11]Tapp, Walter, and Benjamin Natelson. “Life extension in heart disease: an animal model.” &lt;strong&gt;The Lancet&lt;/strong&gt; 327.8475 (1986): 238-24
[12]Pierpaoli, Walter, et al. “The pineal control of aging: the effects of melatonin and pineal grafting on the survival of older mice.” &lt;strong&gt;Annals of the New York Academy of Sciences&lt;/strong&gt; 621.1 (1991): 291-313.
[13]Ooka, Hiroshi, Saori Fujita, and Emiko Yoshimoto. “Pituitary-thyroid activity and longevity in neonatally thyroxine-treated rats.” &lt;strong&gt;Mechanisms of ageing and development&lt;/strong&gt; 22.2 (1983): 113-12
[14]Asdell, S. A., and S. R. Joshi. “Reproduction and longevity in the hamster and rat.” &lt;strong&gt;Biology of reproduction&lt;/strong&gt; 14.4 (1976): 478-480.
[15]Hsin, Honor, and Cynthia Kenyon. “Signals from the reproductive system regulate the lifespan of C. elegans.” Nature 399.6734 (1999): 362.
[16]Hamilton, James B. “Relationship of castration, spaying, and sex to survival and duration of life in domestic cats.” &lt;strong&gt;Reproduction and aging. New York, NY: MSS Information Corporation&lt;/strong&gt; (1974): 96-115.
[17]Frolkis, V. V., et al. “The lateral hypothalamic area: Peculiarities of aging and the effect of chronic electrical stimulation on the lifespan in rats.” &lt;strong&gt;Neurophysiology&lt;/strong&gt; 32.4 (2000): 276-282.
[18]Viswanathan, N., and F. C. Davis. “Suprachiasmatic nucleus grafts restore circadian function in aged hamsters.” &lt;strong&gt;Brain research&lt;/strong&gt; 686.1 (1995): 10-16.
[19]Li, Hua, and Evelyn Satinoff. “Fetal tissue containing the suprachiasmatic nucleus restores multiple circadian rhythms in old rats.” &lt;strong&gt;American Journal of Physiology-Regulatory, Integrative and Comparative Physiology&lt;/strong&gt; 275.6 (1998): R1735-R1744.
[20]Huang, H. H., J. Q. Kissane, and E. J. Hawrylewicz. “Restoration of sexual function and fertility by fetal hypothalamic transplant in impotent aged male rats.” &lt;strong&gt;Neurobiology of aging&lt;/strong&gt; 8.5 (1987): 465-472.
[21]MATSUMOTO, Akira, et al. “Recovery of declined ovarian function in aged female rats by transplantation of newborn hypothalamic tissue.” &lt;strong&gt;Proceedings of the Japan Academy, Series B&lt;/strong&gt; 60.4 (1984): 73-76&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="aging" /><category term="lit-review" /><summary type="html">Why Read Old Papers?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Genes Involved in Aging – Looking For Intersections</title><link href="/2019/12/20/genes-involved-in-aging.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Genes Involved in Aging -- Looking For Intersections" /><published>2019-12-20T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2019-12-20T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>/2019/12/20/genes-involved-in-aging</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2019/12/20/genes-involved-in-aging.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/Top_Aging_Genes_1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;topgenes1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/Top_Aging_Genes2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;topgenes2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A natural type of question you might ask, if you’re interested in understanding aging, is which genes are involved in the aging process. The practical upshot of identifying genes with causal roles is that they’re potential drug targets.  If diseases of aging are caused or worsened by the excess of some protein, you might want to inhibit the production or activity of that protein. If diseases of aging are caused or worsened by a deficit in some protein, you might want to stimulate its production.
We have a lot of different kinds of experiments that can be run for identifying what genes and proteins are involved in aging, and thus a lot of aging-related “omics” studies. I’ll briefly summarize a few categories I know about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Longitudinal Transcriptomics&lt;/strong&gt; 
You can compare the expression of genes in tissue samples from old vs. young organisms (humans or mice) and see which genes are expressed more or less with age.  Today it’s even possible to get single-cell resolution on gene expression; we can identify the rate of gene transcription for each gene in a specific cell at a given time.  Similarly, you can get proteomics data, directly measuring the quantity of each protein in a tissue sample. 
This gives us correlational information about which genes are altered in the aging process, in particular tissues and cell types. It doesn’t by itself tell us which interventions might prevent disease.  If a particular gene is more expressed with age, it could be because it’s a cause of some deleterious process, or because it’s a symptom of that process, or because it’s part of the body’s attempt to mitigate that process.  Whether you want to inhibit that protein’s activity or production depends on what it’s doing, and expression levels by themselves can’t tell you that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Comparative Genomics&lt;/strong&gt; 
Animals don’t all age in the same way. Some are exceptionally long-lived, either in absolute terms (whales, elephants, tortoises, rockfishes, the Greenland shark) or relative to their size (bats, naked mole rats). Some mammals are immune from cancer.  Can we identify “genes responsible for healthy longevity” in the animal kingdom? Could we “borrow” the adaptations that slow-aging animals have developed, as treatments for humans? 
Given the genomes for two species, you can identify homologous genes – genes that have very similar sequences and probably similar functions.  Something like half our genes have homologues in common with insects and all vertebrates.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the homologue of a gene in an exceptionally long-lived species is absent or has a loss-of-function mutation, you might ask whether that gene contributes to aging.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a gene family of similar proteins is “expanded” in a long-lived species (meaning there are more variations on that gene present) or if a gene has a high copy number (meaning there are many identical versions of that gene) you might ask whether that gene has a protective effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a gene shows evidence of positive selection in a long-lived species, you might ask whether that gene has a protective effect against some aging process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If there’s a correlation between copy number or gene family size and lifespan (or lifespan per body weight) across species, that’s somewhat stronger evidence that there’s an association between those genes and lifespan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, these are all correlational; they don’t tell you how the gene works, or what would happen if you interfered with it experimentally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Experimental Genetic Modifications&lt;/strong&gt; 
If you induce a genetic mutation in a mouse gene and the mouse lives longer or avoids the onset of age-related diseases, then you do have causal evidence that the gene is involved in regulating aging. 
There are a variety of ways of inducing specific mutations, some permanent and some temporary, some causing total absence of the gene (knockout) while others cause a deficit (knockdown) or unusually high production of the gene product (overexpression.)
Looking for the Intersection
Most broad studies (longitudinal transcriptomics, comparative genomics) looking for genes involved in aging come up with totally different lists of candidate genes.  
Sometimes, of course, this is expected, because they’re looking at different tissues or different organisms. You don’t expect all animals or all tissues to change in the same way with age. And, of course, comparing genomes between species and comparing gene expression over time within one species are apples-to-oranges comparisons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But even in cases where the experiments are supposed to measure the same thing, there’s poor replication. And that’s not surprising because the samples are so small. It’s not uncommon to see longitudinal transcriptomics studies with fewer than ten organisms in the “old” and “young” groups. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And this matters because if you want to have any hope of translation to humans, you’ve got to be able to have results that are consistent across different strains of mouse, or even species of mammal; if it’s all wiped out by natural variation between organisms, there’s no way you’re getting signal usable for designing human treatments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I did a very, very crude type of meta-analysis; I looked at all the studies I could, out of these three types (transcriptomics and proteomics of aging; comparative genomics of aging in long-lived species; and interventional studies of genetic modifications; all restricted to studies on vertebrates) and ranked genes (or gene families) by the number of papers in which the gene popped out as significant. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a couple of potential flaws in my methodology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, I used Google Scholar to search, and stopped when the relevant search terms stopped returning studies of the relevant type. There may well have been studies this search method missed; it’s just much more time-efficient than using PubMed searches (which reliably produce far less relevant results, but it’s easier to document exactly how many papers matched search terms, which is why they’re the standard method in formal literature reviews.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second of all, I didn’t use a consistent cutoff in picking out which genes were significant. (In a study that tests all 20,000 or so human genes for differential expression, “statistically significant” is a very low bar.) I generally noted down the handful of genes that had the highest fold change and lowest p-value, not literally all the ones that met a significance threshold.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thirdly, some studies, of course, like lifespan studies of a genetic modification, aren’t unbiased screens of all genes; genes that have gained more scientific interest are likely to be studied more often, so in part this list of “top genes” reflects the biases of the research literature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, finally, since we’re comparing different types of studies, we’re not making apples-to-apples comparisons. You don’t expect the genes differentially expressed with age to be exactly the same as the genes which are modified in long-lived organisms or the same as those which alter lifespan when experimentally mutated. If a gene shows up in all three types of studies I think that’s some sort of evidence that it’s “more likely to really be involved” in aging, but not in the same straightforward sense that it’s true that a study is more credible when it replicates exactly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I think it’s worth doing something in this vein, as a way of helping orient ourselves in a growing field. As more and more papers come out claiming that they’ve found genes “associated” with aging, we want to be able to be familiar with what the most common ones that keep showing up are.  Just as with genome-wide association studies for genetic predictors of disease, one correlation showing up in a study doesn’t mean we’ve found the “gene for” anything. I think of the aggregation process as a learning experience, for getting a sense of what the field as a whole looks like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a histogram of the frequency of the distribution of the genes.
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/genehistogram.png&quot; alt=&quot;histogram&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The majority of genes only appeared in one paper; most genes that were significantly related to age or lifespan in one paper did not show up in any others.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Discussion&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The top-scoring gene families suggest some conclusions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It’s probably worth doing interventional genetic modifications on mammals for genes that show a lot of correlational evidence of being involved in aging. Inhibiting the expression of serpins, heat shock proteins, or chemokines in mice might show a delay in some aging phenotypes.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Some of these genes make sense in light of the “hallmarks of aging” – serpins and heat shock proteins are associated with proteostasis and the elimination of misfolded proteins; IGF, GH, and FGF’s are involved in nutrient sensing and growth; UCP is a key mitochondrial function; TNF and the chemokines are inflammatory signals. It would make sense that dysregulation of these functions plays a causal role in age-related disease. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We need much larger sample sizes on longitudinal transcriptomics studies. The typical studies I found, mouse or human, had fewer than ten experimental subjects per age group. As you might expect, this yielded inconsistent results. Between-individual diversity can be a confounding factor that makes it harder to reliably identify age-related changes.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, [22] clusters gene transcripts in human T cells according to their aging-related dynamics, and finds three kinds of genes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;1.	genes that follow a &quot;U-shaped&quot; curve, declining in expression level until about age 60 and then rising again; these include growth-and-proliferation-associated signals

2.	genes that follow an inverted-U curve, rising in expression level until about age 70 and then declining; these are mostly cancer-related genes as well as the mTOR and Jak-STAT pathways

3.	genes that start out high in expression level and start to decline at age 80; these are mostly mitochondrial and neurological. I find this very interesting as a categorization and wonder if it holds up for more cell and tissue types. 
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From a therapeutic perspective, if this pattern generalizes, I could imagine we might want to enhance production or activity of proteins in the third cluster, inhibit the production or activity of compounds in the second cluster, and be cautious about the tradeoffs in the first cluster, since both straightforwardly inhibiting and accelerating nonspecific growth signals can have serious side effects.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s hard to tell, for now. But in order to replicate this result you’d also need more studies to use multiple time periods, instead of just taking old and young samples; once again, increasing the scale of longitudinal transcriptomic studies would be very valuable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt; 
1. Bodyak, Natalya, et al. “Gene expression profiling of the aging mouse cardiac myocytes.” Nucleic acids research 30.17 (2002): 3788-3794. 
2. Park, Sang‐Kyu, et al. “Gene expression profiling of aging in multiple mouse strains: identification of aging biomarkers and impact of dietary antioxidants.” Aging cell 8.4 (2009): 484-495.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3. Yoshida, Shigeo, et al. “Microarray analysis of gene expression in the aging human retina.” Investigative ophthalmology &amp;amp; visual science 43.8 (2002): 2554-2560.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4.Zhou, Jing, et al. “Integrated study on comparative transcriptome and skeletal muscle function in aged rats.” &lt;strong&gt;Mechanisms of ageing and development&lt;/strong&gt; 169 (2018): 32-&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;5. Dobson Jr, James G., et al. “Molecular mechanisms of reduced β-adrenergic signaling in the aged heart as revealed by genomic profiling.” &lt;strong&gt;Physiological genomics&lt;/strong&gt; 15.2 (2003): 142-147.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;6. Yang, S., et al. “Comparative proteomic analysis of brains of naturally aging mice.” &lt;strong&gt;Neuroscience&lt;/strong&gt; 154.3 (2008): 1107-1120.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;7. Glaab, Enrico, and Reinhard Schneider. “Comparative pathway and network analysis of brain transcriptome changes during adult aging and in Parkinson’s disease.” &lt;strong&gt;Neurobiology of disease&lt;/strong&gt; 74 (2015): 1-13.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;8.Huang, Zixia, et al. “Longitudinal comparative transcriptomics reveals unique mechanisms underlying extended healthspan in bats.” &lt;strong&gt;Nature ecology &amp;amp; evolution&lt;/strong&gt; (2019): 1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;9. Welle, Stephen, et al. “Gene expression profile of aging in human muscle.” &lt;strong&gt;Physiological genomics&lt;/strong&gt; 14.2 (2003): 149-159.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;10. Heras, Joseph, and Andres Aguilar. “Comparative Transcriptomics Reveals Patterns of Adaptive Evolution Associated with Depth and Age Within Marine Rockfishes (Sebastes).” Journal of Heredity 110.3 (2019): 340-350.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;11. Ximerakis, Methodios, et al. “Single-cell transcriptomic profiling of the aging mouse brain.” &lt;strong&gt;Nature neuroscience&lt;/strong&gt; 22.10 (2019): 1696-1708&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;12. Angelidis, Ilias, et al. “An atlas of the aging lung mapped by single cell transcriptomics and deep tissue proteomics.” &lt;strong&gt;Nature communications&lt;/strong&gt; 10.1 (2019): 963.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Benayoun, Bérénice A., et al. “Remodeling of epigenome and transcriptome landscapes with aging in mice reveals widespread induction of inflammatory responses.” &lt;strong&gt;Genome research&lt;/strong&gt; 29.4 (2019): 697-709.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;14. Taylor, Jackson, et al. “Transcriptomic profiles of aging in naïve and memory CD4+ cells from mice.” &lt;strong&gt;Immunity &amp;amp; Ageing&lt;/strong&gt; 14.1 (2017): 15.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;15. Shi, Zhanping, et al. “Single-cell transcriptomics reveals gene signatures and alterations associated with aging in distinct neural stem/progenitor cell subpopulations.” &lt;strong&gt;Protein &amp;amp; cell&lt;/strong&gt; 9.4 (2018): 351-364&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;16. Kuehne, Andreas, et al. “An integrative metabolomics and transcriptomics study to identify metabolic alterations in aged skin of humans in vivo.” &lt;strong&gt;BMC genomics&lt;/strong&gt; 18.1 (2017): 169.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;17. Peffers, Mandy Jayne, Xuan Liu, and Peter David Clegg. “Transcriptomic signatures in cartilage ageing.” Arthritis research &amp;amp; therapy 15.4 (2013): R98.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;18. Yu, Ying, et al. “A rat RNA-Seq transcriptomic BodyMap across 11 organs and 4 developmental stages.” &lt;strong&gt;Nature communications&lt;/strong&gt; 5 (2014): 3230&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;19. Galatro, Thais F., et al. “Transcriptomic analysis of purified human cortical microglia reveals age-associated changes.” &lt;strong&gt;Nature neuroscience&lt;/strong&gt; 20.8 (2017): 1162.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;20. Galea, Gabriel L., et al. “Old age and the associated impairment of bones’ adaptation to loading are associated with transcriptomic changes in cellular metabolism, cell-matrix interactions and the cell cycle.” &lt;strong&gt;Gene&lt;/strong&gt; 599 (2017): 36-52.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;21. Marttila, Saara, et al. “Transcriptional analysis reveals gender-specific changes in the aging of the human immune system.” &lt;strong&gt;PloS one&lt;/strong&gt; 8.6 (2013): e66229&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;22. Remondini, Daniel, et al. “Complex patterns of gene expression in human T cells during in vivo aging.” &lt;strong&gt;Molecular bioSystems&lt;/strong&gt; 6.10 (2010): 1983-1992.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;23. Gao, Lin, et al. “Age-mediated transcriptomic changes in adult mouse substantia nigra.” &lt;strong&gt;PloS one&lt;/strong&gt; 8.4 (2013): e62456.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;24. Cai, Hui, et al. “Effects of aging and anatomic location on gene expression in human retina.” &lt;strong&gt;Frontiers neuroscience&lt;/strong&gt; 4 (2012): 8.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;25. Jonker, Martijs J., et al. “Life spanning murine gene expression profiles in relation to chronological and pathological aging in multiple organs. Aging cell__ 12.5 (2013): 901-909.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;26. Lewis, Kaitlyn N., et al. “Unraveling the message: insights into comparative genomics of the naked mole-rat.” Mammalian Genome 27.7-8 (2016): 259-278.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;27. Keane, Michael, et al. “Insights into the evolution of longevity from the bowhead whale genome.” &lt;strong&gt;Cell reports&lt;/strong&gt; 10.1 (2015): 112-122.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;28. Seim, Inge, et al. “Genome analysis reveals insights into physiology and longevity of the Brandt’s bat Myotis brandtii.” &lt;strong&gt;Nature communications&lt;/strong&gt; 4 (2013): 2212.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;29. Quesada, Víctor, et al. “Giant tortoise genomes provide insights into longevity and age-related disease.” &lt;strong&gt;Nature ecology &amp;amp; evolution&lt;/strong&gt; 3.1 (2019): 87.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;30. Abegglen, Lisa M., et al. “Potential mechanisms for cancer resistance in elephants and comparative cellular response to DNA damage in humans.” &lt;strong&gt;Jama&lt;/strong&gt; 314.17 (2015): 1850-1860.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Seabury, Christopher M., et al. “A multi-platform draft de novo genome assembly and comparative analysis for the scarlet macaw (Ara macao).” &lt;strong&gt;PLOS one&lt;/strong&gt; 8.5 (2013): e6&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;32. Foote, Andrew D., et al. “Convergent evolution of the genomes of marine mammals.” &lt;strong&gt;Nature genetics&lt;/strong&gt; 47.3 (2015): 272.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;33. Shaffer, H. Bradley, et al. “The western painted turtle genome, a model for the evolution of extreme physiological adaptations in a slowly evolving lineage.” &lt;strong&gt;Genome biology&lt;/strong&gt; 14.3 (2013): R28.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;34. Wirthlin, Morgan, et al. “Parrot genomes and the evolution of heightened longevity and cognition.” &lt;strong&gt;Current Biology&lt;/strong&gt; 28.24 (2018): 4001-4008.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;35. Wirthlin, Morgan, et al. “Parrot genomes and the evolution of heightened longevity and cognition.” &lt;strong&gt;Current Biology&lt;/strong&gt; 28.24 (2018): 4001-4008.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;36. Ma, Siming, and Vadim N. Gladyshev. “Molecular signatures of longevity: insights from cross-species comparative studies.” &lt;strong&gt;Seminars in cell &amp;amp; developmental biology&lt;/strong&gt;. Vol. 70. Academic Press, 2017.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;37. Fushan, Alexey A., et al. “Gene expression defines natural changes in mammalian lifespan.” &lt;strong&gt;Aging cell&lt;/strong&gt; 14.3 (2015): 352-365.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;38. Pickering, Andrew M., Marcus Lehr, and Richard A. Miller. “Lifespan of mice and primates correlates with immunoproteasome expression.” &lt;strong&gt;The Journal of clinical investigation&lt;/strong&gt; 125.5 (2015): 2059-2068.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;39. Pyo, Jong-Ok, et al. “Overexpression of ATG5 in mice activates autophagy and extends lifespan.” &lt;strong&gt;Nature communications&lt;/strong&gt; 4 (2013): 2300.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;40. Zhang, Yuan, et al. “The starvation hormone, fibroblast growth factor-21, extends lifespan in mice.” &lt;strong&gt;elife&lt;/strong&gt; 1 (2012): e00065.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;41. Conover, Cheryl A., and Laurie K. Bale. “Loss of pregnancy‐associated plasma protein A extends lifespan in mice.” &lt;strong&gt;Aging cell&lt;/strong&gt; 6.5 (2007): 727-729.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;42. Sun, Liou Y., et al. “Growth hormone-releasing hormone disruption extends lifespan and regulates response to caloric restriction in mice.” &lt;strong&gt;Elife&lt;/strong&gt; 2 (2013): e01098.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;43. Baker, Darren J., et al. “Increased expression of BubR1 protects against aneuploidy and cancer and extends healthy lifespan.” &lt;strong&gt;Nature cell biology&lt;/strong&gt; 15.1 (2013): 96.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;44. Selman, Colin, Linda Partridge, and Dominic J. Withers. “Replication of extended lifespan phenotype in mice with deletion of insulin receptor substrate 1.” &lt;strong&gt;PloS one&lt;/strong&gt; 6.1 (2011): e16144.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;45. Kanfi, Yariv, et al. “The SIRTuin SIRT6 regulates lifespan in male mice.” &lt;strong&gt;Nature&lt;/strong&gt; 483.7388 (2012): 218.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;46. Wu, Chia-Yu, et al. “A persistent level of Cisd2 extends healthy lifespan and delays aging in mice.” &lt;strong&gt;Human molecular genetics&lt;/strong&gt; 21.18 (2012): 3956-3968.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;47. Wu, Chia-Yu, et al. “A persistent level of Cisd2 extends healthy lifespan and delays aging in mice.” &lt;strong&gt;Human molecular genetics&lt;/strong&gt; 21.18 (2012): 3956-3968.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;48. Flurkey, Kevin, et al. “Lifespan extension and delayed immune and collagen aging in mutant mice with defects in growth hormone production.” &lt;strong&gt;Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences&lt;/strong&gt; 98.12 (2001): 6736-6741.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;49. Harper, James M., J. Erby Wilkinson, and Richard A. Miller. “Macrophage migration inhibitory factor-knockout mice are long lived and respond to caloric restriction.” &lt;strong&gt;The FASEB Journal&lt;/strong&gt; 24.7 (2010): 2436-2442&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;50. Streeper, Ryan S., et al. “Deficiency of the lipid synthesis enzyme, DGAT1, extends longevity in mice.” &lt;strong&gt;Aging (Albany NY)&lt;/strong&gt; 4.1 (2012): 13.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;51. Müller, Christine, et al. “Reduced expression of C/EBPβ-LIP extends health and lifespan in mice.” &lt;strong&gt;Elife&lt;/strong&gt; 7 (2018): e34985&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;52. de Jesus, Bruno Bernardes, et al. “Telomerase gene therapy in adult and old mice delays aging and increases longevity without increasing cancer.” &lt;strong&gt;EMBO molecular medicine&lt;/strong&gt; 4.8 (2012): 691-704.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;53. Canaan, Allon, et al. “Extended lifespan and reduced adiposity in mice lacking the FAT10 gene.” &lt;strong&gt;Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences&lt;/strong&gt; 111.14 (2014): 5313-5318.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;54. Al-Regaiey, Khalid A., et al. “Long-lived growth hormone receptor knockout mice: interaction of reduced insulin-like growth factor i/insulin signaling and caloric restriction.” &lt;strong&gt;Endocrinology&lt;/strong&gt; 146.2 (2005): 851-860.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;55. Holzenberger, Martin, et al. “IGF-1 receptor regulates lifespan and resistance to oxidative stress in mice.” &lt;strong&gt;Nature&lt;/strong&gt; 421.6919 (2003): 182.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;56. Schriner, Samuel E., and Nancy J. Linford. “Extension of mouse lifespan by overexpression of catalase.” &lt;strong&gt;Age&lt;/strong&gt; 28.2 (2006): 209-218.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;57. Schriner, Samuel E., and Nancy J. Linford. “Extension of mouse lifespan by overexpression of [[catalase]].” &lt;strong&gt;Age&lt;/strong&gt; 28.2 (2006): 209-218.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;58. Satoh, Akiko, et al. “SIRT1 extends life span and delays aging in mice through the regulation of Nk2 homeobox 1 in the DMH and LH.” &lt;strong&gt;Cell metabolism&lt;/strong&gt; 18.3 (2013): 416-430.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;59. Kurosu, Hiroshi, et al. “Suppression of aging in mice by the hormone Klotho.” &lt;strong&gt;Science&lt;/strong&gt; 309.5742 (2005): 1829-1833.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;60. Shimokawa, Isao, et al. “Life span extension by reduction in growth hormone-insulin-like growth factor-1 axis in a transgenic rat model.” &lt;strong&gt;The American journal of pathology&lt;/strong&gt; 160.6 (2002): 2259-2265.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;61. Zhang, Guo, et al. “Hypothalamic programming of systemic ageing involving IKK-β, NF-κB and GnRH.” &lt;strong&gt;Nature&lt;/strong&gt; 497.7448 (2013): 211&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;62. Wu, J. Julie, et al. “Increased mammalian lifespan and a segmental and tissue-specific slowing of aging after genetic reduction of mTOR expression.” &lt;strong&gt;Cell reports&lt;/strong&gt; 4.5 (2013): 913-920.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;63. Selman, Colin, et al. “Ribosomal protein S6 kinase 1 signaling regulates mammalian life span.” &lt;strong&gt;Science&lt;/strong&gt; 326.5949 (2009): 140-144&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;64. Ikeno, Yuji, et al. “Delayed occurrence of fatal neoplastic diseases in Ames dwarf mice: correlation to extended longevity.” The Journals of Gerontology Series A: Biological Sciences and Medical Sciences 58.4 (2003): B291-B296.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;65. Matheu, Ander, et al. “Delayed ageing through damage protection by the Arf/p53 pathway.” &lt;strong&gt;Nature&lt;/strong&gt; 448.7151 (2007): 375.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;66. Ortega-Molina, Ana, et al. “Pten positively regulates brown adipose function, energy expenditure, and longevity.” &lt;strong&gt;Cell metabolism&lt;/strong&gt; 15.3 (2012): 382-3&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;67. Hofmann, Jeffrey W., et al. “Reduced expression of MYC increases longevity and enhances healthspan.” &lt;strong&gt;Cell&lt;/strong&gt; 160.3 (2015): 477-488.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;68. Riera, Céline E., et al. “TRPV1 pain receptors regulate longevity and metabolism by neuropeptide signaling.” &lt;strong&gt;Cell&lt;/strong&gt; 157.5 (2014): 1023-1036&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;69. Conti, Bruno, et al. “Transgenic mice with a reduced core body temperature have an increased life span.” &lt;strong&gt;Science&lt;/strong&gt; 314.5800 (2006): 825-828.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;70. Nóbrega-Pereira, Sandrina, et al. “G6PD protects from oxidative damage and improves healthspan in mice.” &lt;strong&gt;Nature communications&lt;/strong&gt; 7 (2016): 10894.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;71. Dell’Agnello, Carlotta, et al. “Increased longevity and refractoriness to Ca2+-dependent neurodegeneration in Surf1 knockout mice.” &lt;strong&gt;Human molecular genetics&lt;/strong&gt; 16.4 (2007): 431-444.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;72. Miskin, Ruth, and Tamar Masos. “Transgenic mice overexpressing urokinase-type plasminogen activator in the brain exhibit reduced food consumption, body weight and size, and increased longevity.” The Journals of Gerontology Series A: Biological Sciences and Medical Sciences 52.2 (1997): B118-B124.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;73. Miskin, Ruth, and Tamar Masos. “Transgenic mice overexpressing urokinase-type plasminogen activator in the brain exhibit reduced food consumption, body weight and size, and increased longevity.” The Journals of Gerontology Series A: Biological Sciences and Medical Sciences 52.2 (1997): B118-B124.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;74. Fernández, Álvaro F., et al. “Disruption of the beclin 1–BCL2 autophagy regulatory complex promotes longevity in mice.” Nature 558.7708 (2018): 136.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;75. Vatner, Stephen F., et al. “Adenylyl cyclase type 5 disruption prolongs longevity and protects the heart against stress.” &lt;strong&gt;Circulation Journal&lt;/strong&gt; 73.2 (2009): 195-200.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;76.Schriner, Samuel E., et al. “Extension of murine life span by overexpression of catalase targeted to mitochondria.” &lt;strong&gt;science&lt;/strong&gt; 308.5730 (2005): 1909-1911.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;77. Liu, Xingxing, et al. “Evolutionary conservation of the clk-1-dependent mechanism of longevity: loss of mCLK1 increases cellular fitness and lifespan in mice.” &lt;strong&gt;Genes &amp;amp; development&lt;/strong&gt; 19.20 (2005): 2424-2434.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Blüher, Matthias, Barbara B. Kahn, and C. Ronald Kahn. “Extended longevity in mice lacking the insulin receptor in adipose tissue.” &lt;strong&gt;Science&lt;/strong&gt; 299.5606 (2003): 572-574.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;79. Borrás, Consuelo, et al. “RASGrf1 deficiency delays aging in mice.” &lt;strong&gt;Aging (Albany NY)&lt;/strong&gt; 3.3 (2011): 262.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;80. Matheu, Ander, et al. “Anti‐aging activity of the Ink4/Arf locus.” &lt;strong&gt;Aging cell&lt;/strong&gt; 8.2 (2009): 152-161.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;81. Markovich, Daniel, Mei-Chun Ku, and Dzaidenny Muslim. “Increased lifespan in hyposulfatemic NaS1 null mice.” &lt;strong&gt;Experimental gerontology&lt;/strong&gt; 46.10 (2011): 833-835.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;82. Redmann Jr, Stephen M., and George Argyropoulos. “AgRP-deficiency could lead to increased lifespan.” &lt;strong&gt;Biochemical and biophysical research communications&lt;/strong&gt; 351.4 (2006): 860-864.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;83. De Luca, Gabriele, et al. “Prolonged lifespan with enhanced exploratory behavior in mice overexpressing the oxidized nucleoside triphosphatase hMTH1.” &lt;strong&gt;Aging cell&lt;/strong&gt; 12.4 (2013): 695-705.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;84. Andersen, J. B., et al. “Role of 2-5A-dependent RNase-L in senescence and longevity.” &lt;strong&gt;Oncogene&lt;/strong&gt; 26.21 (2007): 3081.
 &lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="aging" /><category term="lit-review" /><summary type="html"></summary></entry></feed>