<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://srconstantin.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://srconstantin.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-06-09T11:23:40-07:00</updated><id>https://srconstantin.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Sarah Constantin</title><subtitle>Trained in math and machine learning, currently trying to solve biological problems and make sense of our world.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Dose-Response Effects of Viral Exposure in COVID-19</title><link href="https://srconstantin.github.io/2020/06/02/Dose-Response.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dose-Response Effects of Viral Exposure in COVID-19" /><published>2020-06-02T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-06-02T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://srconstantin.github.io/2020/06/02/Dose-Response</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://srconstantin.github.io/2020/06/02/Dose-Response.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/virus-infection.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;virus&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Does being exposed to a small quantity of SARS-CoV-2 virus result in less severe disease than being exposed to a large quantity?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The answer is relevant to how we should respond to COVID-19.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If high dose exposures are worse than low-dose exposures, then:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We should consider people who spend a lot of time with infected people, like healthcare workers and family members of COVID-19 patients, to be more at risk than people who get briefly exposed to the virus
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Reopening lower-risk public spaces (like outdoor cafes or parks) may be low-risk compared to reopening spaces that involve a lot of close contact (like gyms and nightclubs)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;We should prioritize PPE even _more _for people who regularly interact with COVID-19 patients&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Low dose exposure to SARS-CoV-2 may produce immunity without producing serious illness.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;If low dose exposure is safe and produces immunity, it may be good for people and available faster than a vaccine can be manufactured and approved.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bottom Lines&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People who have higher respiratory _viral loads _are significantly more likely to have severe COVID-19; the same pattern held in both the SARS and MERS coronavirus epidemics.  More virus in the body does tend to correspond to more severe disease.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s far less data about how different forms of _exposure _correlate to disease severity, but there are a few studies pointing towards a greater chance of severe COVID-19 from household contacts than from travel, and one study indicates that mask usage increases the probability that a SARS case will be asymptomatic.  These constitute weak evidence that larger doses of exposure to human coronaviruses cause more severe disease.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When human volunteers are experimentally exposed to viruses, some viruses cause more severe symptoms at higher doses, while some viruses don’t.  None of the relevant studies were on coronaviruses, however.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In _animal _experimental exposures to virus, higher doses consistently cause more severe symptoms, including in experiments on the coronaviruses SARS, MERS, and PEDV.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The available evidence is highly incomplete, but tends towards the conclusion that lower dose exposure to COVID-19 should result in less severe disease.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Viral Load in COVID-19&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a table of studies that compared viral load in mild and severe COVID-19 patients.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;N&lt;/strong&gt;
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mean Viral Load, Mild&lt;/strong&gt;
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mean Viral Load, Severe&lt;/strong&gt;
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Significance&lt;/strong&gt;
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Location of Sample&lt;/strong&gt;
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Context&lt;/strong&gt;
   &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;15
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Ct = 25 (n = 6, range 17-32)
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Ct = 27 (n = 9, range 19-33)
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;n.s. 
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Nasopharyngeal swab
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Private hospital, Mumbai, India[1]
   &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;92
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Ct = 28 (n = 62, sigma = 0.5)
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Ct = 25 (n = 30, sigma = 0.5)
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;p = 0.017
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Sputum
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Zhejiang, China; severe patients older &amp;amp; with more comorbidities but not different exposure histories. [2]
   &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;96
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;4.1 log copies/mL (n = 22, sigma = 1.4 )
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;5.1 log copies/mL (n = 74, sigma = 1.4)
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;p = 0.03
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Sputum (no difference between mild &amp;amp; severe pts  in serum or stool)
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Zhejiang, China; severe patients more likely to be from Wuhan[3]
   &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;76
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;delta-CT = -1.25 (n = 30, sigma = 5.2)
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;delta-CT = 4.48(n = 46, sigma = 3.0)
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;p &amp;lt; 0.001
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;nasopharyngeal
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Nanchang, China; median time from disease onset = 4 days[4]
   &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;23
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;5 log copies/mL (n = 10, sigma = 2.2)
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;6 log copies/mL (n = 13, sigma = 3.0)
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;n.s. 
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;oropharyngeal
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Hong Kong[5]; mild &amp;amp; severe patients had similar duration of illness at admission, age, sex, &amp;amp; comorbidities
   &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;12
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Ct = 35.2 (n = 10, sigma = 5)
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Ct = 26 (n = 3, sigma = 5.1)
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;p = 0.0177
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;nasal
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Guangdong, China [6]
   &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;18
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Ct = 30.9(n = 12, sigma = 5.6)
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Ct = 30.3 (n = 6, sigma = 5.3)
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;n.s. 
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;nasopharyngeal
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Singapore[7]
   &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;6
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Ct = 39 (n = 2, sigma = 1.2)
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Ct = 39 (n = 4, sigma = 1.1)
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;n.s.
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;nasopharyngeal
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Chongqing, China; all patients had previously recovered from COVID-19 and had reoccurence of disease.[8]
   &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;94
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Ct=30 (n = 76, sigma = 5) 
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Ct = 30 (n = 18, sigma = 4)
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;n.s
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Throat swabs
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Guangzhou, China [9]
   &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;11
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;6.39 log copies/mL (n = 5, sigma = 0.9)
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;6.15 log copies/mL (n = 6, sigma = 1.6)
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;n.s.
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;nasopharyngeal
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Hong Kong [10]; first 11 patients diagnosed with COVID-19
   &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;5
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;6.3 log copies/ 1000 cells (n = 2, sigma = 1.25)
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;5.3 log copies/1000 cells (n = 3, sigma = 2.4)
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;n.s.
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;nasopharyngeal
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;France [11]; patients traveling from Wuhan
   &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do severe COVID-19 patients have higher viral loads than mild patients?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a flawed proxy for the question of initial exposure, since patients are usually not tested for COVID-19 until at least several days after infection. Higher viral load could indicate that the virus replicated faster inside the body, or simply that the patients were later in their course of disease, rather than that the initial exposure was lower.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still, the correlation between viral load and disease severity is suggestive as to whether there’s a dose-response effect in COVID-19.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Viral load can be measured with Ct, the number of PCR amplification cycles necessary before viral RNA is detectable. Lower Ct numbers mean exponentially more virus.  It can also be measured by delta-Ct, the difference between the number of cycles to detection in a control sample (without virus) and the test sample.  Finally, it can be measured by the absolute concentration of viral particles per mL.  These numbers cannot be directly compared because the sensitivity of RT-PCR equipment varies and isn’t always given in the papers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For all studies measured in Ct value, mean Ct score is 29.6 for mild cases and 26.1 for severe cases; this is a significant effect, p = 0.0004.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the 4 studies measured in absolute concentration, mean concentration was 4.7 log copies/mL for mild cases and 5.3 log copies/mL for severe cases, which was not statistically significant, possibly because the sample size was too small.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also note that the two studies which looked at sputum samples both found significant effects, and sputum samples reliably contain more virus RNA than nasopharyngeal samples.  This suggests that viral load in the lungs is more predictive of the amount of lung damage &amp;amp; thus the severity of respiratory illness than viral load in the upper respiratory tract.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Severe COVID-19 patients have significantly higher initial viral loads than mild COVID-19 patients.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Exposure Effects in COVID-19&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another question we might ask is whether people with extensive exposure to the virus had more severe illness than people with transient or low-dose exposure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a study of 36 children with COVID-19, there was no significant difference in disease severity between those who had close contact with a family member with COVID-19 and those who had traveled to an area affected by COVID-19.[12]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1663 patients with COVID-19 in Wuhan, China, there was no significant difference in severity between those who did and did not have a family member with the disease or exposure to the Wuhan seafood market, but were significantly (p&amp;lt;0.0001) less likely to have severe disease if they were healthcare workers compared to the general population.  On the other hand this may be because healthcare workers are younger (most of the patients were retirees.)[13]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 568 COVID-19 patients in Wuhan, China, there was a nonsignificant trend (p = 0.06) for severe cases to be more likely to have had household exposure to the virus, while non-severe cases were more likely to have had hospital exposure to the virus.[14]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In another study of 487 patients with COVID-19 in Zhejiang Province, China, patients with severe disease were significantly less likely to have traveled to an affected area (49.0% vs. 65.1%, p = 0.027) but significantly more likely to be part of a family cluster of three or more patients (10.2% vs. 2.5%).[15]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall it doesn’t seem that the relationship between disease severity and magnitude of exposure to infected people has been much studied in COVID-19.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However we do have two Chinese studies indicating that severe cases of COVID-19 are more common in those who had frequent long-term exposure to other patients (i.e. sharing a household with many other patients) and less likely in those who have had transient contact with patients (as in travel to an epidemic-affected province.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Viral Load in Other Human Coronaviruses&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;_SARS _&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 75 SARS patients, there was no difference in the rate of positive viral RNA samples at diagnosis between patients who later developed ARDS and those who did not.[16]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 133 SARS patients, initial viral load was significantly (p = 0.025) associated with developing ARDS, and with shorter survival time (p = 0.006).[17]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 12 SARS patients, viral RNA levels were 30x higher in patients who required ICU admission than in those who didn’t (p &amp;lt; 0.005).[18]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 154 SARS patients, viral load in nasopharyngeal aspirated was associated (p &amp;lt; 0.01) with diarrhea, oxygen desaturation, mechanical ventilation, and death. Death was 54x as likely in patients positive for viral RNA than negative. [19]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;MERS&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 17 MERS patients, viral load was nonsignificantly (p = 0.06) higher in severe than mild cases.[20]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 21 MERS patients, blood positivity for MERS RNA was associated with much lower survival (p = 0.017) and higher rates of needing mechanical ventilation (p = 0.003).  Higher respiratory viral load was not associated with survival.[21]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 14 MERS patients, viral load was not significantly associated with mortality but plasma and respiratory viral loads were significantly higher in severe than mild cases.[22]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 102 MERS patients, respiratory viral titers were significantly (p = 0.0087) higher in patients who died than patients who survived.[23]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The evidence seems very consistent that_ higher viral load correlates with more severe and deadly disease_ in both SARS and MERS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Exposure Effects in Other Human Coronaviruses&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Among 80 health care workers in Singapore exposed to SARS, 45 were serologically positive for the virus. Of those 45, healthcare workers were significantly more likely to be asymptomatic (p = 0.025) if they used masks.[24]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the SARS epidemic in Hong Kong, there was no significant association between the risk of death and any disease source (household, hospital, community-acquired, airplane, or none of the above.)[25]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1649 SARS patients in Beijing, contact with a SARS patient prior to illness was not a significant predictor of mortality.[26]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Healthcare workers with confirmed MERS infection were younger, more likely to be female, and less likely to have comorbidities disease than other cases of MERS. They also had significantly (p &amp;lt; 0.001) lower risk of death and higher chance of being asymptomatic.[27]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MERS patients have a higher risk of mortality (HR = 2.9, p= 0.001) from hospital-acquired infections as opposed to other routes of infection such as household contacts or camels; even after adjusting for age and comorbidities.[28]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Healthcare workers may be exposed to larger doses of SARS or MERS, but it doesn’t show up in increased risk of death or severe disease for healthcare workers, possibly because healthcare workers tend to be younger than other patients.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hospital-acquired MERS infections are more deadly than other sources of infection, but this may be confounded by the fact that patients who are already in hospitals for other reasons tend to be sicker.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The one piece of evidence from SARS and MERS that points to low-dose exposure being safer is that wearing masks is more likely to result in asymptomatic SARS infection than not wearing masks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dose-Response Effects in Other Viruses: Human Studies&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Humans have been experimentally exposed to viruses (usually with milder effects than SARS or MERS) in a few challenge trials; this can help us ascertain whether there’s a dose-response effect to the quantity of initial viral exposure on the severity of the disease symptoms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Adenovirus Type 4&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 16 military recruits, the probability of infection varied with the dose of adenovirus they were exposed to, but the probability of illness did not.[29]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Echovirus&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 127 adult volunteers inoculated with various doses of ECHO-11 virus, there was a dose-response relationship with infectivity, but dose had no effect on the severity of upper respiratory symptoms in the infected group.  On the other hand, high-dose cases were significantly more likely than low-dose cases to have lower respiratory symptoms (cough, sore throat, laryngitis).  Prior challenge reduced symptoms upon rechallenge, and more for the high-dose-prior-exposed than the low-dose-prior-exposed group.[30]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Influenza&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Across 36 studies with different doses and strains, there was no association of higher doses of influenza with higher chance of the subjects becoming ill.[31]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Norovirus&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a study of 57 adults infected with different doses of Norwalk virus, higher doses were associated with significantly (p =0.001) faster time before symptom onset and longer (p = 0.04) duration of illness, as well as a dose-response relationship in probability of infection.[32]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Respiratory Synctial Virus&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 35 adult volunteers, there was no association between the dose of RSV administered and the viral load or the probability of infection.  Symptom severity, however, as well as cytokine levels, correlated closely with viral load, both across patients and within patients over time.[33]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Volunteers infected with low-dose RSV did not develop illness (0/16), while volunteers infected with high-dose RSV did develop colds (6/17). Illness was independent of the amount of viral shedding.[34]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 36 volunteers infected with high or low dose RSV, higher doses were associated with higher risk of infection but not higher risk of symptomatic illness.[35]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Rhinovirus&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 155 young adult volunteers infected with different doses of rhinovirus, daily symptom scores were consistently higher in those exposed to higher doses.  Higher antibody titers and higher doses of virus were associated with higher rates of infection.[36]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Rotavirus&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a study of 62 adult volunteers experimentally infected with different doses of rotavirus, there was a dose-response relationship between the concentration of virus and the probability of infection, but there was no relationship between the virus dose and the probability of experiencing symptoms.[37]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whether higher initial doses of virus correlate with more severe symptoms or higher probability of having symptoms at all, seems to depend on the virus.  There is no relationship between dose and symptom severity in human volunteers exposed to adenovirus, influenza, and rotavirus, but there is a relationship in echovirus, rhinovirus, and norovirus, and the results are ambiguous in respiratory synctial virus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It remains unclear how well any of these observations translate to COVID-19.  Unfortunately there were no studies comparing the effect of dose on the symptoms of any of the mild human coronaviruses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dose-Response Effects in Other Viruses: Animal Studies&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ebola&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Exposure to 100 plaque-forming units of Ebola virus in the nose was lethal to macaques; but exposure to 10 plaque-forming units caused no clinical symptoms or detectable antibodies or viral RNA.[38]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;EEV&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eastern Equine Encephalitis Virus is lethal in high doses in macaques (6/6 animals died) but less severe in low-dose exposure (2/6 animals died and clinical scores were lower). [39]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;_Herpes _&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Serial dilutions of the baboon herpesvirus HPV2 inoculated into mice showed a dose-response curve with higher doses resulting in higher rates of infection, CNS symptoms, and death.[40]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Influenza&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was a dose-response relationship between initial inoculation dose, probability of infection, and probability of death, in H5N1 and H7N1 influenza  in turkeys, chickens, and ducks.[41]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Probability of infection, probability of clinical signs, and survival time all varied dose-dependently by the inoculation dose of H5N1 in pigeons.[42]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A H0N1 strain of influenza in mice had a dose-response relationship for both infectiousness and mortality; it was more deadly when introduced to the respiratory tract than intranasally.[43]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A PR8 strain of influenza has a dose-response relationship with serum viral load, weight loss, clinical score, and mortality. The low dose and high dose groups had similar antibody and leukocyte recruitment levels as the high dose, but no mortality. [44]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;MERS&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In transgenic mice, there was a dose-response effect in lethality for exposure to MERS virus: it killed 50% of the mice at a dose of 10 TCID50, compared to 25% at 1.25 TCID50 and 100% at 100 TCID50.[45]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;PEDV&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PEDV is a coronavirus that causes diarrhea in pigs. It has a dose-response relationship to symptoms: 0.056 TCID50 caused diarrhea in 25% of piglets while 0.56 TCID50 and higher caused diarrhea in 100% of piglets.[46]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;SARS&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both mice and guinea pigs exposed to SARS virus had a higher probability of increased rectal temperature at higher doses of virus exposure.  For guinea pigs, ID50 = 5.47 log CPE50, or 50% of guinea pigs were infected at 5.47 * log (the dose at which 50% of cells died).[47]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;SIV&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simian immunodeficiency virus, closely related to HIV, had a dose-response relationship with the probability of infection in macaque monkeys, but steady-state (2-week) viral load among those infected did not correlate with initial dose.  There was no correlation between survival time and dose.[48]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Low-dose challenge with SIV successfully produced “silent infection” (no symptoms or viral RNA but virus-specific T cell proliferation.) However, when these monkeys were exposed to a high dose of SIV, they were not immune but became infected and developed AIDS-like disease at the same rate as naive monkeys.[49]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dose-response relationships between virus inoculum and infection rate or death seem to be common in animal studies, and consistently, including in coronaviruses, higher doses cause more severe symptoms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, in at least one case (SIV) a dose of virus that was low enough to produce asymptomatic infection did _not _produce immunity to future exposures, so we can’t assume that low-dose exposure always brings immunity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[1]Shah, Sweta, et al. “Initial Observations with Molecular Testing for COVID-19 in a Private Hospital in Mumbai, India.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[2]Yu, Xia, et al. “SARS-CoV-2 viral load in sputum correlates with risk of COVID-19 progression.” &lt;em&gt;Critical Care&lt;/em&gt; 24.1 (2020): 1-4.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[3]Zheng, Shufa, et al. “Viral load dynamics and disease severity in patients infected with SARS-CoV-2 in Zhejiang province, China, January-March 2020: retrospective cohort study.” &lt;em&gt;bmj&lt;/em&gt; 369 (2020).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[4]Liu, Yang, et al. “Correlation Between Relative Nasopharyngeal Virus RNA Load and Lymphocyte Count Disease Severity in Patients with COVID-19.” &lt;em&gt;Viral Immunology&lt;/em&gt; (2020).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[5]To, Kelvin Kai-Wang, et al. “Temporal profiles of viral load in posterior oropharyngeal saliva samples and serum antibody responses during infection by SARS-CoV-2: an observational cohort study.” &lt;em&gt;The Lancet Infectious Diseases&lt;/em&gt; (2020).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[6]Zou, Lirong, et al. “SARS-CoV-2 viral load in upper respiratory specimens of infected patients.” &lt;em&gt;New England Journal of Medicine&lt;/em&gt; 382.12 (2020): 1177-1179.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[7]Young, Barnaby Edward, et al. “Epidemiologic features and clinical course of patients infected with SARS-CoV-2 in Singapore.” &lt;em&gt;Jama&lt;/em&gt; 323.15 (2020): 1488-1494.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[8]Wu, Jing, et al. “Clinical Characteristics and Outcomes of Discharged COVID-19 Patients with Reoccurrence of SARS-CoV-2 RNA in a County Hospital of Western Chongqing, China.” &lt;em&gt;China (4/14/2020)&lt;/em&gt; (2020).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[9]He, Xi, et al. “Temporal dynamics in viral shedding and transmissibility of COVID-19.” &lt;em&gt;Nature medicine&lt;/em&gt; (2020): 1-4.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[10]Lui, Grace, et al. “Viral dynamics of SARS-CoV-2 across a spectrum of disease severity in COVID-19.” &lt;em&gt;The Journal of Infection&lt;/em&gt; (2020).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[11]Lescure, Francois-Xavier, et al. “Clinical and virological data of the first cases of COVID-19 in Europe: a case series.” &lt;em&gt;The Lancet Infectious Diseases&lt;/em&gt; (2020).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[12]Qiu, Haiyan, et al. “Clinical and epidemiological features of 36 children with coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) in Zhejiang, China: an observational cohort study.” &lt;em&gt;The Lancet Infectious Diseases&lt;/em&gt; (2020).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[13]Xu, Xiao-Wei, et al. “Clinical findings in a group of patients infected with the 2019 novel coronavirus (SARS-Cov-2) outside of Wuhan, China: retrospective case series.” &lt;em&gt;bmj&lt;/em&gt; 368 (2020).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[14]Li, Xiaochen, et al. “Risk factors for severity and mortality in adult COVID-19 inpatients in Wuhan.” &lt;em&gt;Journal of Allergy and Clinical Immunology&lt;/em&gt; (2020).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[15]Shi, Y., et al. “Host susceptibility to severe COVID-19: a retrospective analysis of 487 case outside Wuhan.” (2020).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[16]Peiris, Joseph Sriyal Malik, et al. “Clinical progression and viral load in a community outbreak of coronavirus-associated SARS pneumonia: a prospective study.” &lt;em&gt;The Lancet&lt;/em&gt; 361.9371 (2003): 1767-1772.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[17]Chu, Chung-Ming, et al. “Initial viral load and the outcomes of SARS.” &lt;em&gt;Cmaj&lt;/em&gt; 171.11 (2004): 1349-1352.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[18] Ng, Enders KO, et al. “Quantitative analysis and prognostic implication of SARS coronavirus RNA in the plasma and serum of patients with severe acute respiratory syndrome.” &lt;em&gt;Clinical chemistry&lt;/em&gt; 49.12 (2003): 1976-1980.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[19]Hung, I. F. N., et al. “Viral loads in clinical specimens and SARS manifestations.” Emerging infectious diseases 10.9 (2004): 1550.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[20]Oh, Myoung-don, et al. “Viral load kinetics of MERS coronavirus infection.” &lt;em&gt;New England Journal of Medicine&lt;/em&gt; 375.13 (2016): 1303-1305.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[21]Kim, So Yeon, et al. “Viral RNA in blood as indicator of severe outcome in Middle East respiratory syndrome coronavirus infection.” &lt;em&gt;Emerging infectious diseases&lt;/em&gt; 22.10 (2016): 1813.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[22]Min, Chan-Ki, et al. “Comparative and kinetic analysis of viral shedding and immunological responses in MERS patients representing a broad spectrum of disease severity.” Scientific reports 6.1 (2016): 1-12.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[23] Feikin, Daniel R., et al. “Association of higher MERS-CoV virus load with severe disease and death, Saudi Arabia, 2014.” Emerging infectious diseases 21.11 (2015): 2029.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;APA&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[24] Wilder-Smith, Annelies, et al. “Asymptomatic SARS coronavirus infection among healthcare workers, Singapore.” Emerging infectious diseases 11.7 (2005): 1142.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[25]Leung, Gabriel M., et al. “The epidemiology of severe acute respiratory syndrome in the 2003 Hong Kong epidemic: an analysis of all 1755 patients.” Annals of internal medicine 141.9 (2004): 662-673.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[26]Liu, Min, et al. “Risk factors for SARS-related deaths in 2003, Beijing.” Biomedical and Environmental Sciences 19.5 (2006): 336.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[27]Elkholy, Amgad A., et al. “MERS-CoV infection among healthcare workers and risk factors for death: Retrospective analysis of all laboratory-confirmed cases reported to WHO from 2012 to 2 June 2018.” Journal of infection and public health (2019).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[28]Ahmed, Anwar E. “The predictors of 3-and 30-day mortality in 660 MERS-CoV patients.” BMC infectious diseases 17.1 (2017): 615.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[29]Couch, R. B., et al. “The minimal infectious dose of adenovirus type 4; the case for natural transmission by viral aerosol.” &lt;em&gt;Transactions of the American Clinical and Climatological Association&lt;/em&gt; 80 (1969): 205.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[30]Saliba, Gilbert S., Sylvia L. Franklin, and George Gee Jackson. “ECHO-11 as a respiratory virus: quantitation of infection in man.” &lt;em&gt;The Journal of clinical investigation&lt;/em&gt; 47.6 (1968): 1303-1313.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[31]Yezli, Saber, and Jonathan A. Otter. “Minimum infective dose of the major human respiratory and enteric viruses transmitted through food and the environment.” &lt;em&gt;Food and Environmental Virology&lt;/em&gt; 3.1 (2011): 1-30.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[32]Atmar, Robert L., et al. “Determination of the 50% human infectious dose for Norwalk virus.” &lt;em&gt;The Journal of infectious diseases&lt;/em&gt; 209.7 (2014): 1016-1022.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[33]DeVincenzo, John P., et al. “Viral load drives disease in humans experimentally infected with respiratory syncytial virus.” &lt;em&gt;American journal of respiratory and critical care medicine&lt;/em&gt; 182.10 (2010): 1305-1314.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[34]Mills, John, et al. “Experimental respiratory syncytial virus infection of adults: possible mechanisms of resistance to infection and illness.” &lt;em&gt;The Journal of Immunology&lt;/em&gt; 107.1 (1971): 123-130.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[35]Lee, F. Eun-Hyung, et al. “Experimental infection of humans with A2 respiratory syncytial virus.” &lt;em&gt;Antiviral research&lt;/em&gt; 63.3 (2004): 191-196.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[36]Hendley, J. Owen, William P. Edmondson Jr, and Jack M. Gwaltney Jr. “Relation between naturally acquired immunity and infectivity of two rhinoviruses in volunteers.” &lt;em&gt;Journal of Infectious Diseases&lt;/em&gt; 125.3 (1972): 243-248.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[37]Ward, Richard L., et al. “Human rotavirus studies in volunteers: determination of infectious dose and serological response to infection.” &lt;em&gt;Journal of Infectious Diseases&lt;/em&gt; 154.5 (1986): 871-880.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[38]Mire, Chad E., et al. “Oral and conjunctival exposure of nonhuman primates to low doses of Ebola Makona virus.” The Journal of infectious diseases 214.suppl_3 (2016): S263-S267.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[39]Reed, Douglas S., et al. “Severe encephalitis in cynomolgus macaques exposed to aerosolized eastern equine encephalitis virus.” The Journal of infectious diseases 196.3 (2007): 441-450.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[40]Ritchey, J. W., et al. “Comparative pathology of infections with baboon and African green monkey α-herpesviruses in mice.” &lt;em&gt;Journal of comparative pathology&lt;/em&gt; 127.2-3 (2002): 150-161.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[41]Aldous, E. W., et al. “Infection dynamics of highly pathogenic avian influenza and virulent avian paramyxovirus type 1 viruses in chickens, turkeys and ducks.” &lt;em&gt;Avian Pathology&lt;/em&gt; 39.4 (2010): 265-273.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[42] Phonaknguen, Rassameepen, et al. “Minimal susceptibility to highly pathogenic avian influenza H5N1 viral infection of pigeons (Columba livia) and potential transmission of the virus to comingled domestic chickens.” &lt;em&gt;Kasetsart J-Nat Sci&lt;/em&gt; 47 (2013): 720-732.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[43]Yetter, Robert A., et al. “Outcome of influenza infection: effect of site of initial infection and heterotypic immunity.” &lt;em&gt;Infection and immunity&lt;/em&gt; 29.2 (1980): 654-662.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[44]Powell, Timothy J., et al. “The immune system provides a strong response to even a low exposure to virus.” Clinical immunology 119.1 (2006): 87-94&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[45]Tao, Xinrong, et al. “Characterization and demonstration of the value of a lethal mouse model of Middle East respiratory syndrome coronavirus infection and disease.” &lt;em&gt;Journal of virology&lt;/em&gt; 90.1 (2016): 57-67.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[46]Neumann, Eric J., and William F. Hall. “Disease Control, Prevention, and Elimination.” &lt;em&gt;Diseases of Swine&lt;/em&gt; (2019): 123-157.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[47]Chepurnov, A. A., A. A. Dadaeva, and E. M. Malkova. “Symptoms of infection caused by SARS coronavirus in laboratory mice and guinea pigs.” &lt;em&gt;Doklady Biological Sciences&lt;/em&gt;. Vol. 397. No. 1. Nature Publishing Group, 2004.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[48]Holterman, Lennart, et al. “The rate of progression to AIDS is independent of virus dose in simian immunodeficiency virus-infected macaques.” &lt;em&gt;Journal of General Virology&lt;/em&gt; 81.7 (2000): 1719-1726&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[49]Dittmer, Ulf, et al. “Repeated exposure of rhesus macaques to low doses of simian immunodeficiency virus (SIV) did not protect them against the consequences of a high-dose SIV challenge.” Journal of general virology 76.6 (1995): 1307-1315.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="covid-19" /><category term="lit-review" /><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Avoiding Intubation in COVID-19 Silent Hypoxemia</title><link href="https://srconstantin.github.io/2020/05/04/silent-hypoxemia.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Avoiding Intubation in COVID-19 Silent Hypoxemia" /><published>2020-05-04T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-05-04T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://srconstantin.github.io/2020/05/04/silent-hypoxemia</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://srconstantin.github.io/2020/05/04/silent-hypoxemia.html">&lt;p&gt;One predictable feature of a novel disease is that initial guidelines for treatment may need to be revised, as medical understanding of the disease evolves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Initially, patients with COVID-19 experiencing severe respiratory distress were supposed to be intubated and placed on ventilators early, and non-invasive ventilation procedures like CPAP, BiPAP, and high-flow nasal cannula were to be avoided because they might spread the disease.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the course of the pandemic, we’ve seen additional evidence that a population of COVID-19 patients can be treated effectively with CPAP/BiPAP, and may not even need to be invasively ventilated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These patients are what’s informally called the “silent hypoxemic” – they have very low oxygen levels, but are otherwise surprisingly functional (they can talk, have minimal altered mental status, etc) and they do _not _have the noncompliant lungs typical of ARDS. Therefore, following typical ventilation procedures like ARDSNet, in which patients are intubated when their oxygen saturation drops below a certain point, and placed on mechanical ventilation with high pressures, is actually a _bad _idea.  Excessive PEEP for compliant lungs can cause barotrauma; and intubation in general carries risks (of e.g. hospital-acquired infections, damage to the airway, and PTSD) so if a patient can recover with _non-invasive _respiratory support, it’s safer to avoid intubation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This clinical picture was once purely anecdotal, but the data is starting to come in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Helmet CPAP, in which a continuous positive pressure of oxygenated air is administered through a clear helmet that covers the patient’s whole head, has been extensively used for COVID-19 patients in Italy. The helmet is more comfortable than traditional CPAP masks, and has a tighter seal, to avoid spreading virus particles to healthcare workers.  The RICU of the L. Sacco University hospital in Milan had 75% of their severe COVID-19 patients on helmet CPAP, and had an in-hospital mortality rate of only 25%, compared to Seattle ICUs, which had a 50% in-hospital mortality rate and had 100% of patients on invasive mechanical ventilation.[1]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Helmet CPAP is much less likely to disperse exhaled air than conventional CPAP, making the risks of infection to healthcare workers lower; a study found that air only dispersed 2.5 cm from the helmet.[6]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Italian intensive care physicians observed that 50% of the 150 severe COVID-19 patients in their ICU were the “silent hypoxemia” type, characterized by “severe hypoxemia often associated with near normal respiratory symptom compliance.”  They describe COVID-19 pneumonia as belonging to two separate “phenotypes”, Type L and Type H.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Type L COVID-19 has low elastance (= normally compliant lungs), low lung recruitability (most lung tissue is receiving air), but extreme hypoxemia due to ventilation-perfusion mismatch.  That is, the lung is receiving oxygen but not blood flow, so the blood doesn’t get properly oxygenated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These Type L patients may improve or suddenly worsen. Increased inflammation and negative intrathoracic pressure can cause swelling and fluid buildup in the lungs.  (High inspiratory pressures literally suck fluid from capillaries into lung tissue, which contributes to pulmonary edema.)  Increased edema transitions the patient to the Type H phenotype: high elastance (= noncompliant lungs), high recruitability (= lots of non-aerated lung tissue), and atelectasis (= collapsed alveoli).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This clinical picture implies that Type L patients should be treated noninvasively with high concentrations of oxygen (through masks or, in dyspneic patients, high-flow nasal cannula, CPAP, or BiPAP).  Patients at risk of transitioning to type H, as measured by high inspiratory pressures, should be intubated, and type H patients should be placed on standard invasive ventilation for severe ARDS.[2]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A case report from Norway illustrates a typical case of “silent hypoxemia” in COVID-19: a man in his sixties with an O2 saturation of 66% who nevertheless seemed calm, was “smiling bravely”, and breathing almost silently.  Hypocapnia (low CO2) meant there was little or no sensation of breathlessness despite the extremely low oxygen saturation.[5]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Three ICU doctors at the University College London hospital argued in the _Lancet Respiratory Medicine _against early intubation for COVID-19, saying&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Early intubation of a patient with known or suspected COVID-19 with respiratory distress could result in the intubation and mechanical ventilation of patients who would have otherwise improved on CPAP or NIV”.[3]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They note that the highest incidence of disease transmission to healthcare workers was on general wards, not ICU, i.e. where healthcare staff were least likely to wear personal protective equipment, and that NIV did not increase the risk of disease transmission during the SARS epidemic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, a statement by tropical disease experts about treating COVID-19 in low-resource areas argues&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It seems that in a significant proportion of relatively younger patients, hypoxemia, even less than 88%, is reasonably well tolerated and not accompanied by severe respiratory distress or exhaustion. With the current experience, the trigger for intubation should, within certain limits, probably not be based on hypoxemia alone but more on respiratory distress and fatigue….Invasive ventilation can save lives in patients with severe respiratory distress. However, it can also aggravate or even cause damage,including barotrauma (air leaks, caused by high ventilation pressures), volutrauma (pulmonary edema, due to large tidal volumes), atelectrauma (repetitive opening and closing of vulnerable lung parts with atelectasis), biotrauma (local inflammation with spill to the systemic circulation of inflammatory mediators, bacteria, or bacterial products), and oxytrauma (by free oxygen radicals).”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The authors recommend, when COVID-19 patients are intubated, using lower PEEP and lower tidal volume than would be typical for ARDS, to avoid ventilator-induced injury.[4]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Early awake self-proning in COVID-19 patients can be very beneficial for the “silent hypoxemic” or “type L” patient population. One emergency department in New York City found that in 50 patients, the median SpO2 was 80% at triage, 84% after supplemental oxygen, and 94% after patients were encouraged to lie on their stomachs (in the prone position.)  [7]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“In New York City, during the early stages of the COVID-19 pandemic, patients presented en masse with moderate to severe hypoxia. Some of these patients were distressed, quickly deteriorated and required endotracheal intubation.  COVID-19 produced another group of patients whose pathophysiology confounded existing disease patterns, however. These patients had low oxygen saturations (SpO2 &amp;lt;90%), but were not in significant respiratory distress and often appeared clinically well; this group has been informally referred to as happy hypoxemics.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the authors of the above article, Richard Levitan, an emergency physician in New York City, wrote a New York Times op-ed [8] about this phenomenon.  They were seeing COVID-19 pneumonia in nearly every patient who came into the emergency department, even those without respiratory symptoms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The patient stabbed in the shoulder, whom we X-rayed because we worried he had a collapsed lung, actually had Covid pneumonia. In patients on whom we did CT scans because they were injured in falls, we coincidentally found Covid pneumonia. Elderly patients who had passed out for unknown reasons and a number of diabetic patients were found to have it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“And here is what really surprised us: These patients did not report any sensation of breathing problems, even though their chest X-rays showed diffuse pneumonia and their oxygen was below normal. How could this be?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Patients compensate for the low oxygen in their blood by breathing faster and deeper — and this happens without their realizing it. This silent hypoxia, and the patient’s physiological response to it, causes even more inflammation and more air sacs to collapse, and the pneumonia worsens until oxygen levels plummet. In effect, patients are injuring their own lungs by breathing harder and harder. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.esicm.org/wp-content/uploads/2020/04/684_author-proof.pdf&quot;&gt;Twenty percent&lt;/a&gt; of Covid pneumonia patients then go on to a second and deadlier phase of lung injury. Fluid builds up and the lungs become stiff, carbon dioxide rises, and patients develop acute respiratory failure.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr. Levitan recommends that healthy people, and people who test positive for COVID-19, get pulse oximeters – available over at the counter at the drugstore – to monitor their oxygen levels _before _they get sick enough to need a hospital.  Silent hypoxemia doesn’t come with symptoms, so most infected patients don’t get supplemental oxygen until they’ve progressed to severe lung injury that requires ventilation.  If they caught the problem earlier, they could get supplemental oxygen and recover without ever needing to be ventilated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[1]Radovanovic, Dejan, et al. “Helmet CPAP to Treat Acute Hypoxemic Respiratory Failure in Patients with Covid-19: A Management Strategy Proposal.” &lt;em&gt;Journal of Clinical Medicine&lt;/em&gt; 9.4 (2020): 1191.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[2]Gattinoni, Luciano, et al. “COVID-19 pneumonia: different respiratory treatments for different phenotypes?.” &lt;em&gt;Intensive care medicine&lt;/em&gt; (2020): 1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[3]Arulkumaran, Nishkantha, et al. “Use of non-invasive ventilation for patients with COVID-19: a cause for concern?.” &lt;em&gt;The Lancet. Respiratory Medicine&lt;/em&gt; (2020).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[4]Dondorp, Arjen M., et al. “Respiratory Support in Novel Coronavirus Disease (COVID-19) Patients, with a Focus on Resource-Limited Settings.” &lt;em&gt;The American Journal of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene&lt;/em&gt; (2020): tpmd200283.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[5]Ottestad, William, Mari Seim, and Jens Otto Mæhlen. “COVID-19 with silent hypoxemia.” &lt;em&gt;Tidsskrift for Den norske legeforening&lt;/em&gt; (2020).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[6]Whittle, Jessica S., et al. “Respiratory Support for Adult Patients with COVID‐19.” &lt;em&gt;Journal of the American College of Emergency Physicians Open&lt;/em&gt; (2020).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[7]Caputo, Nicholas D., Reuben J. Strayer, and Richard Levitan. “Early Self‐Proning in Awake, Non‐intubated Patients in the Emergency Department: A Single ED’s Experience during the COVID‐19 Pandemic.” &lt;em&gt;Academic Emergency Medicine&lt;/em&gt; (2020).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[8]&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2020/04/20/opinion/sunday/coronavirus-testing-pneumonia.html&quot;&gt;https://www.nytimes.com/2020/04/20/opinion/sunday/coronavirus-testing-pneumonia.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="covid-19" /><category term="lit-review" /><summary type="html">One predictable feature of a novel disease is that initial guidelines for treatment may need to be revised, as medical understanding of the disease evolves.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Antibody Testing for COVID-19</title><link href="https://srconstantin.github.io/2020/04/27/antibody-testing.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Antibody Testing for COVID-19" /><published>2020-04-27T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-04-27T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://srconstantin.github.io/2020/04/27/antibody-testing</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://srconstantin.github.io/2020/04/27/antibody-testing.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/antibody.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;antibody&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What’s In A COVID-19 Antibody Test?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As of April 24, there are 4 COVID-19 antibody tests approved for diagnostic purposes in the US, and 44 approved for diagnostic or research purposes around the world.[1]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of these are ELISA tests, which detect the presence of antibodies to viral proteins, such as the N (nucleocapsid) protein or S (spike) protein.  The subject’s blood serum is incubated with the protein, and then washed with antibody-dye conjugates that fluoresce in proportion to the concentration of bound antibody/viral protein complexes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some tests, such as one approved in Singapore, is a viral neutralization assay that tests the patient’s serum for its ability to neutralize viral replication in vitro.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, some are rapid tests, which screen for the presence or absence of antibodies to the viral protein, but cannot measure the concentration. These can be very quick (&amp;lt;15 min) to perform, but tell us nothing about the concentration of the antibody.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Viral neutralization tests, compared to ELISA can tell us more about how likely the antibodies are to protect against infection, but they also take longer than ELISA tests (3-5 days vs 1-5 hours.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How Accurate Are COVID-19 Antibody Tests at Predicting Serum Viral RNA?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Manufacturer&lt;/strong&gt;
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Test Type&lt;/strong&gt;
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sensitivity&lt;/strong&gt;
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Specificity&lt;/strong&gt;
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sample Size (# of individuals)&lt;/strong&gt;
   &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;USTC (Hefei, China)
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;IgG/IgA rapid test for S protein receptor binding domain
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;99.2%
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;100%
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;570
   &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Jiangsu Medomics
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;IgM/IgG lateral flow immunoassay for S protein receptor binding domain
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;88.66%
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;90.63%
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;525
   &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;VITROS
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;ELISA against spike protein
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;83%
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;100%
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;436
   &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Cellex
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;IgM/IgG lateral flow immunoassay against N protein
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;93.8%
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;96.0%
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;378
   &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Euroimmun
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;IgG/IgA rapid test for S1 protein
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;94%
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;98%
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;310
   &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Zhejiang Orient
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;IgG rapid test
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;93.1%
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;99.2%
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;153
   &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Wantai
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;ELISA for S protein receptor binding domain
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;93%
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;100%
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;112
   &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Mount Sinai
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;ELISA for S protein
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;100%
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;100%
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;111
   &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;NIH
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;LIPS test for N protein 
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;67% all, 100% 14 days after symptoms
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;100%
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;81
   &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Dynamiker
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Rapid IgG/IgM
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;90%
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;100%
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;62
   &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;CTK Biotech
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Rapid IgG/IgM
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;90%
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;100%
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;62
   &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Unnamed
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Rapid IgG/IgM
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;36.4%
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;88.9%
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;39
   &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Beijing Diagreat Biotechnologies
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Rapid IgG/IgM
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;83%
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;93%
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;30
   &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Chinese-designed IgM/IgG combined assay for COVID-19 (Jiangsu Medomics)  testing for antibodies against the receptor binding domain of the spike protein, tested on confirmed COVID-19 cases selected from hospitals in 6 different provinces and healthy volunteers, had a sensitivity of 88.66% and a specificity of 90.63%.[2]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A German-designed IgG/IgA assay against the spike protein S1 of SARS-CoV-2 (Euroimmun) had a 100% specificity (did not react against healthy volunteers, patients with non-coronavirus viruses, or patients with endemic coronaviruses that cause the common cold.  All 3 SARS-CoV-2 patients got positive tests, for a specificity of 100%. 2/2 SARS-CoV patients also got positive results from this antibody test.  More severe patients had higher antibody titers.[3]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Swedish preprint study evaluating a Chinese-made rapid antibody test (Zhejiang Orient Gene Biotech) on 29 PCR-confirmed COVID-19 patients or convalescents and 100 healthy controls had a sensitivity of 93.1% and specificity of 99.2% for the IgG test. The IgM test had only a 69% sensitivity but a 100% specificity. [4]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Chinese preprint study of RBD antibody kits for combined IgA/IgG antibodies on 330 healthy subjects, 153 patients with non-COVID-19 diseases, and 87 SARS-CoV-2 cases, had a sensitivity of 99.1% and specificity of 100%. IgA levels but not IgM levels were higher in more severe patients (p &amp;lt; 0.0001).[5]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An ELISA test against the SARS-CoV-2 spike protein, developed at Mount Sinai Hospital in the US and approved for diagnostic use, was tested on 17 confirmed COVID-19 cases (3 convalescent, 14 acute) and 94 negative controls collected before the COVID-19 pandemic began.  All 17 COVID-19 patients had antibodies that reacted strongly in the test, while none of the controls did.  Additionally, the concentration of antibody correlates positively to viral neutralization ability (p &amp;lt;0.0001, r = 0.9279).[6]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An independent Danish preprint study of 9 antibody tests on 30 confirmed COVID-19 cases admitted to the ICU and 82 non-COVID-19 patients (healthy blood donors or people with other acute viral infections) found that the Wantai test for the spike protein receptor binding domain had a sensitivity of 93% and specificity of 100%, while the Euroimmun IgA test had a specificity of 93% and sensitivity of 93%.  Point-of-care rapid tests were less sensitive – the Dynamiker and CTK Biotech tests (both IgG/IgM tests) had sensitivities of 90% and specificities of 100%. The best two ELISA tests agreed 93% with each other.[7]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Briefer illnesses (7-13 days vs 14-20 and &amp;gt;21 days) had somewhat lower rates of positive test results, which is consistent with other studies finding that more severe disease correlated with higher antibody levels. [7]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A German study of an unnamed rapid IgG/IgM test on 39 randomly selected patients who were also tested for COVID-19 with RT-PCR (the benchmark), the sensitivity was only 36.4% while the specificity was 88.9%.  (Note that this could include patients who were in the early stages of the disease, when viral RNA is detectable but antibodies are not.)[8]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An Italian study of the Beijing Diagreat Biotechnologies rapid IgG/IgM test on 30 patients admitted to the hospital with either confirmed COVID-19, suspected COVID-19 that turned out to be something else, or asymptomatic controls, the sensitivity was 83% and the specificity was 93%.[9]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A novel type of immunoassay, LIPS (Luciferase Immunoprecipitation System) was  tested on 49 patients with confirmed COVID-19 and 32 blood bank donor controls. None of the controls had a positive result for nucleocapsid antibodies, while 67% of the COVID-19 patients did.  Similarly, none of the controls had a positive result for spike protein antibodies, while 57% of the COVID-19 patients did.  When restricted to samples taken &amp;gt;14 days after symptom onset, the sensitivity and specificity were 100%.[10]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Premarket testing for the Cellex rapid IgG/IgM test evaluated 128 confirmed COVID-19 cases and 250 negative subjects, and found a sensitivity of 93.8% and a specificity of 96.0%.[11]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The VITROS modified ELISA test against spike protein was positive in 30/36 patients with confirmed cases of COVID-19 (sensitivity of 83%) and negative in 100% of 400 non-COVID-19 samples.[12]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Bottom Lines&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All in all, the antibody tests are generally quite specific (at least in patients who have had the disease for at least two weeks) and fairly sensitive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Antibody levels tend to rise over the course of the disease and tend to be higher in more severe cases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How Should We Interpret The Antibody Seroprevalence Data in the US?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Several recent papers have come out with estimates of the prevalence of SARS-CoV-2 in US cities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;PCR Tests of Random Samples in the US&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Out of 131 patients presenting with mild influenza-like symptoms in a Los Angeles clinic, 7 tested positive for SARS-CoV-2, or 5%.[13]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Between March 22 and April 4, all pregnant women delivering at New York Presbyterian and Columbia University hospitals in New York were tested for COVID-19. 15.4% of all pregnant women tested positive for SARS-CoV-2.   Only 12% of the patients who tested positive had COVID-19 symptoms, consistent with a picture in which most infections are asymptomatic.[14]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A screening program of 24 homeless shelters in Seattle, Boston, San Francisco, and Atlanta found 25% of residents and 11% of staff members tested positive for SARS-CoV-2.  This is probably much higher than the general population in those cities since homeless people are sicker than others and living in institutional environments like shelters spreads disease.[20]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;PCR Tests of Random Samples In Other Countries&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Iceland did an extensive testing program for SARS-CoV-2, issuing an open invitation to 10,797 people and random invitations to 2283 people.  In total, 6% of the Icelandic population was screened.  0.6% of the open invitation group and 0.8% of the random invitation group tested positive for the virus.  57% of those who tested positive also reported symptoms of COVID-19.[16]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A study testing 1097 health care workers with mild respiratory symptoms in 9 hospitals in the Netherlands found that 4% tested positive for SARS-CoV-2.[17]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A screening study for SARS-CoV-2 in 1654 UK medical staff with symptoms of cough or fever found 14% tested positive.[22]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;South Korea has one of the largest COVID-19 testing programs in the world, testing 601,660 people between January 3 and April 27, or about 1% of its population. 1.8% of those tested were positive, and 2.3% of the confirmed cases were fatal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Antibody Tests in the US&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A study that recruited participants in Santa Clara County, California through Facebook ads tested 3330 participants with a rapid IgG/IgM test (Premier Biotech.)  This test had previously been found to have an 80% sensitivity rate and 99.5% specificity rate, from combining the manufacturer’s data and an independent experiment, 523 patients in all.[15]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The crude prevalence rate of antibodies in Santa Clara County was 1.5%; after weighting the sample to match Santa Clara County by zipcode, race, and sex, the rate was 2.81%.  Adjusting for the sensitivity and specificity of the test, the estimated prevalence is 2.75%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The authors conclude that, because the prevalence of antibodies is much higher than the number of confirmed cases (there were 985 confirmed cases in Santa Clara County, while this study’s data suggests 48,000-81,000 cases should exist), that COVID-19 is almost always asymptomatic and should have a much lower case fatality rate than previously assumed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t think this conclusion is reasonable.  Confirmed case numbers were low for a long time in the US, even when the pandemic was spreading rapidly, because there was a shortage of tests before the FDA approved several new tests.  Even a serious case of suspected COVID-19 can’t get a diagnostic confirmation if no tests are available.  It makes more sense to suppose that the confirmed case numbers (and, thus, the confirmed fatality numbers) are underestimates than to take those numbers literally and infer that the disease kills only 0.1-0.2% of those infected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Miami-Dade County in Florida has embarked on a random antibody screening program, and preliminary results from 1800 individuals indicate a rate of 6%, which is 16.5x higher than the number of confirmed cases captured by hospitals and testing sites alone.[24] About half of the individuals who tested positive had no symptoms.[25]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A random antibody test of New York State residents sampled from shoppers at grocery and big-box stores found 21% in New York City, 17% in Long Island, 12% in Westchester, and &amp;lt;4% in the rest of the state, had antibodies to the virus.[26]  These numbers may be overestimates because people who are shopping are less likely to be practicing social distancing and thus are more at risk for infection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Preliminary results from a random antibody screening program in Los Angeles County found that 4.1% of residents tested positive for SARS-CoV-19 antibodies.[29]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Antibody Tests in Other Countries&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1000 blood samples from blood donors in Scotland were screened for SARS-CoV-2 neutralizing antibodies; 0.5% tested positive. Note that blood donors are healthier on average than the general population, since donors with a history of recent respiratory infection are turned away; so this serves as more of a lower bound on the prevalence of SARS-CoV-2 antibodies in the Scottish population.[19]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Other Measurements of Prevalence&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SARS-CoV-2 levels in the wastewater of a major water treatment facility in Massachussetts suggest that roughly 5% of the stool samples in the state were positive for the virus between March 18-25, a number much higher than the 0.026% prevalence rate for confirmed SARS-CoV-2 cases in Massachusetts. This points towards COVID-19 being underdiagnosed, as we’d expect given the shortage of tests.[18]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A New York Times report on April 27th observed that New York City had triple the number of all-cause deaths compared to historical baselines, and other countries also had higher rates of all-cause mortality than their historical baselines. (Spain, 67% above normal; Equador, 83% above normal; Jakarta, Indonesia, 57% above normal.) These numbers can’t be confounded by any possible over-diagnosis of COVID-19, and constitute clear evidence that the epidemic is killing people. Moreover, there are more all-cause deaths than can be accounted for by confirmed COVID-19 deaths alone; so either the disease is underdiagnosed or people are dying from other effects of the pandemic (such as a shortage of hospital care.)[21]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In March 2020, the number of LA County cases of influenza-like symptoms was double that in March of the past 4 years, despite it being past the peak of flu season.[13]  This likewise points to COVID-19 causing a large number of symptomatic cases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Conclusions&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most screens of random population samples – that is, _not _specifically selected for having symptoms or for having contacts with COVID-19 – seem to show 0.5-5% prevalence for the disease, in different cities and countries, whether measured by antibodies, viral RNA, or even wastewater RNA concentrations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prevalence numbers are higher among high-risk populations (healthcare workers and homeless people) and _much _higher in New York City, the center of the US epidemic and a very dense population.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the US specifically, where testing has been scarce, this means that the number of confirmed cases has been underestimated by at least an order of magnitude.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The antibody screening experiments have been criticized on the grounds that antibody tests are not perfectly accurate. I don’t think this is a valid argument against the main point (that there are probably &amp;gt;10x as many true cases as confirmed cases in the US.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Antibody tests vary in their _sensitivity _(how likely they are to give a positive result in a real infection) and tend to not show up as positive until 2 weeks after the onset of symptoms.  But, if anything, this should mean the true positive rate is even _larger _than the numbers in the studies. Antibody tests tend to have fairly high _specificity _– the maximum % of false positives I’ve seen reported is 10% – and so even if 10% of the reported positives are false ones, that would still mean that the seroprevalence of COVID-19 is many times higher than the rate of confirmed cases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some commentators have concluded that this means that the danger of COVID-19 has been overstated; that the risk of dying given a SARS-CoV-19 infection is much lower than previously supposed.  I think this is misleading.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The official case fatality rate (# of confirmed COVID-19 deaths/ # of confirmed COVID-19 cases) may be an overestimate, because when testing is scarce, more severe cases are more likely to be tested. Right now the cumulative global case fatality rate is a whopping 7% and the US case fatality rate is 2.8%.[27][28]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, estimating an infection fatality rate defined by # of confirmed deaths / expected # of antibody-positive individuals is likely to be an &lt;em&gt;underestimate&lt;/em&gt;, since if testing capacity is scarce, we can expect even some fatal COVID-19 cases to go unconfirmed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These “optimistic” estimates of infection fatality rate are about 0.3% for Santa Clara County, 0.2% for L.A. County, 0.1% for Miami-Dade County, and 0.7% for New York City.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we compare these estimates to two countries that had extensive COVID-19 testing, Iceland and South Korea, the cumulative case fatality rate for Iceland is 0.5% (in line with the optimistic US estimates) and the rate for South Korea is 2.3% (quite a bit higher than the optimistic US estimates.)  So it’s not clear what conclusion to draw from international comparisons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One consideration is that the South Korean testing program is not a random sample of the population, though it was extensive – people with symptoms or connections to COVID-19 patients are prioritized for testing.  So its 2.3% mortality rate may be an overestimate as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we consider the 3x elevated all-cause mortality rate in NYC, and assume that _all _excess deaths are COVID-19 deaths, and that 21% of New Yorkers are infected, this gives a “pessimistic” estimate of 1.2% of COVID-19 infections being fatal in NYC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My current best guess is that the true estimate of infection fatality rate in the US is somewhere between the “optimistic” and “pessimistic” probabilities, i.e. between 0.1% and 1.2%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is still not, by any means, &lt;em&gt;good&lt;/em&gt;. If the US ended all quarantines today, without a vaccine or effective treatment, and allowed the virus to spread until herd immunity was achieved, or about 60% of the US population, this would mean about 200,000-2,000,000 deaths this year.  On the high end, that’s as deadly per capita as the US Civil War,[30] and deadlier than the Spanish Flu.[31]  “Less deadly than previously estimated” does not mean “no big deal.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Do Viral Antibodies Generally Correspond to Past Viral Infection?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Outside of COVID-19, what’s the track record of accuracy of viral antibody tests?  Are there a sizable population who have positive antibodies to viruses they were never infected with?  Do many people get infected with viruses that they never develop antibodies to?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This can put the credibility of antibody tests for COVID-19 in a broader context. If antibody false positives are really common overall, then the apparently good specificity of the COVID-19 tests (derived from small studies, often by the manufacturers) may be too optimistic, and the actual prevalence of COVID-19 may be quite a bit lower than it appears in the antibody screening studies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Test Type&lt;/strong&gt;
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Virus&lt;/strong&gt;
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sensitivity&lt;/strong&gt;
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Specificity&lt;/strong&gt;
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;# Of Individuals&lt;/strong&gt;
   &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Rapid
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;HIV
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;&amp;gt;95%
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;&amp;gt;99%
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;6282
   &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;NS1 ELISA, IgM/IgG
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Zika
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;100%
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;100%
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;1379
   &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Rapid
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;HCV
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;97.8% \
88.3% \
99.3%
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;99.5%
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;1083
   &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Rapid test and ELISA
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;H5N1
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;18.2% \
38.7%
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;100% \
100%
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;
   &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;IgM ELISA
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Dengue
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;96%
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;84%
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;225
   &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;rapid
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Chikungunya
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;20.5% \
50.8%
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;100% \
89.2%
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;206
   &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;NS1 ELISA
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Dengue
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;83.2%
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;100%
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;138
   &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;NS1 Rapid
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Dengue
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;73.8%
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;100%
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;138
   &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;
   &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;
   &lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;
   &lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An ELISA test and rapid antibody test for dengue virus, tested in 138 Vietnamese patients admitted to the ICU with clinical suspicion of dengue, had sensitivities of 83.2% and 73.8% respectively, and specificities of 100%.[32]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a study of antibody tests for dengue virus on 225 patients from around the world, some with dengue, some with other viruses, and some healthy controls, the ELISA tests for NS1 antigen had sensitivities of 60-75% in acute cases and 19-31% in convalescent cases, and the rapid tests had sensitivities of 40-60% in acute cases and 12-59% in convalescent cases.  The anti-dengue IgM ELISA test had a sensitivity of 98% in both acute and convalescent cases, while the anti-dengue IgM rapid tests had a sensitivity of 45-95 in both acute and convalescent cases.  The specificity of NS1 tests was 71-80%, and the IgM ELISA test had a specificity of 84%.[33]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3 rapid tests for HCV (hepatitis C) on 1083 samples: all specificities over 99.5%, sensitivities were 97.8%, 88.3%, 99.3%[34]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;6 rapid tests for HIV on 6282 study participants, compared to a gold standard of Western blot, ELISA, &amp;amp; treatment status.  All sensitivities were &amp;gt;95% and specificities were &amp;gt;99%.[35]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a study of an IgG/IgM ELISA test for Zika virus, on 112 patients with RT-PCR confirmed or suspected Zika, 1015 healthy patients, and 252 patients with other viruses, the sensitivity of combined IgG and IgM tests was 100% and specificity was 100%.[36]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two rapid tests for chikungunya virus, tested on 132 patients with confirmed chikungunya and 74 patients with a different febrile illness; one had a 20.5% sensitivity and 100% specificity, while the other had a 50.8% sensitivity and 89.2% specificity.[37]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a study of 524 patients tested for H5N1 (avian flu) a rapid test had a sensitivity of 18.2% and an ELISA test had a sensitivity of 38.7%.  Both had specificities of 100%.[38]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Conclusions&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the performance of antibody tests for different viruses depends on the test itself, most have high specificities.  There is no reason to suppose that the measured specificity levels for SARS-CoV-2 tests are unrealistically low.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Do Viral Antibodies Generally Predict Immunity to Future Infection?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The WHO has been saying there’s “no evidence” that antibodies in recovered patients indicate immunity to COVID-19.[39] It’s too soon to tell whether this is true for COVID-19, but do antibody levels predict viral immunity in other viruses?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a longitudinal cohort of 7547 Nicaraguan children monitored for dengue virus, preinfection antibody titer correlated with lower risk of having a symptomatic second infection (p &amp;lt; 0.005).  Children with serologically confirmed but asymptomatic second infections had preinfection antibody titers 2.3-fold higher than children with symptomatic second infections.  Also, children with symptomatic first infections were less likely to have symptomatic second infections independent of antibody titer – apparently infection grants immunity through mechanisms other than antibody quantity.[40]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 17 infants born to mothers with HSV1 or HSV2 infections during pregnancy, the babies with milder (or asymptomatic) infections had higher neutralizing antibody titers at birth than the babies with severe cases.  Average titer was 1:13 for severe cases, 1:65 for mild cases, and 1:69 for asymptomatic cases.[41]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nine studies of human volunteers previously infected with influenza in the 60’s and 70’s and challenged with exposure to an influenza virus found that _no _volunteers developed symptomatic illness after challenge, out of a total of 86 patients.  “The titer of serum anti-HA antibodies remains the most consistent correlate of immunity to influenza virus infection.”[42]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a cohort of 200 Mexican infants monitored for rotavirus, children with higher (&amp;gt; 1:800) rotavirus IgA titers were less likely to have rotavirus infection (RR = 0.21, p &amp;lt; 0.001) and rotavirus diarrhea (RR = 0.16, p &amp;lt; 0.01) and never got severe diarrhea.[43]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1164 healthy children immunized with varicella vaccine, children with lower antibody titers after the vaccine (&amp;lt;5 gpELISA units) were 3.5x as likely to develop a varicella infection in the next 7 years as children with higher antibody titers (&amp;gt;5 gpELISA units.)[44]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a study of 38 adults challenged with rotavirus, patients who got ill from the exposure had higher preinoculation rotavirus IgG antibody (7.3 vs 6.1, p = 0.041).  There was no significant difference in infection rate between those exposed to a larger vs. smaller quantity.[45]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a study of 696 adults and children in rural Bangladesh, serum IgG rotavirus antibodies were on average 4x higher in cases of symptomatic rotavirus than healthy controls.[46]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 33 volunteers experimentally infected with human coronavirus 223E, those who had higher antibody titers prior to exposure were much less likely to get symptomatic disease (average ELISA ratio for neutralizing antibodies was 6.5x higher in the affected group vs the unaffected group, p &amp;lt;0.001)  Those who had had a cold in the last six months had significantly (p&amp;lt;0.05) lower clinical scores than those who had not.[47]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have very consistent results across all viruses studied indicating that yes, higher pre-challenge virus-specific antibody titers are predictive of lower rates of symptomatic disease.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We don’t know yet whether reinfection of people previously infected with COVID-19 is _ever _possible, but we _do _have evidence from other viruses suggesting that if you’ve recovered successfully from a COVID-19 illness you are _less _susceptible to getting a symptomatic disease if you’re exposed again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[1]&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.centerforhealthsecurity.org/resources/COVID-19/serology/Serology-based-tests-for-COVID-19.html&quot;&gt;https://www.centerforhealthsecurity.org/resources/COVID-19/serology/Serology-based-tests-for-COVID-19.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[2]Li, Zhengtu, et al. “Development and clinical application of a rapid IgM‐IgG combined antibody test for SARS‐CoV‐2 infection diagnosis.” &lt;em&gt;Journal of medical virology&lt;/em&gt; (2020).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[3]Okba, Nisreen MA, et al. “SARS-CoV-2 specific antibody responses in COVID-19 patients.” &lt;em&gt;medRxiv&lt;/em&gt; (2020).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[4]Ma, Huan, et al. “COVID-19 diagnosis and study of serum SARS-CoV-2 specific IgA, IgM and IgG by a quantitative and sensitive immunoassay.” &lt;em&gt;medRxiv&lt;/em&gt; (2020).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[5]Zhang, Pingping, et al. “Evaluation of recombinant nucleocapsid and spike proteins for serological diagnosis of novel coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19).” &lt;em&gt;MedRxiv&lt;/em&gt; (2020).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[6]Amanat, Fatima, et al. “A serological assay to detect SARS-CoV-2 seroconversion in humans.” &lt;em&gt;MedRxiv&lt;/em&gt; (2020).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[7]Lassaunière, Ria, et al. “Evaluation of nine commercial SARS-CoV-2 immunoassays.” &lt;em&gt;medRxiv&lt;/em&gt; (2020).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[8]Döhla, M., et al. “Rapid point-of-care testing for SARS-CoV-2 in a community screening setting shows low sensitivity.” &lt;em&gt;Public Health&lt;/em&gt; (2020).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[9]Spicuzza, Lucia, et al. “Reliability and usefulness of a rapid IgM‐IgG antibody test for the diagnosis of SARS-CoV-2 infection: a preliminary report.” &lt;em&gt;Journal of Infection&lt;/em&gt; (2020).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[10]Burbelo, Peter D., et al. “Detection of Nucleocapsid Antibody to SARS-CoV-2 is More Sensitive than Antibody to Spike Protein in COVID-19 Patients.” &lt;em&gt;medRxiv&lt;/em&gt; (2020).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[11]&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fda.gov/media/136625/download&quot;&gt;https://www.fda.gov/media/136625/download&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[12] &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fda.gov/media/136967/download&quot;&gt;https://www.fda.gov/media/136967/download&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[13]Spellberg, Brad, et al. “Community prevalence of SARS-CoV-2 among patients with influenzalike illnesses presenting to a Los Angeles medical center in March 2020.” &lt;em&gt;JAMA&lt;/em&gt; (2020).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[14]Sutton, Desmond, et al. “Universal screening for SARS-CoV-2 in women admitted for delivery.” &lt;em&gt;New England Journal of Medicine&lt;/em&gt; (2020).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[15]Bendavid, Eran, et al. “COVID-19 Antibody Seroprevalence in Santa Clara County, California.” &lt;em&gt;medRxiv&lt;/em&gt; (2020).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[16]Gudbjartsson, Daniel F., et al. “Spread of SARS-CoV-2 in the Icelandic population.” &lt;em&gt;New England Journal of Medicine&lt;/em&gt; (2020).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[17]Reusken, Chantal B., et al. “Rapid assessment of regional SARS-CoV-2 community transmission through a convenience sample of healthcare workers, the Netherlands, March 2020.” &lt;em&gt;Eurosurveillance&lt;/em&gt; 25.12 (2020): 2000334.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[18]Wu, Fuqing, et al. “SARS-CoV-2 titers in wastewater are higher than expected from clinically confirmed cases.” &lt;em&gt;medRxiv&lt;/em&gt; (2020).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[19]Thompson, Craig, et al. “Neutralising antibodies to SARS coronavirus 2 in Scottish blood donors-a pilot study of the value of serology to determine population exposure.” &lt;em&gt;medRxiv&lt;/em&gt; (2020).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[20]Mosites, Emily. “Assessment of SARS-CoV-2 Infection Prevalence in Homeless Shelters—Four US Cities, March 27–April 15, 2020.” &lt;em&gt;MMWR. Morbidity and Mortality Weekly Report&lt;/em&gt; 69 (2020).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[21]&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2020/04/21/world/coronavirus-missing-deaths.html&quot;&gt;https://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2020/04/21/world/coronavirus-missing-deaths.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[22]Hunter, Ewan, et al. “First experience of COVID-19 screening of health-care workers in England.” &lt;em&gt;The Lancet&lt;/em&gt; (2020).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[23]&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.statista.com/statistics/1095848/south-korea-confirmed-and-suspected-coronavirus-cases/&quot;&gt;https://www.statista.com/statistics/1095848/south-korea-confirmed-and-suspected-coronavirus-cases/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[24]&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.miamidade.gov/releases/2020-04-24-sample-testing-results.asp&quot;&gt;https://www.miamidade.gov/releases/2020-04-24-sample-testing-results.asp&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[25]&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.miamiherald.com/news/coronavirus/article242260406.html&quot;&gt;https://www.miamiherald.com/news/coronavirus/article242260406.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[26]&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2020/04/23/nyregion/coronavirus-antibodies-test-ny.html&quot;&gt;https://www.nytimes.com/2020/04/23/nyregion/coronavirus-antibodies-test-ny.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[27]&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cdc.gov/nchs/nvss/vsrr/covid19/index.htm&quot;&gt;https://www.cdc.gov/nchs/nvss/vsrr/covid19/index.htm&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[28]&lt;a href=&quot;https://coronavirus.jhu.edu/map.html&quot;&gt;https://coronavirus.jhu.edu/map.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[29]&lt;a href=&quot;http://publichealth.lacounty.gov/phcommon/public/media/mediapubhpdetail.cfm?prid=2328&quot;&gt;http://publichealth.lacounty.gov/phcommon/public/media/mediapubhpdetail.cfm?prid=2328&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[30]&lt;a href=&quot;https://prospect.org/power/american-war-dead-numbers/&quot;&gt;https://prospect.org/power/american-war-dead-numbers/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[31]&lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/20160923152823/http://www.flu.gov/pandemic/history/1918/&quot;&gt;https://web.archive.org/web/20160923152823/http://www.flu.gov/pandemic/history/1918/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[32]Hang, Vu Ty, et al. “Diagnostic accuracy of NS1 ELISA and lateral flow rapid tests for dengue sensitivity, specificity and relationship to viraemia and antibody responses.” &lt;em&gt;PLoS neglected tropical diseases&lt;/em&gt; 3.1 (2009).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[33]Hunsperger, Elizabeth A., et al. “Evaluation of commercially available diagnostic tests for the detection of dengue virus NS1 antigen and anti-dengue virus IgM antibody.” &lt;em&gt;PLoS neglected tropical diseases&lt;/em&gt; 8.10 (2014).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[34]Smith, Bryce D., et al. “Evaluation of three rapid screening assays for detection of antibodies to hepatitis C virus.” &lt;em&gt;Journal of Infectious Diseases&lt;/em&gt; 204.6 (2011): 825-831.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[35]Delaney, Kevin P., et al. “Evaluation of the performance characteristics of 6 rapid HIV antibody tests.” &lt;em&gt;Clinical Infectious Diseases&lt;/em&gt; 52.2 (2011): 257-263.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[36]Steinhagen, Katja, et al. “Serodiagnosis of Zika virus (ZIKV) infections by a novel NS1-based ELISA devoid of cross-reactivity with dengue virus antibodies: a multicohort study of assay performance, 2015 to 2016.” &lt;em&gt;Eurosurveillance&lt;/em&gt; 21.50 (2016).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[37]Kosasih, Herman, et al. “Evaluation of two IgM rapid immunochromatographic tests during circulation of Asian lineage Chikungunya virus.” &lt;em&gt;Southeast Asian Journal of Tropical Medicineand Public Health&lt;/em&gt; 43.1 (2012): 55.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[38]Ganzenmueller, Tina, et al. “Comparison of the performance of direct fluorescent antibody staining, a point-of-care rapid antigen test and virus isolation with that of RT-PCR for the detection of novel 2009 influenza A (H1N1) virus in respiratory specimens.” &lt;em&gt;Journal of medical microbiology&lt;/em&gt; 59.6 (2010): 713-717.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[39]&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cnbc.com/2020/04/17/who-issues-warning-on-coronavirus-testing-theres-no-evidence-antibody-tests-show-immunity.html&quot;&gt;https://www.cnbc.com/2020/04/17/who-issues-warning-on-coronavirus-testing-theres-no-evidence-antibody-tests-show-immunity.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[40]Katzelnick, Leah C., et al. “Neutralizing antibody titers against dengue virus correlate with protection from symptomatic infection in a longitudinal cohort.” &lt;em&gt;Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences&lt;/em&gt; 113.3 (2016): 728-733.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[41]Yeager, Anne S., et al. “Relationship of antibody to outcome in neonatal herpes simplex virus infections.” &lt;em&gt;Infection and immunity&lt;/em&gt; 29.2 (1980): 532-538.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[42]Couch, Robert B., and Julius A. Kasel. “Immunity to influenza in man.” &lt;em&gt;Annual review of microbiology&lt;/em&gt; 37.1 (1983): 529-549.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[43]Velázquez, F. Raúl, et al. “Serum antibody as a marker of protection against natural rotavirus infection and disease.” &lt;em&gt;The Journal of infectious diseases&lt;/em&gt; 182.6 (2000): 1602-1609.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[44]Li, Shu, et al. “Inverse relationship between six week postvaccination varicella antibody response to vaccine and likelihood of long term breakthrough infection.” &lt;em&gt;The Pediatric infectious disease journal&lt;/em&gt; 21.4 (2002): 337-342.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[45]Ward, Richard L., et al. “Effects of antibody to rotavirus on protection of adults challenged with a human rotavirus.” &lt;em&gt;Journal of Infectious Diseases&lt;/em&gt; 159.1 (1989): 79-88.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[46]Ward, Richard L., et al. “Effects of antibody to rotavirus on protection of adults challenged with a human rotavirus.” &lt;em&gt;Journal of Infectious Diseases&lt;/em&gt; 159.1 (1989): 79-88.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[47]Callow, Kathleen A. “Effect of specific humoral immunity and some non-specific factors on resistance of volunteers to respiratory coronavirus infection.” Epidemiology &amp;amp; Infection 95.1 (1985): 173-189.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="covid-19" /><category term="lit-review" /><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Variolation for COVID-19</title><link href="https://srconstantin.github.io/2020/04/13/variolation.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Variolation for COVID-19" /><published>2020-04-13T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-04-13T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://srconstantin.github.io/2020/04/13/variolation</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://srconstantin.github.io/2020/04/13/variolation.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/anti-vaccination-cartoon.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;variolation&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Variolation refers to a historical precursor of vaccination used for smallpox. Healthy subjects were inoculated with material from the scabs of smallpox patients, which usually gave them a mild version of the disease and protected them from contracting the full disease.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By analogy, is it possible that a low-dose exposure to the SARS-CoV-2 virus could result in a mild illness and immunity to subsequently contracting the disease?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Are Low Doses of COVID-19 Virus Safer?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One (imperfect) proxy for this question is whether lower viral titers of SARS-CoV-2 correspond to less severe disease.  It seems intuitively plausible – smaller quantities of the virus in the body might be easier for the immune system to fight off and/or cause less extensive tissue damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking at viral RNA titers in COVID-19 patients doesn’t tell us whether they were initially exposed to large or small amounts of virus, though. If there’s a correlation between viral titer and disease severity, it could either be because the sicker patients got a higher initial “dose” of virus, or because the virus was more successful at multiplying in them.  However, we can somewhat alleviate this ambiguity by looking at the trajectories of virus titer over time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A retrospective study of 76 Chinese patients found that viral loads (as measured by nasal swab) were significantly higher in severe than mild cases of COVID-19, p &amp;lt; 0.005. All patients’ viral loads followed a similar trajectory over time – they started high and steadily declined.  However, severe cases had detectable levels of virus for much longer – all severe cases still had viral RNA after 10 days from disease onset, while most mild cases were virus-free by 10 days.[1]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Viral load does not correlate perfectly with disease.  Asymptomatic patients [2][3] can have similar viral loads to sick ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another, smaller study with 23 COVID-19 patients found a significant association of peak viral load with age but no significant association of either initial or peak viral load with disease severity.[4]  The correlation of viral load with age is explainable by immunosenescence (aging weakens the immune system) and tells us that higher viral load can be caused by a weaker immune system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the SARS epidemic, healthcare workers who were exposed to one of three index patients and tested positive for SARS were significantly more likely to be asymptomatic if they wore masks, which suggests that masks lower the amount of virus exposure and that lower virus exposure results in less severe disease.[5]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another study of 16 individuals exposed to a single SARS index patient showed that the healthcare workers, who were wearing PPE, had significantly lower viral load than the non-healthcare workers, who had no masks. The non-healthcare workers were also more likely to have severe disease, but they were also older on average.[7]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Among people with exposure to a SARS index patient, they were significantly (p &amp;lt; 0.001) more likely to get SARS the longer the index patient stayed home after the onset of fever; when the patient stayed home for &amp;gt;6 days, as opposed to &amp;lt;=2 days, the risk of getting the disease jumps from 38% to 66%.  You were more likely to get the disease if you shared a room and bed with the index patient, if you dined more frequently with the index patient, and if you had more frequent close contact with the index patient.  This indicates that the volume of contact with the SARS virus influences the risk of contracting disease.[8]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Higher initial viral load is also associated with worse prognosis and shorter survival times in SARS.[6]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The evidence is relatively sparse but consistent with the hypothesis that lower volumes of exposure to SARS-CoV-2 and SARS-CoV result in lower viral titers and less severe disease.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Is COVID-19 Reinfection Possible?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Deliberately infecting a human with a low dose of virus, of course, has not been done enough for there to be a research literature about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what happens when we do it with animals?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have mixed results on reinfection in animals, some studies showing that prior exposure to a coronavirus protects against subsequent infection, while others showed that reinfection can indeed occur.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rhesus monkeys that have been infected with SARS-CoV-2 do not get reinfected after a second challenge; they do not show viral replication or clinical symptoms.[15]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mice who have previously been exposed to SARS-CoV are protected from disease for at least 28 days. Serum from mice that had previously been exposed to the virus, injected into SARS-naive mice, also had a protective effect, while serum from non-exposed mice did not.[12]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ferrets infected with SARS-CoV who were reinfected 4 weeks later did not have as high viral titers upon reinfection and did not show lung histopathology.[14]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alpacas and camels experimentally infected with MERS-CoV are protected against reinfection.[17]  On the other hand, a longitudinal study of a camel herd showed that reinfection can occur in camels who have previously acquired antibodies to MERS-CoV.[18]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reinfection is possible in cats previously exposed to feline coronavirus [19], and in cows with bovine coronavirus [20].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Exposure to an inactivated form of a virus is a standard type of vaccine, and it has been found effective in rodents for SARS-CoV.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Partially inactivated SARS-CoV virus samples (treated with formaldehyde) were no longer able to replicate in vitro. When mice were treated with this inactivated virus (by injection or intranasal administration) they produced detectable antibody responses.[9][10]  SARS-CoV virus inactivated with UV radiation also produced an antibody response in mice.[11]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whole killed SARS-CoV vaccine (inactivated with beta-propiolactone)  protected mice against a challenge infection.[13]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hamsters immunized with beta-propiolactone inactivated SARS-CoV virus had lower virus titers than non-immunized hamsters upon challenge with active SARS-CoV and had less severe lung lesions than non-immunized hamsters.[16]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There have been reports of reinfected COVID-19 patients in China and Japan[21] but some think that these are due to testing errors where the patients erroneously tested as having recovered when they were still infected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The current state of evidence hasn’t ruled out that reinfection could occur for SARS-CoV-2, but tentatively it seems more likely that people who have been infected once are protected against further infections for some period of time. The duration of protection, and whether there are any individuals who don’t get immunological protection, is still unknown.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusion&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s reason to believe that exposure to a lower dose of the SARS-CoV-2 virus produces a milder disease than exposure to larger quantities of SARS-CoV-2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And there’s reason to believe that people who have recovered from COVID-19 have some protection against the disease.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What we _don’t _know is whether a dose low enough not to cause severe symptoms is also high enough to cause immune protection against subsequent infections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Deliberate Exposure as a Policy&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A trial of deliberate exposure of young, healthy volunteers to COVID-19 has been &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.overcomingbias.com/2020/04/variolation-test-design.html&quot;&gt;proposed&lt;/a&gt; by Robin Hanson.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The case for deliberate exposure is to produce a population of immune people who don’t have to be quarantined – for instance, so that they can continue to work as healthcare workers, janitors, and other essential employees in a mostly housebound economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The downside, of course, is that deliberately infecting people with a disease harms them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Deliberate exposure looks better relative to other options under certain conditions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;if deliberate exposure causes little harm to the exposed (either because the dose is low or because young people rarely get severe disease)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;if reinfection after safe doses of virus is rare or impossible&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;if exposure to the active virus is much easier and/or more effective than alternative, safer types of immune protection (like convalescent serum or inactivated virus)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;if containing the virus is expected to be impossible (i.e. most people will get the disease, the question is when) or so costly that countries decide it’s not worth continuing the lockdowns.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;if developing an effective vaccine or treatment is expected to be slow&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am doubtful about the first three conditions.  We don’t know much about what a “safe” dose of SARS-CoV-2 is, and we haven’t fully ruled out reinfection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And young people, while less vulnerable than older people, are not immune from severe COVID-19 – in New York, 9% of patients age 18-44 had to be &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cbsnews.com/news/young-people-coronavirus-new-york-city-percentage-patients-covid-19-symptoms-dying-hospitalizations/&quot;&gt;hospitalized.&lt;/a&gt;  For any given young person, it might be safer to try to stay home and avoid getting the disease until a vaccine or treatment can be developed than to risk deliberate exposure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An animal study prior to a human one can identify what the infectious dose of the virus is, as well as what the minimum active dose to produce an immune response and protection against reinfection is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover, it seems that it would be safer, and not obviously less effective, to treat healthy subjects with convalescent serum or inactivated virus rather than live virus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[1]Liu, Yang, et al. “Viral dynamics in mild and severe cases of COVID-19.” &lt;em&gt;The Lancet Infectious Diseases&lt;/em&gt; (2020).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[2]Zou, Lirong, et al. “SARS-CoV-2 viral load in upper respiratory specimens of infected patients.” &lt;em&gt;New England Journal of Medicine&lt;/em&gt; 382.12 (2020): 1177-1179.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[3]Kam, Kai-qian, et al. “A Well Infant with Coronavirus Disease 2019 with High Viral Load.” &lt;em&gt;Clinical Infectious Diseases&lt;/em&gt; (2020).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[4]To, Kelvin Kai-Wang, et al. “Temporal profiles of viral load in posterior oropharyngeal saliva samples and serum antibody responses during infection by SARS-CoV-2: an observational cohort study.” &lt;em&gt;The Lancet Infectious Diseases&lt;/em&gt; (2020).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[5]Wilder-Smith, Annelies, et al. “Asymptomatic SARS coronavirus infection among healthcare workers, Singapore.” &lt;em&gt;Emerging infectious diseases&lt;/em&gt; 11.7 (2005): 1142.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[6]Chu, Chung-Ming, et al. “Initial viral load and the outcomes of SARS.” &lt;em&gt;Cmaj&lt;/em&gt; 171.11 (2004): 1349-1352.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[7]Lu, Yen-Ta, et al. “Viral load and outcome in SARS infection: the role of personal protective equipment in the emergency department.” &lt;em&gt;The Journal of emergency medicine&lt;/em&gt; 30.1 (2006): 7-15.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[8]Lau, Joseph TF, et al. “Probable secondary infections in households of SARS patients in Hong Kong.” &lt;em&gt;Emerging infectious diseases&lt;/em&gt; 10.2 (2004): 236.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[9]Yang, Zhi-yong, et al. “A DNA vaccine induces SARS coronavirus neutralization and protective immunity in mice.” &lt;em&gt;Nature&lt;/em&gt; 428.6982 (2004): 561-564.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[10]Xiong, Sheng, et al. “Immunogenicity of SARS inactivated vaccine in BALB/c mice.” &lt;em&gt;Immunology letters&lt;/em&gt; 95.2 (2004): 139-143.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[11]Takasuka, Naomi, et al. “A subcutaneously injected UV-inactivated SARS coronavirus vaccine elicits systemic humoral immunity in mice.” &lt;em&gt;International immunology&lt;/em&gt; 16.10 (2004): 1423-1430.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[12]Subbarao, Kanta, et al. “Prior infection and passive transfer of neutralizing antibody prevent replication of severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus in the respiratory tract of mice.” &lt;em&gt;Journal of virology&lt;/em&gt; 78.7 (2004): 3572-3577.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[13]See, Raymond H., et al. “Comparative evaluation of two severe acute respiratory syndrome (SARS) vaccine candidates in mice challenged with SARS coronavirus.” &lt;em&gt;Journal of general virology&lt;/em&gt; 87.3 (2006): 641-650.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[14]Cameron, Mark J., et al. “Lack of innate interferon responses during SARS coronavirus infection in a vaccination and reinfection ferret model.” &lt;em&gt;PLoS one&lt;/em&gt; 7.9 (2012).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[15]Bao, Linlin, et al. “Reinfection could not occur in SARS-CoV-2 infected rhesus macaques.” &lt;em&gt;bioRxiv&lt;/em&gt; (2020).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[16]Roberts, Anjeanette, et al. “Immunogenicity and protective efficacy in mice and hamsters of a β-propiolactone inactivated whole virus SARS-CoV vaccine.” &lt;em&gt;Viral immunology&lt;/em&gt; 23.5 (2010): 509-519.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[17]Wernery, Ulrich, Susanna KP Lau, and Patrick CY Woo. “Middle East respiratory syndrome (MERS) coronavirus and dromedaries.” &lt;em&gt;The Veterinary Journal&lt;/em&gt; 220 (2017): 75-79.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[18]Hemida, Maged Gomaa, et al. “Longitudinal study of Middle East respiratory syndrome coronavirus infection in dromedary camel herds in Saudi Arabia, 2014–2015.” &lt;em&gt;Emerging microbes &amp;amp; infections&lt;/em&gt; 6.1 (2017): 1-7.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[19]Addie, D. D., and O. Jarrett. “Use of a reverse-transcriptase polymerase chain reaction for monitoring the shedding of feline coronavirus by healthy cats.” &lt;em&gt;Veterinary Record&lt;/em&gt; 148.21 (2001): 649-653.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[20]Heckert, R. A., et al. “Epidemiologic factors and isotype-specific antibody responses in serum and mucosal secretions of dairy calves with bovine coronavirus respiratory tract and enteric tract infections.” &lt;em&gt;American journal of veterinary research&lt;/em&gt; 52.6 (1991): 845-851.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[21]Omer, Saad B., Preeti Malani, and Carlos del Rio. “The COVID-19 Pandemic in the US: A Clinical Update.” &lt;em&gt;JAMA&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="covid-19" /><category term="lit-review" /><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">CPAP for COVID-19</title><link href="https://srconstantin.github.io/2020/04/05/CPAP-for-COVID19.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="CPAP for COVID-19" /><published>2020-04-05T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-04-05T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://srconstantin.github.io/2020/04/05/CPAP-for-COVID19</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://srconstantin.github.io/2020/04/05/CPAP-for-COVID19.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/mercedes-CPAP.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;shield&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As COVID-19 sweeps the world, there are more patients who have severe cases of respiratory failure than there are ICU beds and ventilator machines to help them breathe.  Doctors have been forced to find creative solutions to the crisis – and they’re turning to a technique called CPAP, which is gaining credence as a treatment for severe COVID-19.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CPAP stands for continuous positive airway pressure, and refers to a device that blows a steady stream of air into the lungs (which may be supplemented with extra oxygen) to help patients who have moderate difficulty breathing independently.  It may reduce the need for ventilation, which is crucial when ventilators are scarce.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-020-00926-4&quot;&gt;Nature&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; reports on a team of clinicians from the UK, China, and Italy using a CPAP device, now being used in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bmj.com/content/368/bmj.m1294.full&quot;&gt;clinical trials&lt;/a&gt; at University College London Hospital.  These machines have been widely used in Italy, where they prevented the need for ventilation in 50% of patients. (A prospective study on the effectiveness of CPAP on COVID-19 in Italy is &lt;a href=&quot;https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/show/NCT04307459?term=covid-19+cpap&amp;amp;draw=2&quot;&gt;ongoing&lt;/a&gt;; in &lt;a href=&quot;https://srconstantin.github.io/2020/03/22/non-invasive-ventilation.html&quot;&gt;China&lt;/a&gt;, non-invasive ventilation such as CPAP successfully avoided the need for invasive ventilation in 77% of treated patients.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cnn.com/2020/03/30/tech/mercedes-f1-breathing-aid-coronavirus/index.html&quot;&gt;Mercedes F1&lt;/a&gt; engineers designed the device, which can be quickly mass produced and has been recommended for use by the UK Medicines and Healthcare Products Regulatory Agency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the US, Elon Musk has been &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.teslarati.com/tesla-elon-musk-cpap-ventilator-coronavirus/&quot;&gt;donating CPAP/BiPAP machines&lt;/a&gt; to hospitals; these machines can be converted into ventilators if necessary, or used as-is on patients with milder respiratory distress to prevent them needing invasive (and scarce) mechanical ventilation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CPAP and BiPAP for respiratory disorders are &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npr.org/sections/health-shots/2020/03/27/822211604/cpap-machines-were-seen-as-ventilator-alternatives-but-could-spread-covid-19&quot;&gt;controversial&lt;/a&gt;, as they are considered “aerosol generating procedures” that could spread particles of the virus around. However, evidence suggests that these non-invasive ventilation procedures actually produce &lt;a href=&quot;https://srconstantin.github.io/2020/03/22/contagion-risk-from-NIV.html&quot;&gt;droplets rather than aerosols&lt;/a&gt;, larger particles which usually land less than one meter from the patient, and CPAP masks don’t leak much exhaled air (less than a meter away from the patient) when the mask is a good fit, as a 2019 Hong Kong study &lt;a href=&quot;https://sci-hub.tw/10.1183/13993003.02339-2018&quot;&gt;showed.&lt;/a&gt;  ResMed, the leading manufacturer of CPAP machines, recommends that they be used in COVID-19 patients only when caregivers have protective equipment such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.resmed.com/en-us/covid-19/?utm_source=vanity&amp;amp;utm_medium=print&amp;amp;utm_content=covid19&amp;amp;utm_campaign=covid19-update&quot;&gt;N95 masks and eye protection.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even the WHO’s guidance on treatment of &lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.who.int/iris/bitstream/handle/10665/331446/WHO-2019-nCoV-clinical-2020.4-eng.pdf&quot;&gt;COVID-19 &lt;/a&gt;acknowledges a place for CPAP and BiPAP machines.  The document recommends patients be given non-invasive ventilation only in monitored circumstances where they can be intubated and placed on mechanical ventilation if their condition worsens, but it still offers CPAP as an option, particularly in the case of children in low-resource settings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The FDA’s new guidance on COVID-19 clears the way for modifying respiratory support devices without needing to get the modifications separately approved, including the use of CPAP machines in COVID-19: __&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;_Wherever possible, health care facilities should use FDA-cleared conventional/standard full- featured ventilators when necessary to support patients with respiratory failure, or a device subject to an Emergency Use Authorization (EUA), if any. However, to help ensure the availability of the greatest possible number of devices for this purpose, and as described in more detail below, FDA does not intend to object to limited modifications to the indications, claims, functionality, or to the hardware, software, or materials of FDA-cleared devices used to support patients with respiratory failure or respiratory insufficiency, without prior submission of a premarket notification under section 510(k) of the FD&amp;amp;C Act and 21 CFR 807.81 , for the duration of the declared public health emergency…_


_Examples of circumstances where FDA currently believes a modification would not create such undue risk include:_


_1) The use of powered emergency ventilators and anesthesia gas machines for patients needing mechanical ventilation; _


_2) The use of ventilators outside their cleared environment of use (for example, use of a ventilator in a health care facility when it is only cleared for use at home or during transport);_


_3) **The use of devices indicated for sleep apnea (including noncontinuous ventilators delivering continuous positive airway pressure (CPAP) or bilevel positive airway pressure (BiPAP)) to treat patients with respiratory insufficiency, provided that appropriate design mitigations are in place to minimize aerosolization**;_


_4) The use of oxygen concentrators for primary supply when medically necessary and clinically appropriate._
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s time to give CPAP for COVID-19 a second look. Yes, it can disperse air, but the evidence that it spreads disease particles is ambiguous at best; and the risks can be mitigated by using full-face masks with good seals, using filters on the exhaust vents, and making sure medical staff have adequate protective equipment. We know from past pandemics and some early retrospective data in COVID-19 that a sizable fraction of patients improve on CPAP alone without intubation; in a world where invasive ventilation may not be an option for an overwhelmed healthcare system, that means saving lives.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="covid-19" /><category term="lit-review" /><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Comprehensive PPE Project List</title><link href="https://srconstantin.github.io/2020/04/03/Comprehensive-PPE-Project-List.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Comprehensive PPE Project List" /><published>2020-04-03T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-04-03T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://srconstantin.github.io/2020/04/03/Comprehensive-PPE-Project-List</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://srconstantin.github.io/2020/04/03/Comprehensive-PPE-Project-List.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/face_shield.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;shield&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The COVID19 crisis has caused a severe shortage of personal protective equipment (PPE) for healthcare workers. Masks, face shields, respirators, and other supplies help keep the people who care for COVID19 patients from getting sick themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s been a huge outpouring of effort to fix this shortage, by manufacturers, makers, donors, and volunteers. But as of yet, I haven’t seen anything approaching a comprehensive list of who is active in this space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is my best attempt at aggregating all the open-source designs for personal protective equipment (PPE), manufacturers and DIY maker groups currently scaling up their production of PPE, and coordination/distribution efforts to get PPE to the health care workers who need it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am not a hardware engineer or experienced maker, so I have made no attempt to evaluate these designs myself. I do NOT vouch for the quality of any of these designs. I do mention when a design has already been in use in hospitals, been tested by medical professionals, been certified by a governing body, etc. The only designs I’m putting in the “Bad Ideas” section are those that I’ve seen specific criticism of (e.g. from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.helpfulengineering.org/&quot;&gt;Helpful Engineering &lt;/a&gt;team.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just because I have not listed a design under “Bad Ideas” does not mean it is a good idea!  If you are considering manufacturing PPE, use your own critical judgment to choose a design!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Likewise, I have not vetted the charities on this list. I make no claims about their competence or integrity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Open Source Designs&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Surgical/Cloth Face Masks&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://antisocialartshow.org/masks/&quot;&gt;AntiSocialArtShow pattern&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://imgur.com/gallery/p517T4h&quot;&gt;AthenaCosplay pattern&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://aussiefacemaskproject.com.au/pattern/&quot;&gt;Aussie Facemask Project&lt;/a&gt; (pattern + distribution)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.craftpassion.com/wp-json/mv-create/v1/creations/19/print&quot;&gt;CraftPassion &lt;/a&gt;pattern&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.deaconess.com/How-to-make-a-Face-Mask&quot;&gt;Deaconess Hospital, IN instructions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://diymask.site/&quot;&gt;HKMask pattern&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instructables.com/id/DIY-Cloth-Face-Mask/&quot;&gt;Instructables Instructions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://freesewing.org/blog/facemask-frenzy/&quot;&gt;FreeSewing.org pattern&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instructables.com/id/AB-Mask-for-a-Nurse-by-a-Nurse/&quot;&gt;Jessica Nandino pattern&lt;/a&gt; (designed by an RN)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.joann.com/how-to-make-a-face-mask/042188731P321.html&quot;&gt;JoAnn pattern&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://laprotects.org/&quot;&gt;L.A. Protects mask&lt;/a&gt; – developed by Kaiser Permanente, partnering with local garment manufacturers to produce 5M masks&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://makefacemasks.com/&quot;&gt;MakeFaceMasks.com&lt;/a&gt; design (approved by the Belgian Federal Service for Public Health)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.maspire.org/?page_id=115&amp;amp;lang=en&quot;&gt;Maspire&lt;/a&gt; – currently used by HCC Colmar patients in France&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=oLEE8RcyYo8&quot;&gt;NoSew Fabric Mask&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1iUzvKguzBA1zKT60UXgwQcmB_ypfNjKFaw3J6dTDmOU/edit#slide=id.p&quot;&gt;Origami Mask&lt;/a&gt; – made of 3M Filtrete paper&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://sweetredpoppy.com/how-to-sew-a-bias-tape-surgical-face-mask-with-flexible-nose/&quot;&gt;SweetRedPoppy pattern&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.unitypoint.org/cedarrapids/sewing-surgical-masks.aspx&quot;&gt;UnityPoint Health pattern&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.vanwerthospital.org/community/covid-19&quot;&gt;Van Wert Hospital pattern&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://operationwecansewit.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/03/We-Can-Sew-It-Mask-Pattern-2.20.20-v4.pdf&quot;&gt;We Can Sew It pattern&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Face Shields&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://3dverkstan.se/protective-visor/&quot;&gt;3DVerkstan&lt;/a&gt;; this design is being mass produced by multiple NY-based architecture firms&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://airwolf3d.com/2020/03/27/covid-19-face-shield-3d-printable-file/&quot;&gt;Airwolf 3D &lt;/a&gt;design&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.delve.com/assets/documents/OPEN-SOURCE-FACE-SHIELD-DRAWING-v1.PDF&quot;&gt;Badger Shield&lt;/a&gt; (being manufactured by Ford)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://budmen.com/&quot;&gt;Budmen Industries&lt;/a&gt; (upstate NY based)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.carbon3d.com/covid19/&quot;&gt;Carbon3D&lt;/a&gt; (design from a 3d printer company; they also connect requests for PPE with manufacturing partners)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cdamlab.com/faceshield.html&quot;&gt;CDAM&lt;/a&gt; laser-printed design&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://covidmadrid.com/modelos-a-imprimir/&quot;&gt;CovidMadrid&lt;/a&gt; design: approved by the Spanish government for clinical use&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://covidsupplyconnection.com/3d-printed-face-shield/&quot;&gt;CovidSupplyConnection &lt;/a&gt;– NIH approved&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://daniepstein.com/daniepstein/3d-printable-face-shield/&quot;&gt;Dani Epstein &lt;/a&gt;design&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/document/d/10GC1GmupDX6Kft0uBJ31SmSHij6VMt39vFdcCBuAEQs/edit&quot;&gt;David Sims&lt;/a&gt; design – manufacturing PPE in the UK.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://projects.fablabs.io/+fablabbenfica/protective-face-shield&quot;&gt;FabLabs &lt;/a&gt;design&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/gliax/faceshield&quot;&gt;GliaX&lt;/a&gt; design&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://gcmiatl.com/COVID-19-personal-protective-equipment&quot;&gt;GCMI design&lt;/a&gt; – available only to GMP companies&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://hammerspacehobby.com/covid-19/&quot;&gt;Hammerspace &lt;/a&gt;design&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instructables.com/id/Face-Shield-for-Medical-Personnel/&quot;&gt;Hayward CA design&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://cults3d.com/en/3d-model/tool/face-cover-covid-19&quot;&gt;Hintech&lt;/a&gt;: “not medically tested”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://hellosewing.com/homemade-plastic-face-shield/&quot;&gt;Household materials&lt;/a&gt; face shield design&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://gitlab.com/lucidminds/Openfullfaceshield&quot;&gt;LucidMinds&lt;/a&gt; design&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/MakersAsylumIndia/Covid-19&quot;&gt;MakersAsylumIndia&lt;/a&gt; face shield design&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://wikifactory.com/+makersvscovid/face-shield&quot;&gt;MakersvCovid&lt;/a&gt; design (validated by two Portuguese hospitals)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.notion.so/Morakana-Faceshield-7d755c01f3014b78b2c405902acdcd81&quot;&gt;Morakana Shield&lt;/a&gt; – applied for NIH certification&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thingiverse.com/thing:4246351?fbclid=IwAR2PXFBQAiL4XiTqk7zUbfgRZozBKzeaogmRexrtnIvSRjzQf4JG2bzvjz8&quot;&gt;Near East University &lt;/a&gt;design, producing 100/day in Cyprus&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://3dprint.nih.gov/discover/3DPX-013359&quot;&gt;NIH&lt;/a&gt; face shield design&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://open-face-website.now.sh/&quot;&gt;OpenFace&lt;/a&gt;: plastic open source face shield, makeable from McMaster Carr materials. Being tested by Mt. Sinai in NYC; plans to provide 50k shields/week&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/document/d/1kkmi4AXXiO3MM34HUSQM1HEoQGzZ9lCmX02rIgVbk9Q/edit#&quot;&gt;Origami Face Shield &lt;/a&gt;(came out of Helpful Engineering; can be made at a rate of 5000-50,000 units per day via reel-to-reel laser die cutting)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://drive.google.com/drive/folders/1iXL7_kgRxMOVB2Q1Rve6HhigsF9-32Aw?fbclid=IwAR06wlIB9uwzgeLhwVAba0Bzo1lHaJ4lzP6y_24c6IsJ_uH36fuvNSN-FsM&quot;&gt;Pellegrin CHU &lt;/a&gt;face shield (currently in use in a hospital in Bordeaux, France)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://precuris.com/faceshields/&quot;&gt;Precuris&lt;/a&gt; design&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.prusaprinters.org/prints/25857-prusa-protective-face-shield-rc2&quot;&gt;Prusa &lt;/a&gt;design: verified by Czech Ministry of Health&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thingiverse.com/thing:4236526&quot;&gt;Robotikos design&lt;/a&gt;: laser cut&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instructables.com/id/Soda-Bottle-Safety-Goggles./&quot;&gt;Soda Bottle Safety Goggles&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://go.stratasys.com/lp-face-shield.html&quot;&gt;Stratasys design&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thingiverse.com/thing:4155735&quot;&gt;Thingiverse&lt;/a&gt; pattern for laser-cut plastic glasses&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.myminifactory.com/object/3d-print-laser-free-face-shield-face-mask-frame-114656?fbclid=IwAR0Uh7Kw0iADfCkCQ6ArVwhYyyjt319X7WaafqzO1Mx4kTxS_ONHP7UPKmE&quot;&gt;Transparency&lt;/a&gt; face shield (made from overhead projector transparencies)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thingiverse.com/thing:4240063?fbclid=IwAR1N3dSn1WMR_XqI1uFaxwIwIpRl3UJOwwuyVrZ3rC4v1XwHQ4Ch_0eUigk&quot;&gt;Transparency&lt;/a&gt; face shield #2&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://dimin.com/face-shield/?nab=1&amp;amp;utm_referrer=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.google.com%2Furl%3Fq%3Dhttps%253A%252F%252Fdimin.com%252Fface-shield%252F%26sa%3DD%26sntz%3D1%26usg%3DAFQjCNHFiY34C6lJsTGSD3oLoLZGnjnonQ&quot;&gt;UKansas&lt;/a&gt; design&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/document/d/1kq4yI5qcNT4mQvI8Yl7W875CQ7Ixjv6Zy9HegUxD2xI/edit&quot;&gt;UPittsburgh &lt;/a&gt;single material design&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://making.engr.wisc.edu/shield/&quot;&gt;UWisconsin face shield design&lt;/a&gt; (being used in a local hospital)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Nonwoven Polypropylene Face Masks&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These may provide a better seal and more filter protection than cloth masks, though not as much as an N95.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.empirecovers.com/2020/03/25/make-up-to-150-face-masks-with-a-car-cover/&quot;&gt;Car cover face mask &lt;/a&gt;(instructional video)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://solutionshub.epam.com/solution/gentl-mask#utm_source=covid19-mask-design&amp;amp;utm_medium=press-release&amp;amp;utm_campaign=relief-efforts&amp;amp;utm_term=first-link&quot;&gt;GENTL&lt;/a&gt; mask (designed by EPAM)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://makermask.org/&quot;&gt;MakerMask &lt;/a&gt;(design from Helpful Engineering; doctor-reviewed)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;N95-Equivalent Masks&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.intermountain3d.com/covid-respirators.html&quot;&gt;Intermountain3D&lt;/a&gt; printed mask – passed N95 filter &amp;amp; fit test at St. Alphonsus Hospital, ID; uses polypropylene surgical wrap (which is widely available)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Filtration Masks (Note: these do not include the filters, which are in short supply)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.makethemasks.com/about-the-mask&quot;&gt;Montana Mask&lt;/a&gt; (clinically tested and currently used in the Billings Clinic)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thingiverse.com/thing:4231076&quot;&gt;Plastic Thermoformed Mask&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thingiverse.com/thing:4234487&quot;&gt;Vacuum Formed FP2 mask&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PAPR&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://imgur.com/gallery/UD7PEo0&quot;&gt;Diving mask design&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instructables.com/id/COVID-Swim-Mask-HEPA-PAPR/&quot;&gt;Swim Mask PAPR&lt;/a&gt;, designed by a gastroenterologist&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.3dwasp.com/en/protection-helmet-with-ventilation/&quot;&gt;Wasp Space Helmet&lt;/a&gt; 3d printed, ventilated &amp;amp; filtered helmet&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Noninvasive Ventilator Masks&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.isinnova.it/easy-covid19-eng/&quot;&gt;Isinnova&lt;/a&gt;: a full-face snorkel mask + 3d-printed valve, used as a CPAP mask in Italian hospitals&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Other Mask Types&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://diyn95.com/index.php/make-it-yourself-the-guide/&quot;&gt;AC filter respirator&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fixthemask.com/&quot;&gt;FixTheMask&lt;/a&gt;: an attachment that makes a surgical mask fit tighter, designed by Apple engineers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bad Ideas&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.brimshield.com/&quot;&gt;Brimshield&lt;/a&gt; face shield design – clips to a hat, doesn’t account for sanitation of hat&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://copper3d.com/hackthepandemic/#technical_considerations&quot;&gt;Copper 3D&lt;/a&gt; – 3D printed plastic masks will generally &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.prusaprinters.org/from-design-to-mass-3d-printing-of-medical-shields-in-three-days/&quot;&gt;not form a tight enough seal to protect&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://gitlab.com/entraide-maker-covid-19/masques-3d/-/tree/xavpourmanu/Masque%20type%20Mode%20Spiralisation%20des%20contours&quot;&gt;Spiralized Contour mask&lt;/a&gt; – also a 3D printed mask, will not seal tight enough to protect&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thingiverse.com/thing:4177128&quot;&gt;Plastic FFP &lt;/a&gt; – also a 3D printed mask, will not seal tight enough to protect&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DIY Manufacturing Groups&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://3dprintedppe.com/?fbclid=IwAR01s0yasaYXudoSRcnL9DVWqPPvVU2kE0R4uhhwSVDgoJp4IJnTQnfnm5M&quot;&gt;3D Printed PPE&lt;/a&gt;: an online directory of maker groups around the world 3d printing PPE&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://enablingthefuture.org/&quot;&gt;e-NABLE&lt;/a&gt;: network of volunteers using 3d printers to make prosthetics and now COVID19 supplies&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.inksmith.ca/pages/ppe-face-shields&quot;&gt;Inksmith&lt;/a&gt;: Canadian educational 3d printing company, manufactures &amp;amp; donates face shields to hospitals&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.opshieldsup.org/&quot;&gt;Operation Shields Up&lt;/a&gt; is a volunteer maker group in the Sacramento Valley (CA) manufacturing and donating Prusa face shields.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.makethemasks.com/&quot;&gt;MakeTheMask&lt;/a&gt;: coordinates makers to 3d print the Montana Mask&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://maskforce.org/&quot;&gt;MaskForce&lt;/a&gt;: a 2000+ member FB group, making DIY cloth face masks and plastic face shields&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://maskmakervolunteers.com/&quot;&gt;Mask Maker Volunteers&lt;/a&gt;: a 3000+ member FB group making DIY cloth face masks&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sewingforlives.com/&quot;&gt;Sewing4Lives&lt;/a&gt;: volunteer seamstresses have delivered over 32,000 cloth face masks&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://shield48.eu/&quot;&gt;Shield48&lt;/a&gt;; EU based, makes face shields; 2620 produced, 15700 requests&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Commercial Manufacturers&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://cyclingmagazine.ca/sections/news/cycling-company-fight-covid-19/&quot;&gt;10 cycling companies&lt;/a&gt; have switched to making cloth face masks.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://wwd.com/fashion-news/fashion-scoops/fashion-designers-make-masks-hospital-gown-hand-sanitizer-to-fight-coronavirus-1203545006/&quot;&gt;38 fashion designers &lt;/a&gt;are pivoting to producing masks and gowns for healthcare workers; Eddie Bauer is even making N95s.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.digitalengineering247.com/article/3diligent-helping-coordinate-digital-manufacturing-response-to-help-restock-vital-personal-protective-equipment-ppe-in-short-supply-due-to-covid-19/&quot;&gt;3Diligen&lt;/a&gt;t is working with manufacturers to test the viability of new PPE designs, and providing a streamlined procurement process to hospitals.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://news.3m.com/blog/3m-stories/3m-responds-2019-novel-coronavirus&quot;&gt;3M&lt;/a&gt; plans to double their production of N95 masks over the next year, up to 2 billion globally.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://airwolf3d.com/2020/03/17/airwolf3d-offering-emergency-additive-manufacturing-services/&quot;&gt;Airwolf 3D&lt;/a&gt;, in California, has pledged to use their 3d printers for respirator valves.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.necn.com/news/coronavirus/nhs-bauer-to-switch-from-making-hockey-helmets-to-coronavirus-face-shields/2251010/&quot;&gt;Bauer&lt;/a&gt;, the hockey mask manufacturer, is shifting to making face shields&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bcn3d.com/bcn3d-farm-3d-printing-projects-against-covid-19/&quot;&gt;BCN3D&lt;/a&gt;, a Barcelona-based 3D printer company, has pledged its 63 printers for COVID19 projects&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://cleantechnica.com/2020/03/29/carmakers-to-the-rescue-n95-mask-mass-production/&quot;&gt;BYD&lt;/a&gt;, a Chinese auto company, is producing 5 million N95 masks per day.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wired.com/story/disney-donating-100000-n95-masks-covid-19-relief/&quot;&gt;Disney &lt;/a&gt;is donating 100,000 N95 masks.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.unionleader.com/news/health/coronavirus/gun-accessory-maker-now-sews-ppe-for-nursing-home/article_af21c2d5-10bc-5d0a-96d1-7119db41fbd9.html&quot;&gt;Cole-Tac,&lt;/a&gt; a firearms accessories manufacturer, is sewing gowns and masks&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://techcrunch.com/2020/03/24/ford-and-3m-ge-and-the-uaw-to-build-respirators-ventilators-and-faceshields-for-coronavirus-fight/&quot;&gt;Ford &lt;/a&gt;Motors is making PAPRs, 100,000 face shields a week, and donating N95 masks.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wpri.com/health/coronavirus/honeywell-to-start-making-masks-in-ri-for-covid-19-white-house-official-says/&quot;&gt;Honeywell&lt;/a&gt; is adding US manufacturing of N95 masks.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.makergear.com/products/covid-19-donation&quot;&gt;MakerGear,&lt;/a&gt; a 3D printer company, is manufacturing and donating face shields.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.chemengonline.com/mitsui-chemicals-expands-production-of-meltblown-nonwoven-materials/&quot;&gt;Mitsui Chemicals,&lt;/a&gt; a Japanese company, has expanded their capacity to make melt-blown fabrics by 50%.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.protolabs.com/covid-19-updates/&quot;&gt;ProtoLabs&lt;/a&gt;, an on-demand manufacturer, is waiving expedite fees for PPE supplies.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.chemengonline.com/radicigroup-to-deliver-personal-protective-equipment-for-doctors-and-healthcare-workers-fighting-covid-19/&quot;&gt;RadiciGroup&lt;/a&gt; (based in Bergamo, Italy) is producing PPE&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.resonancecompanies.com/about/&quot;&gt;Resonance&lt;/a&gt;, which has a garment factory in the Dominican Republic, is making PPE to distribute there.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://businessfacilities.com/2020/03/sinopec-builds-new-factory-to-help-combat-covid-19-in-12-days/&quot;&gt;Sinopec&lt;/a&gt;, a Chinese company, has built a new factory to produce melt-blown nonwoven fabric for N95 masks.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.stratasys.com/&quot;&gt;Stratasys&lt;/a&gt; is manufacturing 5000 face shields per week.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thefactorynyc.com/emergency-services.html&quot;&gt;The Factory NYC &lt;/a&gt;is fabricating temporary facilities and medical supplies for COVID19&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://combatingcovid.com/&quot;&gt;Voodoo Manufacturing&lt;/a&gt;, based in Brooklyn, has repurposed its factory to produce face shields, which are for sale at $100 each.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Distribution, Donation, &amp;amp; Coordination&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not including here all the organizations that are donating PPE or money for the COVID19 effort, only orgs that a potential donor (like you!) could use to get PPE where it needs to go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There has been a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; of corporate and individual philanthropy and it’s not worth tabulating everyone who has donated to date.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.covidsos.com.au/&quot;&gt;COVID SOS&lt;/a&gt;, an Australian group, connects suppliers of PPE with hospitals&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.damerousky.cz/&quot;&gt;DameRousky &lt;/a&gt;is a Czech group connecting cloth mask sewers with people who need masks&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.donateppe.org/&quot;&gt;DonatePPE&lt;/a&gt; connects donors with hospitals that need PPE&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://helppnwcvd19.com/&quot;&gt;HelpPNWCovid19&lt;/a&gt; is a Pacific Northwest based group for connecting makers to hospitals in need of PPE&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://flexport.org/&quot;&gt;Flexport.org &lt;/a&gt;offers discount shipping for COVID19 medical supplies.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/forms/d/e/1FAIpQLSe015Ylohgm7hE5lRsekdK01_OqElYeSAzqyHx7HbOmrJ_MjQ/viewform&quot;&gt;FormLabs&lt;/a&gt; is connecting people who have 3D printers to people who need 3D printed parts.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.getmeppe-sfbay.org/&quot;&gt;GetMePPE Bay Area&lt;/a&gt; coordinates donations of PPE and volunteers for the San Francisco Bay Area.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://getusppe.org/&quot;&gt;GetUsPPE&lt;/a&gt; coordinates donors, healthcare workers, and makers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://gracefarms.org/covid19-response/&quot;&gt;Grace Farms Relief Fund for Connecticut&lt;/a&gt; collects donations for food and medical supplies for Connecticut&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://makerhub.co/&quot;&gt;MakerHub&lt;/a&gt; connects makers of PPE to hospitals that need them&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mask-match.com/&quot;&gt;Mask Match&lt;/a&gt; connects mask donors to healthcare workers who need masks&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://masksfordocs.com/&quot;&gt;Masksfordocs&lt;/a&gt; accepts donations of money and PPE and distributes to hospitals&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/masks4medicine&quot;&gt;Masks4Medicine&lt;/a&gt; donates masks to hospitals in NYC.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.medicalteams.org/how-we-heal/natural-disasters/covid-19-response/&quot;&gt;Medical Teams International&lt;/a&gt;, based in the Pacific Northwest, has a fleet of vans supporting drive-thru testing and packs and ships PPE to hospitals. They are seeking donations.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://edc.nyc/covid-19-emergency-supply-sourcing-manufacturing&quot;&gt;NYCEDC&lt;/a&gt; is connecting PPE suppliers &amp;amp; manufacturers to New York City hospitals, and accepting donations.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://operationmasks.org/&quot;&gt;Operation Masks&lt;/a&gt; connects PPE suppliers to hospitals who need PPE&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://ppelink.wordpress.com/&quot;&gt;PPELink&lt;/a&gt; connects labs that can donate PPE to hospitals who need it.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.projectn95.org/&quot;&gt;Project N95&lt;/a&gt; connects suppliers, users, and distributors of PPE&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.providence.org/lp/100m-masks&quot;&gt;Providence&lt;/a&gt; (a hospital network spanning several states) is fundraising to buy and distribute PPE.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://wchstv.com/news/entertainment/meek-mills-prison-reform-group-donating-100000-masks&quot;&gt;REFORM alliance&lt;/a&gt; is donating 100,000 masks to prisons.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://repurposingproject.com/&quot;&gt;Repurposing Project&lt;/a&gt; coordinates Ohio manufacturers and hospitals to help retool factories to produce PPE.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/forms/d/e/1FAIpQLScZ0D7EGTxKW6utgeDgi5oA28DpxtbULgrnS4qJQJvTW5zNKQ/viewform&quot;&gt;Seattle Mask Brigade&lt;/a&gt; solicits donations of PPE in Seattle.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.swima.org/covid19/&quot;&gt;SWIMA &lt;/a&gt;coordinates PPE manufacturers in Southwest Idaho to respond to COVID19 with hospitals requesting donations.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://vmcfoundation.org/&quot;&gt;The Valley Medical Center Foundation&lt;/a&gt; in Santa Clara County, CA is collecting and distributing PPE donations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;State &amp;amp; Local Governments: US&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Arkansas
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://appengine.egov.com/apps/ar/lr/donate&quot;&gt;Little Rock, AK&lt;/a&gt; is accepting money donations to buy PPE&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;California
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.smcgov.org/press-release/march-19-2020-update-county-response-covid-19&quot;&gt;San Mateo County, CA&lt;/a&gt; is accepting PPE donations&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Colorado
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.denvergov.org/content/denvergov/en/environmental-health/news/coronavirus-info/donations---volunteering.html&quot;&gt;Denver, CO&lt;/a&gt; is accepting PPE donations&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Illinois
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kcchronicle.com/2020/03/27/kane-county-accepting-donations-of-personal-protective-equipment-for-covid-19-fight/a7vpq6k/&quot;&gt;Kane County, IL&lt;/a&gt; is accepting PPE donations&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nwitimes.com/news/local/govt-and-politics/indiana-continues-seeking-donations-of-covid-19-personal-protective-equipment/article_b6cc497f-d5d5-582c-9374-a2f9edf9ea74.html&quot;&gt;Indiana&lt;/a&gt; is accepting PPE donations&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Iowa
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://thegraphic-advocate.com/content/calhoun-county-consider-donating-personal-protective-equipment-assist-covid-19-response&quot;&gt;Calhoun County, IA &lt;/a&gt;is accepting PPE donations&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://news.nhcgov.com/news-releases/2020/03/new-hanover-county-daily-covid-19-update-total-case-count-now-14-ppe-donation-hours-expanded-through-saturday/&quot;&gt;Muscatine County, IA&lt;/a&gt; is accepting PPE donations&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mass.gov/covid-19-ppe-procurement-and-donation-program&quot;&gt;Massachussetts&lt;/a&gt; is accepting PPE donations.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.missourienterprise.org/blog/302-covid-19-the-state-is-seeking-help-to-make-more-medical-products&quot;&gt;Missouri&lt;/a&gt; is interested in talking to manufacturers of masks and gowns&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;New Jersey
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.insidernj.com/tedesco-bergen-county-begin-accepting-ppe-donations-county-annex-building-located-paramus/&quot;&gt;Bergen County&lt;/a&gt; is accepting PPE donations&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.insidernj.com/gloucester-county-office-emergency-management-seeks-ppe-donations/&quot;&gt;Gloucester County, NJ&lt;/a&gt; is accepting PPE donations&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tapinto.net/sections/government/articles/new-brunswick-accepting-donations-of-personal-protective-equipment&quot;&gt;New Brunswick, NJ&lt;/a&gt; is accepting PPE donations&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mycentraljersey.com/story/news/local/2020/03/22/coronavirus-somerset-county-asks-donations-ppe-supplies/2895391001/&quot;&gt;Somerset County, NJ&lt;/a&gt; is accepting PPE donations&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sussex.nj.us/documents/coronavirus-2020/20200329-ppe-donations.pdf&quot;&gt;Sussex County, NJ&lt;/a&gt; is accepting PPE donations&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;New Mexico
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://nmpoliticalreport.com/2020/03/20/abq-asking-for-ppe-donations-and-other-updates-from-mayor-keller/&quot;&gt;Albuquerque &lt;/a&gt;is accepting PPE donations&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/NYGovCuomo/status/1241040393086685186&quot;&gt;New York &lt;/a&gt; is willing to “pay a premium” for PPE
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.rivernewsonline.com/main.asp?SectionID=6&amp;amp;SubSectionID=47&amp;amp;ArticleID=88393&quot;&gt;Oneida County, NY&lt;/a&gt; is accepting PPE donations&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;North Carolina
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://news.nhcgov.com/news-releases/2020/03/new-hanover-county-daily-covid-19-update-total-case-count-now-14-ppe-donation-hours-expanded-through-saturday/&quot;&gt;New Hanover County, NC&lt;/a&gt; is accepting PPE donations&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.health.nd.gov/news/fund-set-donations-aid-covid-19-response-personal-protective-equipment-also-being-accepted&quot;&gt;North Dakota&lt;/a&gt; is accepting money and PPE donations&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.richlandsource.com/news/covid19/ohio-requests-ppe-donations-sets-up-covid--online-information/article_4c339b4c-6fb5-11ea-a370-e754e44b255c.html&quot;&gt;Ohio&lt;/a&gt; is accepting PPE donations&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.myoregon.gov/2020/03/19/medical-professionals-asked-to-donate-surplus-ppe/&quot;&gt;Oregon&lt;/a&gt; is accepting PPE donations
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lanecounty.org/cms/one.aspx?pageId=16563883&quot;&gt;Lane County, OR&lt;/a&gt; is accepting PPE donations&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Virginia
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.alexandriava.gov/news_display.aspx?id=114511&quot;&gt;Alexandria, VA&lt;/a&gt; is accepting PPE donations&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.alexandriava.gov/news_display.aspx?id=114511&quot;&gt;Alexandria, VA&lt;/a&gt; is accepting PPE donations&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.vbgov.com/news/pages/selected.aspx?release=4737&amp;amp;title=virginia+beach+accepting+donations+of+personal+protective+equipment+for+its+covid-19+response&quot;&gt;Virginia Beach, VA&lt;/a&gt; is accepting PPE donations&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://coronavirus.wa.gov/how-you-can-help&quot;&gt;Washington &lt;/a&gt; is accepting PPE donations
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://durkan.seattle.gov/2020/03/city-of-seattle-leading-coordinated-effort-to-collect-critically-needed-personal-protective-equipment-for-first-responders-medical-professionals-on-the-frontlines-of-covid-19-response/&quot;&gt;Seattle, WA &lt;/a&gt;is accepting PPE donations&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://fox6now.com/2020/03/27/wisconsin-creates-personal-protective-equipment-ppe-donation-buyback-program/&quot;&gt;Wisconsin&lt;/a&gt; has a PPE donation and buyback program
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.browncountywi.gov/community/covid-19/general-information/&quot;&gt;Brown County, WI&lt;/a&gt; is accepting PPE donations&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.milwaukeeindependent.com/special/covid-19/milwaukee-county-seeks-donations-personal-protective-equipment-covid-19-frontline-workers/&quot;&gt;Milwaukee County, WI&lt;/a&gt; is accepting PPE donations&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Other Governments&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Canada
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ottawamatters.com/local-news/city-of-ottawa-accepting-donations-of-personal-protective-equipment-for-covid-19-response-2211633&quot;&gt;Ottawa&lt;/a&gt; is accepting PPE donations&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Information&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://covidtracking.com/&quot;&gt;Covid Tracking&lt;/a&gt; – a project from The Atlantic to aggregate data on US COVID19 testing results.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://findthemasks.com/&quot;&gt;FindTheMasks&lt;/a&gt; – a website with a map of hospital locations currently accepting mask donations and their instructions/requirements to donors.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/14kkwrz8pHXTdkVQQHcWAQ4H0yFAKIGznzNr_RH0btOo/edit#gid=1221424084&quot;&gt;Manufacturer Info Spreadsheet&lt;/a&gt; on face shield manufacturers and how many face shields they’re ready to ship&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="covid-19" /><category term="lit-review" /><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Disinfectants and Anti-Microbial Surfaces Against COVID-19</title><link href="https://srconstantin.github.io/2020/03/31/disinfectants.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Disinfectants and Anti-Microbial Surfaces Against COVID-19" /><published>2020-03-31T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-03-31T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://srconstantin.github.io/2020/03/31/disinfectants</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://srconstantin.github.io/2020/03/31/disinfectants.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/1200px-NatCopper.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;copper&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A little good news on the COVID-19 front: yes, you can kill the virus on surfaces, with easily available disinfectants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Copper surfaces, silver particles, alcohol-based disinfectants, and UV light will kill the virus.  Frequently touched items, especially in public places, should probably just be irradiated with UVC light and/or coated with copper as a routine prevention measure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Regular UV light is an effective disinfectant but can also blind people and burn skin; UVC is a shorter wavelength, equally effective against microbes but not harmful to eyes or skin.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Do Copper Surfaces Kill/Inactivate Coronaviruses?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In an experiment with aerosolized SARS-CoV-2 and SARS-CoV-1, at 21-23 degrees C and 40% humidity, both reached undetectable levels within 8 hours exposure to copper; by contrast, they lasted 72 hours on stainless steel and plastic.[1]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;H1N1 influenza, which was another pandemic virus, though not a coronavirus, lasted significantly less time on copper than stainless steel; 10^5 viable viruses after 24 hours on stainless steel vs. 10^2 viable viruses after 2 hours on copper.[2]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Human coronavirus 229E remains infectious on plastic, ceramic, glass, and stainless steel for at least 5 days, was inactivated in less than 5 minutes on copper and brass when applied dry, and inactivated in less than an hour when applied in solution to metal alloys containing &amp;gt;75% copper.[4]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using copper-coated surfaces in real-world environments reduces microbial contamination. In 5 residential healthcare facilities, where half of the doorknobs and handrails were coated with copper alloys while half were not, the bacterial concentration was significantly (p &amp;lt; 0.0001) lower on the copper-coated doorknobs and handrails.[5]  Similarly, when weights and grips in a gym were coated with copper alloy or left as rubber or stainless steel, the bacterial concentrations on the copper-coated surfaces were 94% lower than the controls.[6]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Silver Ion Zeolites as Anti-Microbial Surfaces&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Commercially available silver zeolite powder (AgION powder, manufactured by Sinanen Co.) completely inactivated SARS-CoV at concentrations above 375 mg/L.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Zeolites are fine, talc-like powders that can be incorporated into coatings to produce antimicrobial surfaces; the FDA has approved zeolites for use in food packaging.[3]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Disinfectants&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a study of 7 disinfectant liquids on the SARS coronavirus, including several with &amp;gt;80% ethanol as active ingredient, all of them significantly reduced SARS concentrations, by a factor of at least 1000.[7]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;70%+ ethanol was effective at reducing (by a factor of &amp;gt;1000) the infectivity of both SARS and MERS coronaviruses; so was 50%+ 2-propanol, hydrogen peroxide, glutaraldehyde, formaldehyde, and povidone iodine. Chlorhexidine was not effective.[9]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a study of human coronaviruses 229E and OC43, soap, bleach, and Proviodine (the active ingredient was iodine) all completely inactivated the viruses.[8]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Axe dishwashing detergent, sodium hypochlorite solution, and the disinfectant Virkon S, all killed SARS-CoV virus by a factor of at least 1000.[10]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Against two coronaviruses, mouse hepatitis virus and transmissible gastroenteritis virus, a solution of 70% ethanol reduced viral infectivity by a factor of &amp;gt;1000; phenolic, sodium hypochlorite, and orthopthalaldehyde did not.[11]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;UVC Radiation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Exposure of SARS virus to UVC radiation for six minutes results in a 400-fold reduction in infectivity.  UVA and gamma radiation did not affect infectivity.[12]  Another study of SARS found 1000-fold inactivation from 15 minutes of exposure to UVC.[13]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A study of Ebola virus and MERS virus found that UVC light at &amp;gt;0.1 J/cm^2 reduced infectivity more than 5000-fold in both.  Methylene blue plus light at &amp;gt;30 J/cm^2 also reduced infectivity 2000-fold in both.[14]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Far-UVC light (207-222 nm) inactivates bacteria without harm to human skin.  It also reduces H1N1 infectivity by 100-fold at low doses: 2 mJ/cm^2.[15]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;222-nm far-UVC light applied to a mouse wound where MRSA bacteria had been spread reduced skin bacteria concentrations by &amp;gt;1000-fold, just like 254-nm conventional antimicrobial UV irradiation, but only the 254-nm light increased skin thickness significantly ( a measure of skin damage.)[16]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[1]van Doremalen, Neeltje, et al. “Aerosol and surface stability of SARS-CoV-2 as compared with SARS-CoV-1.” New England Journal of Medicine (2020).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[2]Otter, J. A., et al. “Transmission of SARS and MERS coronaviruses and influenza virus in healthcare settings: the possible role of dry surface contamination.” Journal of Hospital Infection 92.3 (2016): 235-250.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[3]Feied, Craig. “Novel Antimicrobial Surface Coatings and the Potential for Reduced Fomite Transmission of SARS and Other Pathogens.” (2004): 1-22.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[4]Warnes, Sarah L., Zoë R. Little, and C. William Keevil. “Human coronavirus 229E remains infectious on common touch surface materials.” MBio 6.6 (2015): e01697-15.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[5]Colin, Marius, et al. “Copper alloy touch surfaces in healthcare facilities: an effective solution to prevent bacterial spreading.” Materials 11.12 (2018): 2479.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[6]Ibrahim, Zina, et al. “Reduction of bacterial burden by copper alloys on high-touch athletic center surfaces.” American journal of infection control 46.2 (2018): 197-201.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[7]Rabenau, H. F., et al. “Efficacy of various disinfectants against SARS coronavirus.” Journal of Hospital Infection 61.2 (2005): 107-111.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[8]Sizun, J., M. W. N. Yu, and P. J. Talbot. “Survival of human coronaviruses 229E and OC43 in suspension and after drying onsurfaces: a possible source ofhospital-acquired infections.” Journal of Hospital Infection 46.1 (2000): 55-60.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[9]Kampf, Günter, et al. “Persistence of coronaviruses on inanimate surfaces and its inactivation with biocidal agents.” Journal of Hospital Infection (2020).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[10]Lai, Mary YY, Peter KC Cheng, and Wilina WL Lim. “Survival of severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus.” Clinical Infectious Diseases 41.7 (2005): e67-e71.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[11]Hulkower, Rachel L., et al. “Inactivation of surrogate coronaviruses on hard surfaces by health care germicides.” American journal of infection control 39.5 (2011): 401-407.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[12]Darnell, Miriam ER, et al. “Inactivation of the coronavirus that induces severe acute respiratory syndrome, SARS-CoV.” Journal of virological methods 121.1 (2004): 85-91.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[13]Darnell, Miriam ER, and Deborah R. Taylor. “Evaluation of inactivation methods for severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus in noncellular blood products.” Transfusion 46.10 (2006): 1770-1777.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[14]Eickmann, Markus, et al. “Inactivation of Ebola virus and Middle East respiratory syndrome coronavirus in platelet concentrates and plasma by ultraviolet C light and methylene blue plus visible light, respectively.” Transfusion 58.9 (2018): 2202-2207.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[15]Welch, David, et al. “Far-UVC light: A new tool to control the spread of airborne-mediated microbial diseases.” Scientific Reports 8.1 (2018): 1-7.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[16]Ponnaiya, Brian, et al. “Far-UVC light prevents MRSA infection of superficial wounds in vivo.” PloS one 13.2 (2018).&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="covid-19" /><category term="lit-review" /><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Home Care for Mild COVID-19</title><link href="https://srconstantin.github.io/2020/03/27/home-care-mild-COVID19.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Home Care for Mild COVID-19" /><published>2020-03-27T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-03-27T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://srconstantin.github.io/2020/03/27/home-care-mild-COVID19</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://srconstantin.github.io/2020/03/27/home-care-mild-COVID19.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/sick-mom.png&quot; alt=&quot;sickmom&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What Should You Do For A Mild Case of COVID-19?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, you, or someone in your household, has a flu-like or pneumonia-like illness that you suspect is COVID-19.  What can you do to increase your chances of getting well, and decrease your chances of getting sick enough to need a hospital?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This document doesn’t actually have a lot of answers.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For respiratory infections not severe enough to need hospitalization, most medical guidelines advise identifying the pathogen, prescribing antivirals or antibiotics effective against that pathogen (we don’t know that much yet about which ones work for COVID-19), and otherwise practicing “supportive care” – rest, fluids, treating symptoms, avoiding infecting others.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Supportive care often isn’t specified in studies, which is annoying, because it means we don’t have data on the effectiveness or potential disadvantages of over-the-counter medications to treat symptoms like fever and cough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the purposes of this document, I am restricting attention to studies and reports of human subjects – no animal or in-vitro evidence – but I am including correlational evidence or even case reports, and I am including evidence from other diseases than COVID-19 where it seems that the result could translate. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(For instance, I’m not including all the evidence about oseltamivir (Tamiflu) being effective against influenza, because it doesn’t seem to help with COVID-19; but I am including evidence about N-acetylcysteine preventing and reducing the severity of influenza, because NAC seems to work by generic immune-stimulatory effects rather than an effect specific to a particular virus.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s important to get tested by a doctor if you have a respiratory illness you think is COVID-19. Even if you can’t get access to a COVID-19 test, you might also have a different bacterial or viral infection (either instead of or in addition to COVID-19) which is treatable by antivirals or antibiotics. It’s very common for viral pneumonia to be complicated by an opportunistic bacterial infection, and killing the bacteria can help improve outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Symptoms of Mild COVID-19&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most common symptoms of mild COVID-19 are fever, cough, fatigue and muscle pain, and headache.  Other symptoms include sore throat, difficulty breathing, diarrhea, chest tightness, fear of cold, and sputum production.[1][2][4] Rash on the limbs is also possible.[3]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rest and Fluids&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just like with any mild illness, public health departments are advising patients who have mild COVID-19 to get rest and drink fluids.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I couldn’t find experimental evidence for this but it makes sense and can’t hurt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sanitation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The WHO’s recommendations for home care for mild COVID-19 cases are primarily about avoiding infection for caregivers; patients should be in their own, well-ventilated room if possible, caregivers should wear masks and clean &amp;amp; disinfect surfaces daily, etc.[5]  There is no mention of how to optimize for recovery of the patient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Avoid Ibuprofen&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;France’s health minister has counseled patients with mild COVID-19 not to use ibuprofen or other NSAIDs to treat symptoms, after four young patients with the disease developed severe symptoms after using NSAIDs.  Patients were advised to take paracetamol instead.[6]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Avoid Corticosteroids&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Corticosteroids were associated with increased mortality and viral shedding in H1N1 viral pneumonia.[8]  Corticosteroids increased viral load in SARS.[11]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Favipiravir&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In an open-label study, COVID-19 patients who took favipiravir had on average a shorter course of disease (4 days vs 12 days, p &amp;lt; 0.001) than those who took a combination of lopinavir and ritonavir.  All patients in the study also received interferon-alpha1b by aerosol inhalation, rehydration, electrolytes, antipyretics, analgesics, and antiemetics.[7]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hydroxychloroquine and Azithromycin&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a non-randomized study of 36 patients with COVID-19 treated with placebo, hydroxychloroquine, or hydroxychloroquine + azithromycin, hydroxychloroquine had a significantly higher rate of virological cure (p &amp;lt; 0.001) than placebo.  By day 6, 70% of hydroxychloroquine patients were cured, compared to 20% with placebo. With azithromycin + hydroxychloroquine, 100% of patients were cured by day 5.[10]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, a Chinese study (reported by Bloomberg [12] because it’s in Chinese) of 30 patients given hydroxychloroquine or placebo found no difference in the rate of cure between the two groups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;N-Acetylcysteine&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a randomized trial of 262 elderly patients, assigned to N-acetylcysteine or placebo for 6 months, NAC significantly (p&amp;lt;0.01) reduced the incidence of influenza-like episodes, and significantly (p &amp;lt; 0.001) reduced the incidence of headache, muscle soreness, sore throat, and cough. In the NAC group, 25% of serologically confirmed H1N1 influenza cases were symptomatic, compared to 79% in the placebo group.[9]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Air Quality&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a retrospective study in Utah hospitals, high concentrations of particulate matter in the air were associated with slightly but significantly higher (OR = 1.004) rates of admission to the emergency room for pneumonia, and slightly (OR = 1.02) but significantly higher rates of pneumonia mortality.[12] &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having air filters in the home may be slightly protective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[1]Wan, Suxin, et al. “Clinical Features and Treatment of COVID‐19 Patients in Northeast Chongqing.” Journal of Medical Virology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[2]Ong, John, Barnaby Edward Young, and Sharon Ong. “COVID-19 in gastroenterology: a clinical perspective.” Gut (2020).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[3]Lu, Shubiao, et al. “Alert for non‐respiratory symptoms of Coronavirus Disease 2019 (COVID‐19) patients in epidemic period: A case report of familial cluster with three asymptomatic COVID‐19 patients.” Journal of Medical Virology (2020).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[4]Xu, Wentao, et al. “Epidemiologic Features and Clinical Findings of COVID-19-Infected Patients in Suzhou.” Available at SSRN 3551352 (2020).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[5]World Health Organization. Home care for patients with COVID-19 presenting with mild symptoms and management of their contacts: interim guidance, 17 March 2020. No. WHO/nCov/IPC/HomeCare/2020.3. World Health Organization, 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[6]Day, Michael. “Covid-19: ibuprofen should not be used for managing symptoms, say doctors and scientists.” (2020).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[7]Cai, Qingxian, et al. “Experimental Treatment with Favipiravir for COVID-19: An Open-Label Control Study.” Engineering (2020).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[8]Cao, Bin, et al. “Adjuvant corticosteroid treatment in adults with influenza A (H7N9) viral pneumonia.” Critical care medicine 44.6 (2016): e318-e328.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[9]De Flora, S., C. Grassi, and L. Carati. “Attenuation of influenza-like symptomatology and improvement of cell-mediated immunity with long-term N-acetylcysteine treatment.” European Respiratory Journal 10.7 (1997): 1535-1541.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[10]Gautret, Philippe, et al. “Hydroxychloroquine and azithromycin as a treatment of COVID-19: results of an open-label non-randomized clinical trial.” International Journal of Antimicrobial Agents (2020): 105949.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[11]Lee, Nelson, et al. “Effects of early corticosteroid treatment on plasma SARS-associated Coronavirus RNA concentrations in adult patients.” Journal of clinical virology 31.4 (2004): 304-309.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[12]Pirozzi, Cheryl S., et al. “Short-term air pollution and incident pneumonia. A case–crossover study.” Annals of the American Thoracic Society 15.4 (2018): 449-459.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[12]https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2020-03-25/hydroxychloroquine-no-better-than-regular-covid-19-care-in-study&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="covid-19" /><category term="lit-review" /><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Tangled Thinking 3 – Motivated Cognition and Suffering</title><link href="https://srconstantin.github.io/2020/03/25/tangled-thinking-3.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Tangled Thinking 3 -- Motivated Cognition and Suffering" /><published>2020-03-25T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-03-25T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://srconstantin.github.io/2020/03/25/tangled-thinking-3</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://srconstantin.github.io/2020/03/25/tangled-thinking-3.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/dogface.png&quot; alt=&quot;dogface&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still have a lot of planned COVID-19 lit review posts, but I’m going to take a quick break and go back to my sequence on psychology/cognition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might recall that in &lt;a href=&quot;https://srconstantin.github.io/2020/02/21/tangled-thinking-1.html&quot;&gt;the first post in this sequence&lt;/a&gt; I laid out a framework where the content of our conscious minds is made up of &lt;strong&gt;mental objects&lt;/strong&gt;, much of what we do when we think, act, or perceive is a process of reconciling (apparent) &lt;strong&gt;conflicts&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;contradictions&lt;/strong&gt; between our mental objects, and &lt;strong&gt;suffering&lt;/strong&gt; is what we experience when we actively &lt;em&gt;refuse&lt;/em&gt; to resolve a contradiction or indeed deny its existence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;a href=&quot;https://srconstantin.github.io/2020/02/24/tangled-thinking-2.html&quot;&gt;second post&lt;/a&gt; I talked about &lt;strong&gt;motivated cognition&lt;/strong&gt;, which is defined as being motivated to have certain &lt;em&gt;beliefs&lt;/em&gt; rather than being motivated to achieve certain outcomes “out there” in the world. And I clarified that the problem with motivated cognition isn’t that people have motives, but that they’re in a sense motivated &lt;em&gt;about the wrong things&lt;/em&gt; – that it’s dysfunctional to turn your optimization power inward (believing things because you want to believe them) rather than outward (doing things because you want to do them.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That raises some new questions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, how does motivated cognition (optimizing for what &lt;em&gt;internal&lt;/em&gt; mental experiences you want to have) relate to suffering (refusing to resolve contradictions)?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, what do we even mean by internal vs. external?  Isn’t that kind of dualist? Why is it good to optimize for what you want to achieve in the external world, but bad to optimize for what kinds of internal mental states you want to have? A priori this isn’t a really principled distinction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can resolve both questions at once.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Out in the real world”, we saw in &lt;a href=&quot;https://srconstantin.github.io/2020/02/21/tangled-thinking-1.html&quot;&gt;part 1&lt;/a&gt;, from a subjective perspective, really just means “consistent with the experiences, mental objects, phenomena, etc, that I &lt;em&gt;will&lt;/em&gt; have, but haven’t had yet.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can’t know anything, &lt;em&gt;yet&lt;/em&gt;, about the things I’m still ignorant of, by definition. Those are things that are &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; currently mental objects in my mind. They are not in my model.  They are outside my current cognitive “world.”  The unknown. The out-of-frame. The unmapped Universe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, if I believe in the Universe, I believe that &lt;em&gt;when&lt;/em&gt; I encounter these new, out-of-model, surprising things, I will eventually be able to reconcile them with all the &lt;em&gt;current&lt;/em&gt; mental objects in my subjective “world.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I am “optimizing for a state of reality”, or “having preferences about reality”, the things I have preferences about are still mental objects – mental objects are all I have subjective access to!  BUT, I am trying to achieve a setup of these mental objects that will &lt;em&gt;survive&lt;/em&gt; new discoveries, new data, ontology shifts, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I try to fool myself, usually the false belief is &lt;em&gt;fragile&lt;/em&gt;. There is some new data I must not acquire because it would destabilize the belief. If I want to believe I can still make the train, I have to not check my watch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s what it means to not be optimizing for reality; you’re optimizing your subjective world in a fragile way, that would collapse completely if you explored even a little bit in the wrong direction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Oscar Wilde said, “Ignorance is like a delicate exotic fruit; touch it and the bloom is gone.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s actually a surprisingly deep statement. The delicacy, the fragility, is what &lt;em&gt;makes&lt;/em&gt; it ignorance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why is it bad to try to be ignorant?  Well, “bad” may be the wrong word for it, but by our earlier definition of “suffering”, it &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; suffering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you &lt;em&gt;already&lt;/em&gt; predict that some new discovery will ruin your desired mental state, and therefore that you must not look over there, then you already have something in your field of consciousness that is ruining or conflicting with your desired mental state.  But you’re trying to believe that it’s not &lt;em&gt;yet&lt;/em&gt; ruining anything, so long as you don’t look at it. That’s having an internal contradiction and trying not to resolve it. That’s suffering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If there’s anything in the world that you &lt;em&gt;remember&lt;/em&gt; not to pay attention to because it’ll upset you – let’s say you never read anything by a particular author – then, at the moment you choose to look away from the upsetting thing, you &lt;em&gt;already&lt;/em&gt; have a thing that upsets you. The upsetting thing may not be, itself, the actual author you choose not to read; it may be your memory or impression of that author, or a thought you had once while reading that author, or something else. But if you are capable of thinking “ew, I won’t read that, it’ll just upset me” then you &lt;em&gt;have a thing that upsets you right now.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But you are &lt;em&gt;confused&lt;/em&gt; about how your mind works, and you think that you are actually &lt;em&gt;sparing&lt;/em&gt; yourself upset by avoiding the author.  You think that this state you’re in now – where you’re going “ew, that’ll upset me” – is what not being upset feels like.  But you’re wrong! This is actually an upset state.  This is a state of internal conflict, RIGHT NOW.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That doesn’t mean the “right” (anti-suffering) thing to do is to push through and read the article anyway.  The “right” thing to do would be to interrogate your &lt;em&gt;current&lt;/em&gt; state of upset or inner conflict, see what’s going on there, try to resolve or dissolve it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, you don’t always have time to do that in practice; it takes time to “untangle” your thoughts, and if you untangled literally everything as it came up, you’d be spending a colossal amount of time in silent contemplation, and sometimes life wants us to respond faster than that. Although I suspect that perhaps if you actually did that colossal amount of contemplation, you’d eventually get faster at the untangling process, and also get rid of the “backlog” of unresolved inner conflicts you’re carrying around, so that afterwards you could deal with the world more or less in real time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is what’s going on when we suffer. We think we are avoiding things that could hurt us, but we are actually &lt;em&gt;already&lt;/em&gt; hurting, and stubbornly refusing to salve our present hurts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Noticing More&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The macho/stoic “just lean into the discomfort” thing is exactly the reverse of this cognitive-resolution perspective. It sounds similar, in that it also says “avoidance and denial is bad”, but it’s going in exactly the opposite direction.  It says to &lt;em&gt;override&lt;/em&gt; your sensitivities, rather than to become &lt;em&gt;so much more&lt;/em&gt; sensitive that you notice and fix the subtler aversions that come &lt;em&gt;before&lt;/em&gt; whatever you’re currently avoiding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you get good at noticing the subtle stuff, you’ll see that there are specific, discrete, but kinda…stupid? mental objects that are present in your mind.  They’re “stupid” in that, they’re usually nonverbal, and they’re kind of like the cells in DeepDream, they’re sort of shaped like one &lt;em&gt;component&lt;/em&gt; of a sense memory. “The way this shadow of a roof beam fell across the room one time on a middle school retreat in the woods, and the sharp smell of bug spray, and the way I had a vague sense of being unprepared to deal with physically challenging activities and being creeped out by the Evangelical Christian mottoes everywhere.”  Except that’s one single “note”, one brain-phenomenon, and it gets activated when I think about “why do I feel resistant to doing physically uncomfortable things like jumping into freezing cold water?”  I feel like “but ugh, [THIS]” where THIS is the roof-beam-shadow-in-the-lodge thought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s how a big chunk of thoughts are &lt;em&gt;actually shaped&lt;/em&gt;, at least in my experience; we may just not talk about them because it sounds too weird.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I wonder sometimes if dealing with the “associative receptor field” or “emotional-sense-memory basis element” level of thought is actually what needs to happen to resolve a bunch of stuff and actually know what your mind is doing and reprogram it if you want.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For instance.  Why am I not going out for a run today? Well, I have a &lt;em&gt;memory&lt;/em&gt; – a snapshot sense-memory – of one time five years ago when I tried going out for a run when I was out of shape, and I was really embarrassed and humiliated; my throat was burning and I was almost in tears.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Would I feel that same way if I went running now? I don’t know. The road outside my door today looks different than that road in New Haven, the weather is different, I’m different, so maybe my experience will be different.  Intellectually that seems clear. But the loudest “note” in my mind is that full-body memory of it sucking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I really think the &lt;em&gt;mechanics&lt;/em&gt; of why I’m not making the decision to go for that run are at the “evoked full-body memory” level of granularity.  It seems kind of…arrogant? to think I can just detect that; outside view, nobody is very good at understanding their “subconscious”, and fake-epiphanies where people think they can intentionally rewrite “subconscious” patterns (but they actually can’t) are a dime a dozen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I don’t have the sense that I have mastered self-reprogramming, at all; I just have the sense that I know &lt;em&gt;where my decisions are coming from&lt;/em&gt;, and they’re these memory-fragments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, a thing is obviously not “subconscious” if you can &lt;em&gt;literally experience it in consciousness.&lt;/em&gt; I suspect that a lot of what people call “subconscious” is totally available to attention, just stuff that we expect ourselves not to attend to, especially because we don’t normally talk to &lt;em&gt;other&lt;/em&gt; people about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Could it be that attending to &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; internal phenomena is actually a “spiritual path” or a “self-improvement path” or whatever? There’s &lt;em&gt;so&lt;/em&gt; much more attention paid to overriding internal phenomena than exploring them; maybe most people know something I don’t, or maybe there’s a really persistent bias in the world of psychological advice.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="cog-psych" /><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How Effective is Non-Invasive Ventilation in COVID-19?</title><link href="https://srconstantin.github.io/2020/03/22/non-invasive-ventilation.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How Effective is Non-Invasive Ventilation in COVID-19?" /><published>2020-03-22T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-03-22T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://srconstantin.github.io/2020/03/22/non-invasive-ventilation</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://srconstantin.github.io/2020/03/22/non-invasive-ventilation.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/totalfacemask.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;cpapman&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Does non-invasive ventilation even work in critically ill COVID-19 patients?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last post in this blog discussed whether non-invasive ventilation (NIV) can be effective in acute respiratory failure for any cause, and examined only randomized controlled trials of the intervention.  But is COVID-19 different?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There aren’t any controlled experimental trials of non-invasive ventilation for COVID-19 or related coronaviruses, so for this post we’ve had to look at retrospective observational studies. The evidence is weaker here. But it still looks like NIV can be helpful, at least in a large fraction of cases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;COVID-19: Experiences&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a retrospective analysis of 191 patients with confirmed COVID-19 in two hospitals in Wuhan, China, 41 received high-flow nasal cannula oxygen therapy; 33 (80%) of those died. 26 patients received non-invasive mechanical ventilation; 24 (92%) of those died. Finally, 32 received invasive mechanical ventilation; 31 (97%) of those died.  This was not a statistically significant difference between the survival rates of different respiratory support techniques.[1]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a retrospective study of 60 severe COVID-19 patients from Jiangsu Province, China, 16 patients (26.7%) had respiratory failure. 14 patients received non-invasive mechanical ventilation (NIV), 15 received high-flow nasal cannula (HFNC), 6 received both NIV and HFNC, and 3 received invasive mechanical ventilation.  14 (93%) of the HFNC patients improved; 9 (64%) of the NIV patients improved; this is not a statistically significant difference.  3 patients needed invasive mechanical ventilation; the paper did not list which therapies they had previously failed.[2]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A retrospective on 631 patients in Jiangsu Province, China, reports that they were able to keep the rate of invasive mechanical ventilation under 1%, far below the Chinese average, despite a 10% rate of critically ill patients, by continuously monitoring high-risk patients and placing them on NIV or HFNC.[3]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a retrospective of 53 critically ill COVID-19 patients from Wuhan, 33 were treated with HFNC and 52% survived; 29 were placed on NIV and 26% survived; and 22 were placed on invasive ventilation and 14% survived.  Of those placed on NIV, 48% had to be placed on invasive ventilation.[4]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a preliminary (not-peer-reviewed) retrospective of 45 critically ill patients from Guangdong Province, China, with COVID-19, 6 (13.3%) were treated with standard oxygen therapy, 13 (28.9%) were treated with HNFC, 6 (13.3%) with NIV (all on a BiPAP), and 20 (44.4%) with invasive mechanical ventilation. Only one patient (2.2%) died in this cohort, compared to 62% in Wuhan. No patients treated with non-invasive oxygen therapies needed to be intubated.[5]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a retrospective study of 267 confirmed COVID-19 patients from Chongqing Municipality, China, 5 patients received invasive mechanical ventilation, 35 received non-invasive ventilation, 12 received HFNC, and 91 patients received standard oxygen therapy.  4 (1.5%) patients died in the entire study. All 50 patients with severe disease received oxygen, and all 50 needed further respiratory therapy; 2/35, or 5.7%, of patients on non-invasive ventilation needed to be intubated.[6]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusions Based on COVID-19 Published Data&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There have been no controlled studies of non-invasive ventilation for COVID-19.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a total of 70 COVID-19 patients, from three Chinese studies, treated with non-invasive ventilation, 23% needed to be intubated.  This is well within the range of failure of NIV for other causes of acute respiratory failure, and leaves it as an option that can still work in the majority of cases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a total of 90 patients treated with HFNC, 56% died; in a total of 69 patients treated with NIV, 72% died; in a total of 54 patients treated with invasive ventilation, 93% died.  There is no statistically significant difference in the death rates between groups. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The WHO’s clinical guidelines [7] on the use of NIV and HFNC in COVID-19 are as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;High-flow nasal oxygen (HFNO) should only be used in selected patients with hypoxemic respiratory failure. &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Non-invasive ventilation (NIV) should only be used in selected patients with hypoxemic respiratory failure.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;em&gt;Patients treated with either HFNO or NIV should be closely monitored for clinical deterioration. &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Remark 1: Adult HFNO systems can deliver 60 L/min of gas flow and FiO2 up to 1.0. Paediatric circuits generally only handle up to 25 L/min, and many children will require an adult circuit to deliver adequate flow.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Remark 2: Due to uncertainty around the potential for aerosolization, HFO, NIV, including bubble CPAP, should be used with airborne precautions until further evaluation of the safety can be completed.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Remark 3: Compared with standard oxygen therapy, HFNO reduces the need for intubation (42). Patients with hypercapnia (exacerbation of obstructive lung disease, cardiogenic pulmonary oedema), hemodynamic instability, multiorgan failure, or abnormal mental status should generally not receive HFNO, although emerging data suggest that HFNO may be safe in patients with mild-moderate and non-worsening hypercapnia (42, 43, 44). Patients receiving HFNO should be in a monitored setting and cared for by experienced personnel capable of endotracheal intubation in case the patient acutely deteriorates or does not improve after a short trial (about 1 hour). Evidence-based guidelines on HFNO do not exist, and reports on HFNO in other coronavirus-infected patients are limited (44).&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not much is known about the use of NIV and HFNO in COVID-19.  If possible, patients being given these therapies should be monitored in case they fail and the patient needs to be urgently intubated. However, what little evidence we have is in line with the results from other severe pulmonary diseases like pneumonia: in a majority of cases, non-invasive respiratory therapy can suffice and invasive mechanical ventilation can be avoided.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SARS&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Among 1512 patients with SARS in Guangdong Province, China, there were 58 deaths, for a case fatality rate of 3.8%, the lowest in the world. The author attributes this success to prompt treatment with corticosteroids and, in 20-30% of cases, with non-invasive ventilation (usually with a CPAP mask.)[8]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a Hong Kong case series of SARS patients, non-invasive ventilation was reported to be able to avoid intubation in ⅔ of patients.[9]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a retrospective study of two hospitals in Hong Kong, one which used non-invasive ventilation with a BiPAP and one which only used invasive ventilation for SARS, 21.4% out of 42 patients needed to be intubated at the NIV hospital compared to 41.2% out of 451 patients at the invasive-ventilation hospital, a significant (p = 0.012) reduction in the need for intubation.  Also, the mortality rate was lower (9.5% vs 25.1%, p = 0.024) in the NIV hospital. Only 8/21 (38%) of NIV-treated patients needed to be intubated.  No healthcare workers acquired SARS at the NIV hospital.[10]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a meta-analysis of 4 studies comprising 96 SARS patients treated with NIV, the non-invasive ventilation treatment failed in a total of 51 patients, or 53%.[11]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; In 17 studies of patients with H1N1 influenza comprising 551 patients treated with NIV, 338 or 61% failed the treatment.  The paper summarizes the use of NIV in H1N1 as follows: “NIV has a role in the management of early respiratory failure due to pH1N1 infection; however, in a strictly controlled environment with close monitoring of healthcare workers and with adequate precautions for prevention of infection transmission. NIV has no role in severe respiratory failure and ARDS related to severe pH1N1 infection.” [11]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;MERS&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 32 critically ill healthcare workers with MERS, 13 received NIV and 26 received invasive ventilation; that is, 7/13, or 54%, of patients treated with NIV failed and needed to be intubated. [12] &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In COVID-19 and in other coronavirus epidemics (SARS and MERS), non-invasive ventilation significantly reduces the need for intubation. In the case of SARS, NIV has been shown to significantly reduce mortality as well. In these viruses, NIV has high failure rates – 20-60%, depending on the disease – so ideally it should be closely monitored in case the patient needs to be intubated. However, NIV succeeds often enough that it makes sense to use it for critically ill patients when invasive ventilation is not an option. (Some patients have a Do Not Intubate order, for instance.)  We don’t know much yet about how well it works in COVID-19, and there are no randomized studies, but from what little evidence we have, it seems that there’s a sizable proportion of patients who can benefit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;References&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[1]Zhou, Fei, et al. “Clinical course and risk factors for mortality of adult inpatients with COVID-19 in Wuhan, China: a retrospective cohort study.” The Lancet (2020).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[2]Wu, Jian, et al. “Clinical characteristics of imported cases of COVID-19 in Jiangsu province: a multicenter descriptive study.” Clinical Infectious Diseases (2020).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[3]Sun, Qin, et al. “Lower mortality of COVID-19 by early recognition and intervention: experience from Jiangsu Province.” Annals of Intensive Care 10.1 (2020): 1-4.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[4]Yang, Xiaobo, et al. “Clinical course and outcomes of critically ill patients with SARS-CoV-2 pneumonia in Wuhan, China: a single-centered, retrospective, observational study.” The Lancet Respiratory Medicine (2020).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[5]Xu, Yonghao, et al. “Clinical findings in critical ill patients infected with SARS-Cov-2 in Guangdong Province, China: a multi-center, retrospective, observational study.” medRxiv (2020).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[6]Yang, Xiaobo, et al. “Clinical course and outcomes of critically ill patients with SARS-CoV-2 pneumonia in Wuhan, China: a single-centered, retrospective, observational study.” The Lancet Respiratory Medicine (2020).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[7]World Health Organization. Clinical management of severe acute respiratory infection (SARI) when COVID-19 disease is suspected: interim guidance, 13 March 2020. No. WHO/2019-nCoV/clinical/2020.4. World Health Organization, 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[8]Zhong, Nanshan. “Management and prevention of SARS in China.” Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society of London. Series B: Biological Sciences 359.1447 (2004): 1115-1116.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[9]Yam, Loretta Yc, Rong Chang Chen, and Nan Shan Zhong. “SARS: ventilatory and intensive care.” Respirology 8 (2003): S31-S35.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[10]Yam, L. Y., et al. “Non-invasive versus invasive mechanical ventilation for respiratory failure in severe acute respiratory syndrome.” Chin Med J 118.17 (2005): 1413-1421.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[11]Esquinas, Antonio M., et al. “Noninvasive mechanical ventilation in high-risk pulmonary infections: a clinical review.” European Respiratory Review 23.134 (2014): 427-438.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[12]Shalhoub, Sarah, et al. “Critically ill healthcare workers with the middle east respiratory syndrome (MERS): A multicenter study.” PloS one 13.11 (2018).&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="covid-19" /><category term="lit-review" /><summary type="html"></summary></entry></feed>